<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<algorithms version="110505">
<algorithm name="ParsCit" version="110505">
<citationList>
<citation valid="false">
<authors>
<author>D BOURIGAULT</author>
<author>C JACQUEMIN</author>
</authors>
<title>Construction des ressources terminologiques,</title>
<date>2000</date>
<journal>Journal of Society for Information Science,</journal>
<booktitle>In Ingénierie des langues »,</booktitle>
<volume>41</volume>
<pages>215--230</pages>
<editor>ed. J.M. Pierrel. Hermes Sciences DEERWESTER S., DUMAIS S., FURNAS G., LANDAUER T., HARSHMAN R.</editor>
<marker>BOURIGAULT, JACQUEMIN, 2000</marker>
<rawString>BOURIGAULT D., JACQUEMIN C. (2000): « Construction des ressources terminologiques, In Ingénierie des langues », pp 215-230, 2000, ed. J.M. Pierrel. Hermes Sciences DEERWESTER S., DUMAIS S., FURNAS G., LANDAUER T., HARSHMAN R. (1990): « Indexing by Latent Semantic Analysis », Journal of Society for Information Science, Vol.41, n.6, pp. 391-407, 1990 DUMAIS S., LETSCHE T., LITTMAN M., LANDAUER T. (1996): « Automatic Cross-Language Retrieval using Latent Semantic Indexing », SigIR Multilingual IR Workshop, Aug. 22, 1996 FARAJ N., GODIN R., MISSAOUI R., DAVID S., PLANTE P. (1996): « Analyse d’une méthode d’indexation automatique basée sur une analyse syntaxique de texte », Canadian Journal of Information and Library Science / Revue l’information et de bibliothéconomie, 1996 HUSBANDS P., SIMON H., DING H. (1996): « On the use of Singular Value Decomposition for Text Retrieval », Proceeding’s of SIAM Comp. Information Retrieval Workshop, 2000.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>P SEGUELA</author>
</authors>
<title>Construction de modèles de connaissances par analyse linguistique de relations lexicales dans les documents techniques,</title>
<date>2001</date>
<journal>France SINGHAL A., SALTON G., BUCKLEY C.</journal>
<booktitle>Proceedings of Fifth Annual Symposium on Document Analysis and Information Retrieval,</booktitle>
<pages>149--162</pages>
<marker>SEGUELA, 2001</marker>
<rawString>SEGUELA P. (2001): Construction de modèles de connaissances par analyse linguistique de relations lexicales dans les documents techniques, 2001, Université Toulouse III, France SINGHAL A., SALTON G., BUCKLEY C. (1996): « Length normalization in degraded text collections», Proceedings of Fifth Annual Symposium on Document Analysis and Information Retrieval, April 15-17, 1996, pp. 149-162.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>M SILBERZTEIN</author>
</authors>
<date>2001</date>
<booktitle>Intex @ manual , 2000-2001. ASSTRIL - LADL, 201p</booktitle>
<marker>SILBERZTEIN, 2001</marker>
<rawString>SILBERZTEIN,M. (2001), Intex @ manual , 2000-2001. ASSTRIL - LADL, 201p</rawString>
</citation>
</citationList>
</algorithm>
</algorithms>