<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<algorithms version="110505">
<algorithm name="ParsCit" version="110505">
<citationList>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>R BEESLEY</author>
</authors>
<title>Xerox Arabic Morphological Analysis and Generation Romanization, Transcription and Transliteration.</title>
<date>2005</date>
<marker>BEESLEY, 2005</marker>
<rawString>BEESLEY, R. (2005). Xerox Arabic Morphological Analysis and Generation Romanization, Transcription and Transliteration.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>T BUCKWALTER</author>
</authors>
<title>Buckwalter Arabic Morphological Analyser Version 2.0.</title>
<date>2004</date>
<booktitle>Linguistic Data Consortium (LDC) Catalog Number LDC2004L02, ISBN</booktitle>
<pages>1--58563</pages>
<marker>BUCKWALTER, 2004</marker>
<rawString>BUCKWALTER, T. (2004). Buckwalter Arabic Morphological Analyser Version 2.0. Linguistic Data Consortium (LDC) Catalog Number LDC2004L02, ISBN 1-58563-324-0.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>F et ACHOUR DEBILI</author>
<author>H</author>
</authors>
<title>Voyellation automatique de l’arabe.</title>
<date>1998</date>
<booktitle>Actes du Workshop on Computational Approaches To Semitic Languages, Université de Montréal.</booktitle>
<marker>DEBILI, H, 1998</marker>
<rawString>DEBILI, F. et ACHOUR, H. (1998). Voyellation automatique de l’arabe. Actes du Workshop on Computational Approaches To Semitic Languages, Université de Montréal.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>F et SOUISSI DEBILI</author>
<author>E</author>
</authors>
<title>Etiquetage grammatical de l’arabe voyellé ou non.</title>
<date>1998</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the Workshop on Computational Approaches to Semetic Languages,</booktitle>
<location>Stroudsburg.</location>
<marker>DEBILI, E, 1998</marker>
<rawString>DEBILI, F. et SOUISSI, E. (1998). Etiquetage grammatical de l’arabe voyellé ou non. In Proceedings of the Workshop on Computational Approaches to Semetic Languages, Stroudsburg.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>F DEBILI</author>
<author>H et SOUISSI ACHOUR</author>
<author>E</author>
</authors>
<title>La langue arabe et l’ordinateur : de l’étiquetage grammatical à la voyellation automatique. Correspondances de l’IRMC,</title>
<date>2002</date>
<location>N°71, Tunis.</location>
<marker>DEBILI, ACHOUR, E, 2002</marker>
<rawString>DEBILI, F., ACHOUR, H. et SOUISSI, E. (2002). La langue arabe et l’ordinateur : de l’étiquetage grammatical à la voyellation automatique. Correspondances de l’IRMC, N°71, Tunis.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>N et OWEN HABASH</author>
<author>R</author>
</authors>
<title>Arabic Tokenization, Part-of-speech Tagging and Morphological Disambiguation in One Fell Swoop.</title>
<date>2005</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the Conference of the American Association for Computational Linguistics,</booktitle>
<location>New York.</location>
<marker>HABASH, R, 2005</marker>
<rawString>HABASH, N. et OWEN, R. (2005). Arabic Tokenization, Part-of-speech Tagging and Morphological Disambiguation in One Fell Swoop. In Proceedings of the Conference of the American Association for Computational Linguistics, New York.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>J HAJIC</author>
<author>F SMRZ</author>
<author>T et JIN BUCKWALTER</author>
<author>H</author>
</authors>
<title>Feature-Based Tagger of Approximations of Functional Arabic Morphology. Actes de la quatrième conférence sur les Treebanks et les théories linguistiques, Université de Barcelone.</title>
<date>2005</date>
<marker>HAJIC, SMRZ, BUCKWALTER, H, 2005</marker>
<rawString>HAJIC, J., SMRZ, F., BUCKWALTER, T. et JIN, H. (2005). Feature-Based Tagger of Approximations of Functional Arabic Morphology. Actes de la quatrième conférence sur les Treebanks et les théories linguistiques, Université de Barcelone.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>M MAAMOURI</author>
<author>A et BUCKWALTER BIES</author>
<author>T</author>
</authors>
<title>The Pen Arabic Treebank: Building a Large-Scale Annotated Arabic Corpus.</title>
<date>2004</date>
<booktitle>In EMAR Conference on Arabic Language Ressources</booktitle>
<marker>MAAMOURI, BIES, T, 2004</marker>
<rawString>MAAMOURI, M., BIES, A. et BUCKWALTER, T. (2004). The Pen Arabic Treebank: Building a Large-Scale Annotated Arabic Corpus. In EMAR Conference on Arabic Language Ressources and Tools, le Caire.</rawString>
</citation>
</citationList>
</algorithm>
</algorithms>