<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<algorithms version="110505">
<algorithm name="ParsCit" version="110505">
<citationList>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>ALMEIDA N M DE</author>
</authors>
<title>Methodic Grammar of the Portuguese Language (in Portuguese),</title>
<date>1988</date>
<location>São Paulo, Brazil, Saraiva.</location>
<marker>DE, 1988</marker>
<rawString>ALMEIDA N. M. DE (1988), Methodic Grammar of the Portuguese Language (in Portuguese), São Paulo, Brazil, Saraiva.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>L C CAGLIARI</author>
</authors>
<title>On the importance of the prosody in the description of grammatical events (in Portuguese), In:</title>
<date>1992</date>
<booktitle>ILARI, R. (org.) Grammar of the spoken Portuguese (in Portuguese), v.2.</booktitle>
<location>Campinas (SP), Brazil, Unicamp.</location>
<marker>CAGLIARI, 1992</marker>
<rawString>CAGLIARI L. C. (1992), On the importance of the prosody in the description of grammatical events (in Portuguese), In: ILARI, R. (org.) Grammar of the spoken Portuguese (in Portuguese), v.2. Campinas (SP), Brazil, Unicamp.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>E CAMPIONE</author>
<author>J VERONIS</author>
</authors>
<title>Etude des relations entre pauses et pontuations pour la synthèse de la parole à partir de texte.</title>
<date>2002</date>
<booktitle>Proceedings of Traitement Automatique des Langues Natureles (TALN 2002),</booktitle>
<pages>1--10</pages>
<location>Nancy, France,</location>
<marker>CAMPIONE, VERONIS, 2002</marker>
<rawString>CAMPIONE E., VERONIS J. (2002), Etude des relations entre pauses et pontuations pour la synthèse de la parole à partir de texte. Proceedings of Traitement Automatique des Langues Natureles (TALN 2002), Nancy, France, 1-10.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>C E FARACO</author>
<author>MOURA F M DE</author>
</authors>
<title>Grammar: phonetic and phonology, morphology, syntax, stylistic (in Portuguese),</title>
<date>1991</date>
<location>São Paulo, Brazil, Ática.</location>
<marker>FARACO, DE, 1991</marker>
<rawString>FARACO C. E., MOURA F. M. DE. (1991), Grammar: phonetic and phonology, morphology, syntax, stylistic (in Portuguese), São Paulo, Brazil, Ática.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>R MARIN</author>
<author>L AGUILAR</author>
<author>D CASACUBERTA</author>
</authors>
<title>Placing pauses in read Spanish : a model and an algorithm.Language Design,</title>
<date>2002</date>
<volume>4</volume>
<pages>46--66</pages>
<marker>MARIN, AGUILAR, CASACUBERTA, 2002</marker>
<rawString>MARIN R., AGUILAR L., CASACUBERTA D. (2002) Placing pauses in read Spanish : a model and an algorithm.Language Design, 4, 46-66.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>C MOLLICA</author>
</authors>
<title>Intervals between the silence and the speech and their representations in written text.</title>
<date>1993</date>
<booktitle>Cadernos de Letras (in Portuguese), no. 9, Rio de Janeiro,</booktitle>
<pages>143--149</pages>
<marker>MOLLICA, 1993</marker>
<rawString>MOLLICA C. (1993). Intervals between the silence and the speech and their representations in written text. Cadernos de Letras (in Portuguese), no. 9, Rio de Janeiro, 143-149.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>E PONTES</author>
</authors>
<title>The topic in the Brazilian Portuguese (in Portuguese),</title>
<date>1987</date>
<location>São Paulo, Brazil, Pontes.</location>
<marker>PONTES, 1987</marker>
<rawString>PONTES E. (1987) The topic in the Brazilian Portuguese (in Portuguese), São Paulo, Brazil, Pontes.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>I C SEARA</author>
</authors>
<title>Analysis acoustic-perceptual of nasality of the vowels in the Brazilian Portuguese.</title>
<date>2000</date>
<tech>PhD. Thesis</tech>
<institution>(in Portuguese), Federal University of Santa Catarina,</institution>
<location>Florianópolis, Brazil.</location>
<marker>SEARA, 2000</marker>
<rawString>SEARA I. C. (2000), Analysis acoustic-perceptual of nasality of the vowels in the Brazilian Portuguese. PhD. Thesis (in Portuguese), Federal University of Santa Catarina, Florianópolis, Brazil.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>I C SEARA</author>
<author>S G KAFKA</author>
<author>S KLEIN</author>
<author>R SEARA</author>
</authors>
<title>Vowel sound alternation of verbs and nouns of the Portuguese spoken in Brazil for application in text-to-speech synthesis.</title>
<date>2002</date>
<journal>Journal of the Brazilian Telecommunication Society (in Portuguese),</journal>
<volume>17</volume>
<pages>79--85</pages>
<marker>SEARA, KAFKA, KLEIN, SEARA, 2002</marker>
<rawString>SEARA I. C., KAFKA S. G., KLEIN S., SEARA R. (2002), Vowel sound alternation of verbs and nouns of the Portuguese spoken in Brazil for application in text-to-speech synthesis. Journal of the Brazilian Telecommunication Society (in Portuguese), vol. 17, no. 1, 79-85.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>E STRANGERT</author>
</authors>
<title>Speech chunks in conversation: Syntactic and prosodic aspects.</title>
<date>2004</date>
<booktitle>Proceedings of Speech Prosody,</booktitle>
<location>Nara, Japan.</location>
<marker>STRANGERT, 2004</marker>
<rawString>STRANGERT E. (2004), Speech chunks in conversation: Syntactic and prosodic aspects. Proceedings of Speech Prosody, Nara, Japan.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>G VANNIER</author>
<author>A LACHERET-DUJOUR</author>
<author>J VERGNE</author>
</authors>
<title>Pauses location and duration calculated with syntactic dependencies and textual considerations for T.T.S. system.</title>
<date>1999</date>
<booktitle>Proceedings of XIV International Congress of Phonetics Sciences (ICPhS),</booktitle>
<location>San Francisco, USA.</location>
<marker>VANNIER, LACHERET-DUJOUR, VERGNE, 1999</marker>
<rawString>VANNIER G., LACHERET-DUJOUR A., VERGNE J. (1999), Pauses location and duration calculated with syntactic dependencies and textual considerations for T.T.S. system. Proceedings of XIV International Congress of Phonetics Sciences (ICPhS), San Francisco, USA.</rawString>
</citation>
</citationList>
</algorithm>
</algorithms>