<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<algorithms version="110505">
<algorithm name="ParsCit" version="110505">
<citationList>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>C AMARAL</author>
<author>D LAURENT</author>
<author>A MARTINS</author>
<author>A MENDES</author>
<author>C PINTO</author>
</authors>
<title>Design &amp; Implementation of a Semantic Search Engine for Portuguese,</title>
<date>2004</date>
<booktitle>Proceedings of the Fourth Conference on Language Resources and Evaluation.</booktitle>
<marker>AMARAL, LAURENT, MARTINS, MENDES, PINTO, 2004</marker>
<rawString>AMARAL C., LAURENT D., MARTINS A., MENDES A., PINTO C. (2004), Design &amp; Implementation of a Semantic Search Engine for Portuguese, Proceedings of the Fourth Conference on Language Resources and Evaluation.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>C L A CLARKE</author>
<author>G V CORMACK</author>
<author>T R LYNAM</author>
</authors>
<title>Exploiting Redundancy in Question Answering,</title>
<date>2001</date>
<booktitle>Proceedings of 24th Annual International ACM SIGIR Conference (SIGIR</booktitle>
<pages>358--365</pages>
<marker>CLARKE, CORMACK, LYNAM, 2001</marker>
<rawString>CLARKE C. L. A., CORMACK G. V., LYNAM T. R. (2001), Exploiting Redundancy in Question Answering, Proceedings of 24th Annual International ACM SIGIR Conference (SIGIR 2001), p. 358-365.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>B GRAU</author>
</authors>
<title>L&apos;évaluation des systemes de question-réponse, Evaluation des syste‘mes de traitement de l &apos;information, TSTI,</title>
<date>2004</date>
<pages>77--98</pages>
<publisher>Lavoisier.</publisher>
<contexts>
<context position="12755" citStr="GRAU 2004" startWordPosition="1874" endWordPosition="1875">istiques des entités nommées ou sur la base de nature syntaxique des groupes ou propositions. Pour une question sur un corpus ferrné, le temps de réponse est d&apos;enViron 3 secondes avec un Pentium 3 GHz. Sur le Web, les premieres réponses sont généralement foumies au bout de 2 secondes, un afﬁnage progressif ayant lieu et pouvant durer jusqu&apos;a une quinzaine de secondes, selon le paramétrage utilisateur (nombre de moteurs, nombre de pages analysées, etc.) 3 Evaluation EQueR QRISTAL a été évalué dans le cadre d&apos;EQueR, campagne d’éValuation des systemes de Questions-Réponses du projet EVALDA (voir GRAU 2004). Le projet EVALDA et, plus généralement, les projets Technolangue, ont été initiés par les Ministeres francais de l’Industrie, de la Recherche et de la Culture. La campagne EQueR a été organisée par l’ELDA (Evaluations and Language resources Distribution Agency, www.elda.org) entre janvier 2003 et décembre 2004. Tres similaire dans ses principes aux campagnes TREC-QA (USA) ou NTCIR (Japon), elle a pris la forme de deux tests distincts : Dominique Laurent, Patrick Séguéla 0 500 questions générales, principalement factuelles, sur un corpus journalistique et administratif de 1,5 Go. 0 200 questi</context>
</contexts>
<marker>GRAU, 2004</marker>
<rawString>GRAU B.. (2004), L&apos;évaluation des systemes de question-réponse, Evaluation des syste‘mes de traitement de l &apos;information, TSTI, p. 77-98, éd. Lavoisier.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>S HARABAGIU</author>
<author>D MOLDOVAN</author>
<author>C CLARK</author>
<author>M BOWDEN</author>
<author>J WILLIAMS</author>
<author>J BENSLEY</author>
</authors>
<title>Answer Mining by Combining Extraction Techniques with Abductive Reasoning,</title>
<date>2002</date>
<booktitle>Proceedings of The Twelfth Text Retrieval Conference (TREC</booktitle>
<marker>HARABAGIU, MOLDOVAN, CLARK, BOWDEN, WILLIAMS, BENSLEY, 2002</marker>
<rawString>HARABAGIU S., MOLDOVAN D., CLARK C., BOWDEN M., WILLIAMS J., BENSLEY J. (2002), Answer Mining by Combining Extraction Techniques with Abductive Reasoning, Proceedings of The Twelfth Text Retrieval Conference (TREC 2003).</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>D LAURENT</author>
<author>M VARONE</author>
<author>C AMARAL</author>
<author>P FUGLEWICZ</author>
</authors>
<title>Multilingual Semantic and Cognitive Search Engine for Text Retrieval Using Semantic Technologies,</title>
<date>2004</date>
<booktitle>First International Workshop on Prooﬁng Tools and Language Technologies,</booktitle>
<location>Patras, Gréce.</location>
<marker>LAURENT, VARONE, AMARAL, FUGLEWICZ, 2004</marker>
<rawString>LAURENT D., VARONE M., AMARAL C., FUGLEWICZ P. (2004), Multilingual Semantic and Cognitive Search Engine for Text Retrieval Using Semantic Technologies, First International Workshop on Prooﬁng Tools and Language Technologies, Patras, Gréce.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>B MAGNINI</author>
<author>M NEGRI</author>
<author>R PREVETE</author>
<author>H TANEV</author>
</authors>
<title>Is It the Right Answer? Exploiting Web Redundancy for Answer Validation,</title>
<date>2002</date>
<booktitle>Proceedings of the 40th Annual Meeting of the ACL,</booktitle>
<pages>425--432</pages>
<location>Amsterdam.</location>
<marker>MAGNINI, NEGRI, PREVETE, TANEV, 2002</marker>
<rawString>MAGNINI B., NEGRI M., PREVETE R., TANEV H. (2002), Is It the Right Answer? Exploiting Web Redundancy for Answer Validation, Proceedings of the 40th Annual Meeting of the ACL, p. 425-432 MONZ C. (2003), From Document Retrieval to Question Answering, ILLC Dissertation Series 2003-4, HLC, Amsterdam.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>E M VOORHEES</author>
</authors>
<title>Question Answering Track,</title>
<date>2003</date>
<journal>Overview of the TREC</journal>
<pages>proceedings.html).</pages>
<location>NIST,</location>
<marker>VOORHEES, 2003</marker>
<rawString>VOORHEES E. M.. (2003), Overview of the TREC 2003 Question Answering Track, NIST, 54-68 (http://trec.nist.gov/pubs/trec12/tl2 proceedings.html).</rawString>
</citation>
</citationList>
</algorithm>
</algorithms>