<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<algorithms version="110505">
<algorithm name="ParsCit" version="110505">
<citationList>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>G Ainsi</author>
</authors>
<title>Perrier a pu réutiliser cette méthode pour produire une grammaire d’interaction. Nous avons également mené quelques expériences encourageantes qui ont permis de créer une petite grammaire XDG du français. Références Anne Abeillé. (Abe02) Une grammaire d’arbres adjoints pour le français. CNRS,</title>
<date>2002</date>
<location>Paris,</location>
<marker>Ainsi, 2002</marker>
<rawString>ment lexicalisés. Ainsi, G. Perrier a pu réutiliser cette méthode pour produire une grammaire d’interaction. Nous avons également mené quelques expériences encourageantes qui ont permis de créer une petite grammaire XDG du français. Références Anne Abeillé. (Abe02) Une grammaire d’arbres adjoints pour le français. CNRS, Paris, 2002.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Tilman Becker</author>
</authors>
<title>(Bec93) HyTAG: A new Type of Tree Adjoining Grammars for Hybrid Syntactic Representation of Free Word Order Language.</title>
<date>1993</date>
<tech>PhD thesis,</tech>
<institution>Universität des Saarlandes,</institution>
<marker>Becker, 1993</marker>
<rawString>Tilman Becker. (Bec93) HyTAG: A new Type of Tree Adjoining Grammars for Hybrid Syntactic Representation of Free Word Order Language. PhD thesis, Universität des Saarlandes, 1993.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Marie-Hélène Candito</author>
</authors>
<title>(Can99) Organisation Modulaire et Paramétrable de Grammaires Electroniques Lexicalisées.</title>
<date>1999</date>
<tech>PhD thesis,</tech>
<institution>Université de Paris</institution>
<marker>Candito, 1999</marker>
<rawString>Marie-Hélène Candito. (Can99) Organisation Modulaire et Paramétrable de Grammaires Electroniques Lexicalisées. PhD thesis, Université de Paris 7, 1999.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Benoit Crabbé</author>
<author>Denys Duchier</author>
</authors>
<title>(CD04) Metagrammar redux.</title>
<date>2004</date>
<booktitle>In Constraint Solving and Language Processing,</booktitle>
<location>Copenhagen,</location>
<marker>Crabbé, Duchier, 2004</marker>
<rawString>Benoit Crabbé and Denys Duchier. (CD04) Metagrammar redux. In Constraint Solving and Language Processing, Copenhagen, 2004.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Denys Duchier</author>
<author>Joseph Leroux</author>
<author>Yannick Parmentier</author>
</authors>
<title>The metagrammar compiler: An nlp application with a multi-paradigm architecture. In Mozart</title>
<date></date>
<location>Charleroi,</location>
<marker>Duchier, Leroux, Parmentier, </marker>
<rawString>Denys Duchier, Joseph Leroux, and Yannick Parmentier. (DLP04) The metagrammar compiler: An nlp application with a multi-paradigm architecture. In Mozart 2004, Charleroi, 2004.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Bertrand Gaiffe</author>
</authors>
<title>Benoit Crabbé, and Azim Roussanaly. (GCR02) A new metagrammar compiler.</title>
<date>2002</date>
<booktitle>In Proc. TAG+6, Venise,</booktitle>
<marker>Gaiffe, 2002</marker>
<rawString>Bertrand Gaiffe, Benoit Crabbé, and Azim Roussanaly. (GCR02) A new metagrammar compiler. In Proc. TAG+6, Venise, 2002.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Claire Gardent</author>
<author>Laura Kallmeyer</author>
</authors>
<title>Semantic construction in feature-based tree adjoining grammar.</title>
<date></date>
<booktitle>In Proc. EACL,</booktitle>
<marker>Gardent, Kallmeyer, </marker>
<rawString>Claire Gardent and Laura Kallmeyer. (GK03) Semantic construction in feature-based tree adjoining grammar. In Proc. EACL, 2003.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Claire Gardent</author>
<author>Yannick Parmentier</author>
</authors>
<title>Large scale semantic construction for tree adjoining grammar.</title>
<date></date>
<booktitle>In Proc. LACL 2005,</booktitle>
<location>Bordeaux,</location>
<marker>Gardent, Parmentier, </marker>
<rawString>Claire Gardent and Yannick Parmentier. (GP05) Large scale semantic construction for tree adjoining grammar. In Proc. LACL 2005, Bordeaux, 2005.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Carlos Prolo</author>
</authors>
<title>(Pro02) Systematic grammar development in the XTAG project.</title>
<date>2002</date>
<booktitle>In COLING’02,</booktitle>
<marker>Prolo, 2002</marker>
<rawString>Carlos Prolo. (Pro02) Systematic grammar development in the XTAG project. In COLING’02, 2002.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Fei Xia</author>
</authors>
<title>(Xia01) Automatic Grammar Generation from two Different Perspectives.</title>
<date>2001</date>
<tech>PhD thesis,</tech>
<institution>University of Pennsylvania,</institution>
<marker>Xia, 2001</marker>
<rawString>Fei Xia. (Xia01) Automatic Grammar Generation from two Different Perspectives. PhD thesis, University of Pennsylvania, 2001.</rawString>
</citation>
</citationList>
</algorithm>
</algorithms>