<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<algorithms version="110505">
<algorithm name="ParsCit" version="110505">
<citationList>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>D BOURIGAULT</author>
<author>C JACQUEMIN</author>
</authors>
<date>2001</date>
<booktitle>Recent Advances in Computational Terminologies.</booktitle>
<location>Amsterdam/Philadelphia: John Benjamins.</location>
<marker>BOURIGAULT, JACQUEMIN, 2001</marker>
<rawString>BOURIGAULT, D., JACQUEMIN, C., et al. 2001. Recent Advances in Computational Terminologies. Amsterdam/Philadelphia: John Benjamins.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Y-C CHIAO</author>
<author>P ZWEIGENBAUM</author>
</authors>
<title>The effect of a general lexicon in corpus-based identification of French-English medical word translations. Actes</title>
<date>2003</date>
<location>MIE, Amsterdam:.</location>
<marker>CHIAO, ZWEIGENBAUM, 2003</marker>
<rawString>CHIAO, Y-C., ZWEIGENBAUM, P. 2003. The effect of a general lexicon in corpus-based identification of French-English medical word translations. Actes MIE, Amsterdam:.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>D CORBIN</author>
</authors>
<title>Morphologie dérivationnelle et structuration du lexique. Lille: PUL. 16 Merci au relecteur anonyme pour cette suggestion.</title>
<date>1987</date>
<marker>CORBIN, 1987</marker>
<rawString>CORBIN, D. 1987. Morphologie dérivationnelle et structuration du lexique. Lille: PUL. 16 Merci au relecteur anonyme pour cette suggestion.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Fiammetta Namer DAILLE</author>
<author>B</author>
</authors>
<title>L&apos;identification en corpus d&apos;adjectifs relationnels: une piste linguistique pour l&apos;extraction automatique de terminologie.</title>
<date>2001</date>
<booktitle>In T.A.L, 42/3,</booktitle>
<location>Paris, Hermès:815-832.</location>
<marker>DAILLE, B, 2001</marker>
<rawString>Fiammetta Namer DAILLE, B. 2001. L&apos;identification en corpus d&apos;adjectifs relationnels: une piste linguistique pour l&apos;extraction automatique de terminologie. In T.A.L, 42/3, Paris, Hermès:815-832.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>S J DARMONI</author>
<author>E JARROUSSE</author>
</authors>
<title>VumeF: Extending the French part of the UMLS.</title>
<date>2003</date>
<marker>DARMONI, JARROUSSE, 2003</marker>
<rawString>DARMONI, S. J., JARROUSSE, E., et al. 2003. VumeF: Extending the French part of the UMLS.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="false">
<authors>
<author>B FRADIN</author>
</authors>
<title>Combining forms, blends and related phenomena.</title>
<date></date>
<journal>Journal of AMIA</journal>
<booktitle>Proceedings of the AMIA Symposium,</booktitle>
<pages>7--310</pages>
<location>Washington,</location>
<marker>FRADIN, </marker>
<rawString>Proceedings of the AMIA Symposium, Washington, DC:824 FRADIN, B. 2000. Combining forms, blends and related phenomena. In Extragrammatical and Marginal Morphology, München: Lincom Europa: 11-59 GAUSSIER, E. 2001. General Considerations on Bilingual Terminology Extraction. In Recent Advances in Computational Terminology. Amsterdam/Philadelphia: John Benjamins: 167-184 GRABAR, N., ZWEIGENBAUM, P. 2000. A general method for sifting linguistic knowledge from structured terminologies. Journal of AMIA 7(suppl):310-314.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>U HAHN</author>
<author>M HONECK</author>
</authors>
<title>Subword segmentation: Leveling out morphological variations for medical document retrieval.</title>
<date>2001</date>
<journal>Journal of AMIA</journal>
<pages>8--229</pages>
<marker>HAHN, HONECK, 2001</marker>
<rawString>HAHN, U., HONECK, M., et al. 2001. Subword segmentation: Leveling out morphological variations for medical document retrieval. Journal of AMIA 8(suppl):229-233.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>M HASPELMATH</author>
</authors>
<title>Understanding Morphology.</title>
<date>2002</date>
<location>London: Arnold.</location>
<marker>HASPELMATH, 2002</marker>
<rawString>HASPELMATH, M. 2002. Understanding Morphology. London: Arnold.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>N HATHOUT</author>
</authors>
<title>L&apos;analogie, un moyen de croiser les contraintes et les paradigmes. Acquisition de connaissances à partir de dictionnaires de synonymes,</title>
<date>2003</date>
<pages>17--5</pages>
<marker>HATHOUT, 2003</marker>
<rawString>HATHOUT, N. 2003. L&apos;analogie, un moyen de croiser les contraintes et les paradigmes. Acquisition de connaissances à partir de dictionnaires de synonymes, RIA. 17(5-6),:923-934.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>C IACOBINI</author>
</authors>
<title>Composizione con elementi neoclassici. In La formazione delle parole in italiano,</title>
<date>2003</date>
<booktitle>In NLP and Information Retrieval,</booktitle>
<pages>25--74</pages>
<location>Tübingen: Niemeyer:</location>
<marker>IACOBINI, 2003</marker>
<rawString>IACOBINI, C. 2003. Composizione con elementi neoclassici. In La formazione delle parole in italiano, Tübingen: Niemeyer: 69-96 JACQUEMIN, C., TZOUKERMANN, E. 1999. NLP for term variant extraction: A synergy of morphology, lexicon, and syntax. In NLP and Information Retrieval, Boston, Kluwer: 25-74.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>C LOVIS</author>
<author>P A MICHEL</author>
</authors>
<title>Word segmentation processing: a way to exponentially extend medical dictionaries.</title>
<date>1995</date>
<booktitle>8th World Congress on Medical Informatics:</booktitle>
<pages>28--32</pages>
<marker>LOVIS, MICHEL, 1995</marker>
<rawString>LOVIS, C., MICHEL, P.A., et al. 1995. Word segmentation processing: a way to exponentially extend medical dictionaries. 8th World Congress on Medical Informatics: 28-32.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>C LOVIS</author>
<author>R BAUD</author>
</authors>
<title>Medical dictionaries for patient encoding systems: a methodology.</title>
<date>1998</date>
<journal>Artificial Intelligence in Medecine</journal>
<pages>14--201</pages>
<marker>LOVIS, BAUD, 1998</marker>
<rawString>LOVIS, C., BAUD, R., et al. 1998. Medical dictionaries for patient encoding systems: a methodology. Artificial Intelligence in Medecine 14:201-214.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>F NAMER</author>
</authors>
<title>Automatiser l&apos;analyse morpho-sémantique non affixale: le système DériF.</title>
<date>2003</date>
<booktitle>In Cahiers de Grammaire.</booktitle>
<pages>31--48</pages>
<location>Toulouse: ERSS:</location>
<marker>NAMER, 2003</marker>
<rawString>NAMER, F. 2003. Automatiser l&apos;analyse morpho-sémantique non affixale: le système DériF. In Cahiers de Grammaire. Toulouse: ERSS: 31-48.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>F NAMER</author>
<author>P ZWEIGENBAUM</author>
</authors>
<title>Acquiring meaning for French Medical Terminology: contribution of Morphosemantics.</title>
<date>2004</date>
<booktitle>in 11th MEDINFO.</booktitle>
<pages>535--539</pages>
<location>San Francisco,</location>
<marker>NAMER, ZWEIGENBAUM, 2004</marker>
<rawString>NAMER, F., ZWEIGENBAUM P., 2004 Acquiring meaning for French Medical Terminology: contribution of Morphosemantics. in 11th MEDINFO. 2004. San Francisco, CA:535-539.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>S SCHULZ</author>
<author>M ROMACKER</author>
</authors>
<title>Towards a multilingual morpheme thesaurus for medical free-text retrieval.</title>
<date>1999</date>
<booktitle>Proceedings of MIE,</booktitle>
<pages>891--894</pages>
<location>Ljubliana, Slovenia:</location>
<marker>SCHULZ, ROMACKER, 1999</marker>
<rawString>SCHULZ, S., ROMACKER, M., et al. 1999. Towards a multilingual morpheme thesaurus for medical free-text retrieval. Proceedings of MIE, Ljubliana, Slovenia: 891-894.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>T-D TRAN</author>
<author>A BURGUN</author>
</authors>
<title>Acquisition semi-automatique de terminologie bilingue en biologie moléculaire à partir des corpus comparables. TIA,</title>
<date>2003</date>
<booktitle>In Contemporary Morphology,</booktitle>
<pages>166--175</pages>
<location>Strasbourg:</location>
<marker>TRAN, BURGUN, 2003</marker>
<rawString>TRAN, T-D., BURGUN, A., et al. 2003. Acquisition semi-automatique de terminologie bilingue en biologie moléculaire à partir des corpus comparables. TIA, Strasbourg: 166-175 WARREN, B. 1990. The importance of combining forms. In Contemporary Morphology, Berlin, New York: Mouton - Walter de Gruyter: 111-132.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>P ZWEIGENBAUM</author>
<author>R BAUD</author>
</authors>
<title>Towards a unified medical lexicon for French. In Actes</title>
<date>2003</date>
<pages>415--420</pages>
<publisher>IOS Press:</publisher>
<location>MIE, Amsterdam:</location>
<marker>ZWEIGENBAUM, BAUD, 2003</marker>
<rawString>ZWEIGENBAUM, P., BAUD, R., et al.. 2003. Towards a unified medical lexicon for French. In Actes MIE, Amsterdam: IOS Press: 415-420.</rawString>
</citation>
</citationList>
</algorithm>
</algorithms>