<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<algorithms version="110505">
<algorithm name="ParsCit" version="110505">
<citationList>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>C ALOULOU</author>
</authors>
<title>Utilisation de l&apos;approche multi-critère pour orienter un processus de correction des erreurs d&apos;accord dans des phrases de la langue arabe non voyellée, Mémoire de DEA, Institut Supérieur de Gestion, Université de Tunis III.</title>
<date>1996</date>
<marker>ALOULOU, 1996</marker>
<rawString>ALOULOU C. (1996), Utilisation de l&apos;approche multi-critère pour orienter un processus de correction des erreurs d&apos;accord dans des phrases de la langue arabe non voyellée, Mémoire de DEA, Institut Supérieur de Gestion, Université de Tunis III.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>BEN HAMADOU A</author>
</authors>
<title>Vérification et correction automatique par analyse affixale des textes écrits en langue naturelle : le cas de l’arabe non voyellé, Thèse d’état en informatique, Faculté des Sciences de Tunis.</title>
<date>1993</date>
<marker>A, 1993</marker>
<rawString>BEN HAMADOU A. (1993), Vérification et correction automatique par analyse affixale des textes écrits en langue naturelle : le cas de l’arabe non voyellé, Thèse d’état en informatique, Faculté des Sciences de Tunis.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>BEN OTHMANE ZRIBI C</author>
</authors>
<title>De la synthèse lexicographique à la détection et à la correction des graphies fautives arabes, Thèse de doctorat, Université de</title>
<date>1998</date>
<location>Paris XI, Orsay.</location>
<marker>C, 1998</marker>
<rawString>BEN OTHMANE ZRIBI C. (1998), De la synthèse lexicographique à la détection et à la correction des graphies fautives arabes, Thèse de doctorat, Université de Paris XI, Orsay.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>BEN OTHMANE ZRIBI C et BEN AHMED M</author>
</authors>
<title>Le contexte au service de la correction des graphies fautives arabes, TALN&apos;03,</title>
<date>2003</date>
<location>Nantes.</location>
<marker>M, 2003</marker>
<rawString>BEN OTHMANE ZRIBI C. et BEN AHMED M. (2003), Le contexte au service de la correction des graphies fautives arabes, TALN&apos;03, Nantes.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>J BIGERT</author>
<author>O KNUTSSON</author>
</authors>
<title>Robust Error Detection : A Hybrid Approach Combining Unsupervised Error Detection and Linguistic Knowledge,</title>
<date>2002</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of Robust Methods in Analysis of Natural Language Data (ROMAND’02),</booktitle>
<location>Frascati, Italie.</location>
<marker>BIGERT, KNUTSSON, 2002</marker>
<rawString>BIGERT J., KNUTSSON O. (2002), Robust Error Detection : A Hybrid Approach Combining Unsupervised Error Detection and Linguistic Knowledge, In Proceedings of Robust Methods in Analysis of Natural Language Data (ROMAND’02), Frascati, Italie.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>F DEBILI</author>
<author>H ACHOUR</author>
<author>E SOUISSI</author>
</authors>
<title>La langue arabe et l&apos;ordinateur: De l&apos;étiquetage grammatical à la voyellation automatique,</title>
<date>2002</date>
<booktitle>Correspondances N°71,</booktitle>
<location>Lyon.</location>
<marker>DEBILI, ACHOUR, SOUISSI, 2002</marker>
<rawString>DEBILI F., ACHOUR H., SOUISSI E. (2002), La langue arabe et l&apos;ordinateur: De l&apos;étiquetage grammatical à la voyellation automatique, Correspondances N°71, Lyon.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>A R GOLDING</author>
</authors>
<title>A bayesian hybrid method for context- sensitive spelling correction,</title>
<date>1995</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the Third Workshop on Very Large Corpora,</booktitle>
<pages>39--53</pages>
<location>Cambridge, Massachusetts, USA,</location>
<marker>GOLDING, 1995</marker>
<rawString>GOLDING A. R. (1995), A bayesian hybrid method for context- sensitive spelling correction, In Proceedings of the Third Workshop on Very Large Corpora, Cambridge, Massachusetts, USA, pages 39-53.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>A R GOLDING</author>
<author>Y SCHABES</author>
</authors>
<title>Combining trigram-based and feature-based methods for context-Sensitive Spelling Correction, ACL’96,</title>
<date>1996</date>
<location>San Fransisco.</location>
<marker>GOLDING, SCHABES, 1996</marker>
<rawString>GOLDING A. R., SCHABES Y. (1996), Combining trigram-based and feature-based methods for context-Sensitive Spelling Correction, ACL’96, San Fransisco.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>A R GOLDING</author>
<author>R DAN</author>
</authors>
<title>A winnow-based approach to context-sensitive spelling correction,</title>
<date>1999</date>
<booktitle>Machine Learning,</booktitle>
<volume>34</volume>
<issue>1</issue>
<pages>107--130</pages>
<marker>GOLDING, DAN, 1999</marker>
<rawString>GOLDING A. R., DAN R., (1999), A winnow-based approach to context-sensitive spelling correction, Machine Learning, 34(1-3), 107-130.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>S VERBERNE</author>
</authors>
<title>Context sensitive spell checking based on word trigram probabilities, Mémoire de Mastère, Université de Nijmegen.</title>
<date>2002</date>
<marker>VERBERNE, 2002</marker>
<rawString>VERBERNE S. (2002), Context sensitive spell checking based on word trigram probabilities, Mémoire de Mastère, Université de Nijmegen.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>W XIAOLONG</author>
<author>L JIANHUA</author>
</authors>
<title>Combine trigram and automatic weight distribution in Chinese spelling error correction,</title>
<date>2001</date>
<journal>Journal of computer Science and Technology, Volume</journal>
<volume>17</volume>
<location>Province,</location>
<marker>XIAOLONG, JIANHUA, 2001</marker>
<rawString>XIAOLONG W., JIANHUA L. (2001), Combine trigram and automatic weight distribution in Chinese spelling error correction, Journal of computer Science and Technology, Volume 17 Issue 6, Province, China.</rawString>
</citation>
</citationList>
</algorithm>
</algorithms>