<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<algorithms version="110505">
<algorithm name="ParsCit" version="110505">
<citationList>
<citation valid="false">
<authors>
<author>S AÏT-MOKTAR</author>
<author>J-P CHANOD</author>
<author>C ROUX</author>
</authors>
<title>Robustness beyond shallowness : incremental deep parsing, Natural Language Engineering Journal,</title>
<date>2002</date>
<booktitle>Proceedings of VEXTAL’99 , Venise</booktitle>
<pages>81--86</pages>
<location>Chemnitz, Germany</location>
<marker>AÏT-MOKTAR, CHANOD, ROUX, 2002</marker>
<rawString>AÏT-MOKTAR S., CHANOD J.-P, ROUX C. (2002), Robustness beyond shallowness : incremental deep parsing, Natural Language Engineering Journal, 8(2/3):121-147 BASILI R., PAZIENZA M.-T., VINDIGNI M. (1999), Adaptative Parsing and Lexical Learning, Proceedings of VEXTAL’99 , Venise BASILI R., VINDIGNI M. (1998), Adapting a Subcategorization Lexicon to a Domain, Proceedings of the ECML98 Workshop TANLPS, Chemnitz, Germany BOURIGAULT D. (1993), An endogenous Corpus Based Method for Structural Noun Phrase Disambiguation, In Proceedings of the 6th Conference of the European Chapter of ACL (EACL), pp. 81-86, Utrecht, The Netherlands BOURIGAULT D., FABRE C. (2000), Approche linguistique pour l’analyse syntaxique de corpus, Cahiers de Grammaire, 25, Université Toulouse le Mirail, pp. 131-151 CHARNIAK E. (1997), Statistical Parsing with a Contexte-Free Grammar and Word Statistics.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<title>Groupes prépositionnels arguments ou circonstants : vers un repérage automatique en corpus.</title>
<date>2002</date>
<journal>Rhode Island, pp.598-603 FABRE C., FRÉROT C</journal>
<booktitle>Proceedings of the AAAI97 Conference,</booktitle>
<pages>215--224</pages>
<institution>Browne University,</institution>
<marker>2002</marker>
<rawString>Proceedings of the AAAI97 Conference, Browne University, Rhode Island, pp.598-603 FABRE C., FRÉROT C (2002), Groupes prépositionnels arguments ou circonstants : vers un repérage automatique en corpus. Actes de la Conférence TALN, pp. 215-224.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="false">
<authors>
<author>C FRÉROT</author>
</authors>
<title>Etude en corpus variés sur l’intégration de ressources linguistiques générales dans un analyseur syntaxique, Thèse en sciences du langage de l’Université Toulouse le Mirail</title>
<date>2005</date>
<journal>Computational Linguistics,</journal>
<booktitle>in Proceedings of the 2001 Conference on Empirical Methods in Natural Language Processing,</booktitle>
<volume>29</volume>
<pages>167--202</pages>
<editor>D. Bourigault, C. Frérot FRÉROT C., BOURIGAULT D., FABRE C.</editor>
<publisher>Morgan Kaufmann</publisher>
<location>Hillsdale, N.J.,</location>
<marker>FRÉROT, 2005</marker>
<rawString>FRÉROT C. (2005), Etude en corpus variés sur l’intégration de ressources linguistiques générales dans un analyseur syntaxique, Thèse en sciences du langage de l’Université Toulouse le Mirail D. Bourigault, C. Frérot FRÉROT C., BOURIGAULT D., FABRE C. (2003), Marier apprentissage endogène et ressources exogènes dans un analyseur syntaxique de corpus. Le cas du rattachement verbal à distance de la préposition « de », in Revue t.a.l., 44-3 GALA PAVIA N. (2003), Un modèle d’analyseur syntaxique robuste basé sur la modularité et la lexicalisation de ses grammaires, PhD, University of Paris XI, Orsay GILDEA D. (2001), Corpus Variation and Parser Performance. In Lillian Lee and Donna Harma, editors, in Proceedings of the 2001 Conference on Empirical Methods in Natural Language Processing, pp. 167-202 HINDLE D., ROOTH M. (1993), Structural Ambiguity and Lexical Relations. Computational Linguistics, 19(1):103-120 KILGARRIFF A., GREFENSTETTE G. (2003), Introduction to the special issue of Web as Corpus. Computational Linguistics, 29:3, pp. 333-338 MANNING C. (1993), Automatic Acquisition of Large Subcategorization Dictionary from Corpora, Proceedings of the 31st Meeting of the Association for Computational Linguistics, Columbus PANTEL P., LIN D. (2000), An unsupervised approach to prepositional phrase attachment using contextually similar words. In K. VijayShanker and Chang-Ning Huang, editors, Proceedings of the 38th Meeting of the Association for Computational Linguistics, pp. 101-108, Hong Kong RATNAPARKHI A., REYNAR J., ROUKOS S. (1994), A Maximum Entropy Model for Prepositional Phrase Attachment. Proceedings of the ARPA Workshop on Human Language Technology, Morgan Kaufmann ROLAND D., JURAFSKY, D. (1998). How Verb Subcategorization Frequencies Are Affected By Corpus Choice. Proceedings of Coling-ACL, pp. 1122-1128 SEKINE S. (1997), The domain dependence of parsing. Proceedings of the Fith Conference on Applied Natural Language Processing, pp. 96-102 SLOCUM J. (1986), How one might Automatically Identify and Adapt to a Sublanguage: An Initial Exploration, in Grishman R. and Kittredge R., eds., Analyzing Language in Restricted Domains: Sublanguage Description and Processing. Lawrence Erlbaum Associates, Hillsdale, N.J., 1986, pp. 195-210 STETINA J., NAGAO M. (1997), Corpus-based PP attachment ambiguity resolution with a semantic dictionary. In J. Zhou and K. Church editors, Proceedings of the 5th Workshop on Very Large Corpora, Beijing and Hongkong.</rawString>
</citation>
</citationList>
</algorithm>
</algorithms>