<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<algorithms version="110505">
<algorithm name="ParsCit" version="110505">
<citationList>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>ELDA EQueR</author>
</authors>
<title>Evaluation de systèmes de Question-Réponse, http://www.elda.org/article118.html Gauvain</title>
<date>2003</date>
<journal>J. Mariani.</journal>
<marker>EQueR, 2003</marker>
<rawString>EQueR, ELDA (2003) - Evaluation de systèmes de Question-Réponse, http://www.elda.org/article118.html Gauvain J. L. et Lamel L. F. (2002), Systèmes de reconnaissance, de compréhension et de dialogue, Reconnaissance de la parole Traitement automatique du langage parlé, Hermes Lavoisier, J. Mariani.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>J R Glass</author>
</authors>
<title>Data collection and performance evaluation of spoken dialogue systems : the MIT experience, Actes de ICSLP’00,</title>
<date>2000</date>
<location>Pekin, Chine.</location>
<marker>Glass, 2000</marker>
<rawString>Glass J. R. et al. (2000), Data collection and performance evaluation of spoken dialogue systems : the MIT experience, Actes de ICSLP’00, Pekin, Chine.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>B Grau</author>
</authors>
<title>Les systèmes de question-réponse, Méthodes avancées pour les systèmes de recherche d’informations, sous la direction de Madjid Ihadjadene, collection Traité des sciences et techniques de l’information,</title>
<date>2005</date>
<location>Hermes-science.</location>
<marker>Grau, 2005</marker>
<rawString>Grau B. (2005), Les systèmes de question-réponse, Méthodes avancées pour les systèmes de recherche d’informations, sous la direction de Madjid Ihadjadene, collection Traité des sciences et techniques de l’information, Hermes-science.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>S Harabagiu</author>
</authors>
<title>The Role of Lexico-Semantic Feedback in Open-Domain Textual QuestionAnswering, Actes de Association for Computational Linguistics L. Lamel et al.,</title>
<date>2001</date>
<journal>The LIMSI ARISE System, Speech Communication</journal>
<volume>Vol.</volume>
<pages>31--4</pages>
<marker>Harabagiu, 2001</marker>
<rawString>S. Harabagiu, et al., (2001), The Role of Lexico-Semantic Feedback in Open-Domain Textual QuestionAnswering, Actes de Association for Computational Linguistics L. Lamel et al., (2000), The LIMSI ARISE System, Speech Communication Vol. 31(4):339-354.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>L Devillers</author>
</authors>
<title>The French MEDIA/EVALDA Project: the Evaluation of the Understanding Capability of Spoken Language Dialogue Systems,</title>
<date>2004</date>
<journal>LREC’04 J. Villaneau</journal>
<marker>Devillers, 2004</marker>
<rawString>Devillers L. et al. (2004), The French MEDIA/EVALDA Project: the Evaluation of the Understanding Capability of Spoken Language Dialogue Systems, LREC’04 J. Villaneau (2003), Contribution au traitement syntactico-pragmatique de la langue naturelle parlée : approche logique pour la compréhension de la parole, Thèse de Doctorat, Université de Bretagne Sud.</rawString>
</citation>
</citationList>
</algorithm>
</algorithms>