<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<algorithms version="110505">
<algorithm name="ParsCit" version="110505">
<citationList>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>I DAGAN</author>
<author>A ITAI</author>
</authors>
<title>Word Sense Disambiguation Using a Second Language Monolingual Corpus.</title>
<date>1994</date>
<journal>Computational Linguistics,</journal>
<pages>20--4</pages>
<marker>DAGAN, ITAI, 1994</marker>
<rawString>DAGAN I., ITAI A. (1994), Word Sense Disambiguation Using a Second Language Monolingual Corpus. Computational Linguistics, 20(4):563-596.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>DE LOUPY CL</author>
</authors>
<title>Evaluation de l’Apport de Connaissances Linguistiques en Desambigu&apos;1&apos;sation Semantique et Recherche Documentaire. These de Doctorat, Universite d’Avignon et des Pays du Vaucluse.</title>
<date>2000</date>
<marker>CL, 2000</marker>
<rawString>DE LOUPY CL. (2000), Evaluation de l’Apport de Connaissances Linguistiques en Desambigu&apos;1&apos;sation Semantique et Recherche Documentaire. These de Doctorat, Universite d’Avignon et des Pays du Vaucluse.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>M DIAB</author>
<author>P RESNIK</author>
</authors>
<title>An Unsupervised Method for Word Sense Tagging using Parallel Corpora,</title>
<date>2002</date>
<booktitle>Proc. of 40th Anniversary Meeting of the Association for Computational Linguistics (ACL-02),</booktitle>
<location>Philadelphia.</location>
<marker>DIAB, RESNIK, 2002</marker>
<rawString>DIAB M., RESNIK P. (2002), An Unsupervised Method for Word Sense Tagging using Parallel Corpora, Proc. of 40th Anniversary Meeting of the Association for Computational Linguistics (ACL-02), Philadelphia.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>M DIAB</author>
</authors>
<title>Word Sense Disambiguation within a Multilingual Framework. Ph.D. thesis,University of Maryland.</title>
<date>2003</date>
<marker>DIAB, 2003</marker>
<rawString>DIAB M. (2003), Word Sense Disambiguation within a Multilingual Framework. Ph.D. thesis,University of Maryland.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>W A GALE</author>
<author>K W CHURCH</author>
<author>D YAROWSKY</author>
</authors>
<title>Using Bilingual Materials to Develop Word Sense Disambiguation Methods.</title>
<date>1992</date>
<booktitle>In Proc. of the Fourth Inter—national Conference on Theoretical and Methodological Issues in Machine Translation,</booktitle>
<pages>101--112</pages>
<location>Montreal.</location>
<marker>GALE, CHURCH, YAROWSKY, 1992</marker>
<rawString>GALE W. A., CHURCH K. W., YAROWSKY D. (1992). Using Bilingual Materials to Develop Word Sense Disambiguation Methods. In Proc. of the Fourth Inter—national Conference on Theoretical and Methodological Issues in Machine Translation, pages 101-112, Montreal.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>N IDE</author>
<author>T ERJAVEC</author>
<author>D TUFIS</author>
</authors>
<title>Sense Discrimination with Parallel Corpora.</title>
<date>2002</date>
<booktitle>Proceedings of ACL&apos;02 Workshop on Word Sense Disambiguation: Recent Successes and Future Directions,</booktitle>
<pages>54--60</pages>
<location>Philadelphia,</location>
<marker>IDE, ERJAVEC, TUFIS, 2002</marker>
<rawString>IDE N., ERJAVEC T., TUFIS D. (2002). Sense Discrimination with Parallel Corpora. Proceedings of ACL&apos;02 Workshop on Word Sense Disambiguation: Recent Successes and Future Directions, Philadelphia, 54-60.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>CHEN BOXING</author>
</authors>
<title>Combining clues for lexical level aligning using the Null hypothesis approach,</title>
<date>2004</date>
<booktitle>in Proceedings of Coling 2004,</booktitle>
<pages>1261--1264</pages>
<location>Geneva,</location>
<marker>BOXING, 2004</marker>
<rawString>KRAIF 0., BOXING, CHEN (2004) Combining clues for lexical level aligning using the Null hypothesis approach, in Proceedings of Coling 2004, Geneva, August 2004, pp. 1261-1264.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>D TUFIS</author>
<author>R ION</author>
<author>N IDE</author>
</authors>
<title>Fine-Grained Word Sense Disambiguation Based on Parallel Corpora, Word Alignment, Word Clustering and Aligned Wordnets.</title>
<date>2004</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the 20th International Conference on Computational Linguistics, COLING2004,</booktitle>
<location>Geneva.</location>
<marker>TUFIS, ION, IDE, 2004</marker>
<rawString>TUFIS D., ION R., IDE N. (2004), Fine-Grained Word Sense Disambiguation Based on Parallel Corpora, Word Alignment, Word Clustering and Aligned Wordnets. In Proceedings of the 20th International Conference on Computational Linguistics, COLING2004, Geneva.</rawString>
</citation>
</citationList>
</algorithm>
</algorithms>