<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<algorithms version="110505">
<algorithm name="ParsCit" version="110505">
<citationList>
<citation valid="false">
<title>Les Sables d’Olonne DAnIEL : Veille épidémiologique multilingue parcimonieuse Gaël Lejeune, Romain Brixtel, Charlotte Lecluze, Antoine Doucet, Nadine Lucas Normandie Université;</title>
<date>2012</date>
<booktitle>UNICAEN, GREYC, CNRS UMR 6072, F-14032</booktitle>
<pages>64--75</pages>
<location>Caen</location>
<marker>2012</marker>
<rawString>TALN-RÉCITAL 2013, 17-21 Juin, Les Sables d’Olonne DAnIEL : Veille épidémiologique multilingue parcimonieuse Gaël Lejeune, Romain Brixtel, Charlotte Lecluze, Antoine Doucet, Nadine Lucas Normandie Université; UNICAEN, GREYC, CNRS UMR 6072, F-14032 Caen LEJEUNE, G., BRIXTEL, R., DOUCET, A. et LUCAS, N. (2012). DAnIEL : Language Independent Character-Based News Surveillance. In Advances in Natural Language Processing, Springer LNAI 7614, pages 64–75.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>G LEJEUNE</author>
<author>R BRIXTEL</author>
<author>C LECLUZE</author>
<author>A et LUCAS DOUCET</author>
<author>N</author>
</authors>
<title>Added-value of automatic multilingual text analysis for epidemic surveillance.</title>
<date>2013</date>
<booktitle>14th Conf. Artificial Intelligence in Medicine AIME,</booktitle>
<location>Murcia,</location>
<marker>LEJEUNE, BRIXTEL, LECLUZE, DOUCET, N, 2013</marker>
<rawString>LEJEUNE, G., BRIXTEL, R., LECLUZE, C., DOUCET, A. et LUCAS, N. (2013). Added-value of automatic multilingual text analysis for epidemic surveillance. 14th Conf. Artificial Intelligence in Medicine AIME, Murcia, May.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>R STEINBERGER</author>
</authors>
<title>A survey of methods to ease the development of highly multilingual text mining applications. Language Resources and Evaluation,</title>
<date>2011</date>
<pages>1--22</pages>
<note>1. https://daniel.greyc.fr 788 c ATALA</note>
<marker>STEINBERGER, 2011</marker>
<rawString>STEINBERGER, R. (2011). A survey of methods to ease the development of highly multilingual text mining applications. Language Resources and Evaluation, pages 1–22. 1. https://daniel.greyc.fr 788 c ATALA</rawString>
</citation>
</citationList>
</algorithm>
</algorithms>