<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<algorithms version="110505">
<algorithm name="ParsCit" version="110505">
<citationList>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>A BROWN</author>
</authors>
<title>A review of the tip of the tongue experience.</title>
<date>1991</date>
<journal>Psychological Bulletin,</journal>
<volume>10</volume>
<pages>204--223</pages>
<marker>BROWN, 1991</marker>
<rawString>BROWN, A. (1991). A review of the tip of the tongue experience. Psychological Bulletin, 10, pages 204-223 BROWN, R. et MC NEILL, D. (1966). The tip of the tongue phenomenon. Journal of Verbal Learning and Verbal Behavior, 5, pages 325-337 DELL, G. (1986). A spreading-activation theory of retrieval in sentence production. Psychological Review, 93, 283-321.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<title>The Oxford Reverse Dictionary,</title>
<date>1999</date>
<editor>EDMONDS, D. (ed.)</editor>
<publisher>University Press,</publisher>
<location>Oxford</location>
<marker>1999</marker>
<rawString>EDMONDS, D. (ed.) (1999). The Oxford Reverse Dictionary, Oxford University Press, Oxford, 1999.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>C FELLBAUM</author>
</authors>
<title>WordNet: An Electronic Lexical Database and some of its Applications.</title>
<date>1998</date>
<publisher>MIT Press.</publisher>
<location>Cambridge, MA:</location>
<marker>FELLBAUM, 1998</marker>
<rawString>FELLBAUM, C. (éd.) (1998). WordNet: An Electronic Lexical Database and some of its Applications. Cambridge, MA: MIT Press.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>A JOUBERT</author>
<author>M LAFOURCADE</author>
</authors>
<title>A new dynamic approach for lexical networks evaluation.</title>
<date>2012</date>
<booktitle>Proceedings LREC’12 (Eight International Conference on Language Resources and Evaluation), Istanbul, Turkey, European Language Resources Association (ELRA).</booktitle>
<editor>In Choukri et al. (eds.),</editor>
<marker>JOUBERT, LAFOURCADE, 2012</marker>
<rawString>JOUBERT, A., LAFOURCADE, M. (2012). A new dynamic approach for lexical networks evaluation. In Choukri et al. (eds.), Proceedings LREC’12 (Eight International Conference on Language Resources and Evaluation), Istanbul, Turkey, European Language Resources Association (ELRA).</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="false">
<authors>
<author>A LAFOURCADE JOUBERT</author>
<author>M SCHWAB</author>
<author>D et ZOCK</author>
<author>M</author>
</authors>
<title>Évaluation et consolidation d’un réseau lexical !via un outil pour retrouver !le mot sur le bout de la langue.</title>
<date>2011</date>
<booktitle>Actes de 602 c ATALA TALN-RÉCITAL 2013, 17-21 Juin, Les Sables d’Olonne la 18ème conférence sur le Traitement Automatique des Langues Naturelles (TALN), Montpellier,</booktitle>
<pages>295--306</pages>
<marker>JOUBERT, SCHWAB, ZOCK, M, 2011</marker>
<rawString>JOUBERT, A. LAFOURCADE, M., SCHWAB, D. et ZOCK, M. (2011). Évaluation et consolidation d’un réseau lexical !via un outil pour retrouver !le mot sur le bout de la langue. Actes de 602 c ATALA TALN-RÉCITAL 2013, 17-21 Juin, Les Sables d’Olonne la 18ème conférence sur le Traitement Automatique des Langues Naturelles (TALN), Montpellier, pp. 295-306 KILGARRIFF, A., RYCHLY, R., SMRZ, P. et TUGWELL, D. (2004). The Sketch Engine.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>M LAFOURCADE</author>
</authors>
<title>Making people play for lexical acquisition.</title>
<date>2007</date>
<booktitle>Proceedings of the 11th Euralex International Congress.</booktitle>
<pages>105--116</pages>
<location>Lorient, France,</location>
<marker>LAFOURCADE, 2007</marker>
<rawString>Proceedings of the 11th Euralex International Congress. Lorient, France, pages 105-116 LAFOURCADE, M. (2007). Making people play for lexical acquisition. In Proceedings SNLP 2007 (7th Symposium on Natural Language Processing), Pattaya, Thailande.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>W LEVELT</author>
<author>A et MEYER ROELOFS</author>
<author>A</author>
</authors>
<title>A theory of lexical access in speech production.</title>
<date>1999</date>
<journal>Behavioral and Brain Sciences,</journal>
<volume>22</volume>
<pages>1--75</pages>
<marker>LEVELT, ROELOFS, A, 1999</marker>
<rawString>LEVELT, W., ROELOFS, A. et MEYER, A. (1999). A theory of lexical access in speech production. Behavioral and Brain Sciences, 22, pages 1-75.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>A MARCHETTI</author>
<author>M TESCONI</author>
<author>F RONZANO</author>
<author>M et MINUTOLI ROSELLA</author>
<author>S</author>
</authors>
<title>SEMKEY. A semantic collaborative tagging system.</title>
<date>2007</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of WWW2007,</booktitle>
<location>Banf, Canada.</location>
<marker>MARCHETTI, TESCONI, RONZANO, ROSELLA, S, 2007</marker>
<rawString>MARCHETTI, A., TESCONI, M., RONZANO, F., ROSELLA, M. et MINUTOLI, S. (2007). SEMKEY. A semantic collaborative tagging system. In Proceedings of WWW2007, Banf, Canada.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>R et MOLDOVAN MIHALCEA</author>
<author>D</author>
</authors>
<title>Extended wordnet: progress report.</title>
<date>2001</date>
<booktitle>In NAACL 2001 (Workshop on WordNet and Other Lexical Resources),</booktitle>
<location>Pittsburgh, USA.</location>
<marker>MIHALCEA, D, 2001</marker>
<rawString>MIHALCEA, R. et MOLDOVAN, D. (2001). Extended wordnet: progress report. In NAACL 2001 (Workshop on WordNet and Other Lexical Resources), Pittsburgh, USA.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>R et CHKLOVSKI MIHALCEA</author>
<author>T</author>
</authors>
<title>Open Mind Word Expert: Creating large annotated data collections with web userp&apos;s help.</title>
<date>2003</date>
<booktitle>In LINC 2003 (Proceedings of the EACL 2003 Workshop on Linguistically Annotated Corpora),</booktitle>
<location>Budapest.</location>
<marker>MIHALCEA, T, 2003</marker>
<rawString>MIHALCEA, R. et CHKLOVSKI, T. (2003). Open Mind Word Expert: Creating large annotated data collections with web userp&apos;s help. In LINC 2003 (Proceedings of the EACL 2003 Workshop on Linguistically Annotated Corpora), Budapest.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>G MILLER</author>
<author>R BECKWITH</author>
<author>C FELLBAUM</author>
<author>D GROSS</author>
<author>K MILLER</author>
</authors>
<title>Introduction to WordNet: an on-line lexical database.</title>
<date>1990</date>
<journal>International Journal of Lexicography</journal>
<volume>3</volume>
<pages>235--244</pages>
<marker>MILLER, BECKWITH, FELLBAUM, GROSS, MILLER, 1990</marker>
<rawString>MILLER, G., BECKWITH, R., FELLBAUM, C., GROSS, D., MILLER, K. (1990). Introduction to WordNet: an on-line lexical database. International Journal of Lexicography 3, pages 235-244.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="false">
<authors>
<author>M PENNACCHIOTTI</author>
<author>P PANTEL</author>
</authors>
<title>A bootstrapping algorithm for automatically harvesting semantic relations.</title>
<date>2006</date>
<journal>Computational Linguistics</journal>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of ICoS (Inference in Computational Semantis), Boxton, England,</booktitle>
<volume>32</volume>
<pages>87--96</pages>
<editor>RUNDELL, M. et FOX, G. (eds.)</editor>
<marker>PENNACCHIOTTI, PANTEL, 2006</marker>
<rawString>PENNACCHIOTTI, M., PANTEL, P. (2006). A bootstrapping algorithm for automatically harvesting semantic relations. In Proceedings of ICoS (Inference in Computational Semantis), Boxton, England, pages 87-96 RUNDELL, M. et FOX, G. (eds.) (2002). Macmillan English Dictionary for Advanced Learners (MEDAL). Oxford ROGET, P. (1852). Thesaurus of English Words and Phrases. Longman, London TURNEY, P.D. (2006). Similarity of semantic relations. Computational Linguistics 32, pages 379-416 ZOCK, M., FERRET, O., SCHWAB, D. (2010). Deliberate word access: an intuition, a roadmap and some preliminary empirical results. Int J Speech Technol 13, pages 201-218 ZOCK, M. et SCHWAB, D. (2011). Storage does not garantee access: The problem of organizing and accessing words in a speaker&apos;s lexicon. Journal of Cognitive Science 12, pages 233-259 ZOCK, M. et SCHWAB, D. (2013) L&apos;index, une ressource vitale pour guider les auteurs à trouver le mot bloqué sur le bout de la langue. In Gala, N. et M. Zock (éds). Ressources lexicales : construction et utilisation. Lingvisticae Investigationes, John Benjamins, Amsterdam, The Netherlands 603 c ATALA</rawString>
</citation>
</citationList>
</algorithm>
</algorithms>