<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<algorithms version="110505">
<algorithm name="ParsCit" version="110505">
<citationList>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>T BUCKWALTER</author>
</authors>
<title>Buckwalter Arabic Morphological Analyzer Version 1.0. Linguistic Data Consortium,</title>
<date>2002</date>
<institution>University of Pennsylvania.</institution>
<note>Catalog: LDC2 002 L49.</note>
<marker>BUCKWALTER, 2002</marker>
<rawString>BUCKWALTER, T. (2002). Buckwalter Arabic Morphological Analyzer Version 1.0. Linguistic Data Consortium, University of Pennsylvania. Catalog: LDC2 002 L49.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>M CARPUAT</author>
<author>Y et HABASH MARTON</author>
<author>N</author>
</authors>
<title>Reordering Matrix Post-verbal Subjects for Arabic-to-English SMT.</title>
<date>2010</date>
<booktitle>In proceedings of the 17th Conference sur le Traitement des Langues Naturelles (TALN 2010).</booktitle>
<location>Montreal, Canada.</location>
<marker>CARPUAT, MARTON, N, 2010</marker>
<rawString>CARPUAT, M., MARTON, Y. et HABASH, N. (2010). Reordering Matrix Post-verbal Subjects for Arabic-to-English SMT. In proceedings of the 17th Conference sur le Traitement des Langues Naturelles (TALN 2010). Montreal, Canada.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>M DIAB</author>
<author>K et IURAFSKY HACIOGLU</author>
<author>D</author>
</authors>
<title>Automatic Tagging of Arabic Text: From Raw Text to Base Phrase Chunks.</title>
<date>2004</date>
<booktitle>In Proc. of the North American Chapter of the Association for Computational Linguistics (NAACL),</booktitle>
<location>Boston, MA.</location>
<marker>DIAB, HACIOGLU, D, 2004</marker>
<rawString>DIAB, M., HACIOGLU, K. et IURAFSKY, D. (2004). Automatic Tagging of Arabic Text: From Raw Text to Base Phrase Chunks. In Proc. of the North American Chapter of the Association for Computational Linguistics (NAACL), Boston, MA.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>ATALA TALN-RECITAL</author>
</authors>
<title>Is Arabic Part of Speech Tagging Feasible Without Word Segmentation?</title>
<date>2013</date>
<booktitle>In HLT/ACL 2010, Human Language Technologies: The 2010 Annual Conference of the North American Chapter of the ACL,</booktitle>
<pages>17--21</pages>
<location>Los Angeles, California, ]une</location>
<contexts>
<context position="2423" citStr="TALN-RECITAL 2013" startWordPosition="342" endWordPosition="343">re-processing schemes for Arabic and applying additional language analysis rules in relation to the target language. The proposed approach is completed using pre-processing and language analysis rules without increasing the amount of training data. MOTS-CLES : Traduction automatique statistique, traduction arabe-francais, pré-traitement de corpus, morphologie de l’Arabe. KEYWORDS: Statistical machine translation, Arabic-French translation, Corpus preprocessing, Arabic morphology. 1 Introduction Arabic is a morphologically rich and complex language, in which a word carries not only 620 © ATALA TALN-RECITAL 2013, 17-21 Iuin, Les Sables d’Olonne inﬂections but also clitics, such as pronouns, conjunctions, and prepositions. This morphological complexity also has consequences for NLP applications, such as machine translation and information retrieval. On the one hand, developing an Arabic-French machine translation system is not an easy task, although there is a vast amount of training data nowadays. On the other hand, dealing with the complexity and ambiguity of the source language plays a major role in boosting the efﬁciency of the translation system. In previous research, it was shown that morphologi</context>
<context position="6046" citStr="TALN-RECITAL 2013" startWordPosition="898" endWordPosition="899">ench General Directorate for Armament (DGA). Our main interest at this stage is related to the pre-processing of the source language, in order to improve the quality of translation, rather than the radical changes that might improve the translation or training engines or the increase of the amount of training corpora. This paper is organized as follows. The morphology of Arabic language is described in section 2. In section 3, we discuss the proposed solutions of pre-processing Arabic through 1 http://www.bechno1angue.net/article.php3?id_article=199 2 http://www.trad-campaign.org/ 621 © ATALA TALN-RECITAL 2013, 17-21 Iuin, Les Sables d’Olonne segmentation and language analysis. In section 4-, we present the experiments on ArabicFrench SMT with different evaluations. Section 5 concludes the present paper with a discussion and some perspectives. a The Morphology of Arabic Language Before we delve into the methods, we need to discuss the nature of the Arabic language, which has a bearing on the text preparation stage. Figure 1 shows a white-space delimited word in Arabic. The Arabic script is complicated in that each white-space-delimited unit may correspond to several syntactic units. The Arabic orth</context>
<context position="8615" citStr="TALN-RECITAL 2013" startWordPosition="1308" endWordPosition="1309">ical complexity in order to obtain better alignments and decoding for Statistical Machine Translation (Habash et al., 2010). Our goal at this stage is related to the pre-processing of Arabic as a source language, in order to improve the quality of translation. First, in order to perform Arabic pre-processing, we used a machine learning approach that performs word segmentation and POS tagging at the segment level. We then use rules to derive the different pre-processing schemes 3 All Arabic transliterations are provided using the Buckwalter transliteration scheme (Buckwalter, 2002) 622 © ATALA TALN-RECITAL 2013, 17-21 Iuin, Les Sables d’Olonne required for the machine translation experiments. Thus, instead of using MADA (Habash et al., 2010), the well known morphological analyzer for Arabic, we choose our own morphological analyzer that is memory-based learning for both word segmentation and part of speech tagging (Emad and Kiibler, 2010). The segmentation and POS tagging modules above give a rich representation with enough information for almost any further required transformation. Given an input sentence like (a), the system produces (b) as a segmented and annotated sentence, as described in the f</context>
<context position="11536" citStr="TALN-RECITAL 2013" startWordPosition="1698" endWordPosition="1699">CON] qd/VERB_PART ArtbT/PV+t/PVSUFF_SUB]:3FS Al/DET ADTrAb/NOUN+At/NSUFF_FEM_PL b/PREP trHyl/NOUN Al/DET slT/NOUN+At/NSUFF_FEM_PL Al/DET frnsy/AD]+p/NSUFF_FEM_SG l/PREP Al/DET Edyd/NOUN mn/PREP Al/DET mhAjr/NOUN+yn/NSUFF_MASC_PL_GEN gyr/NEG_PART Al/DET $rEy/AD]+yn/ NSUFF_MASC_PL_GEN&amp;quot;. Where the conjunction w, the prepositions b and I, and the deﬁnite article A1 are no longer preﬁxes, but separate tokens. The process also normalized the deﬁnite article from I to AI, which is the more frequent form. Morp Reduced. In the morphologically reduced experiment, we reduce the morphology of 623 © ATALA TALN-RECITAL 2013, 17-21 Iuin, Les Sables d’Olonne Arabic to a level that makes it closer to that of the French language. An example of this is the dual form, which does not occur in French and has thus been transformed to the plural. The following table (Table 1) lists the most common examples of Arabic morphological reduction. Rule Example before applying the Example after applying rule the rule Regular Plural mstv\fT n W11 AlmstWTnyn Nominative —&gt; Regular Plural Accusative dual Nominative —&gt; lAEbAn lAEbyn Regular Plural Accusative ]ussive Mood —&gt; hn lm ylEb11 hm lm ylEbw11 Indicative Mood hm lm ylEb WA hn l</context>
<context position="13956" citStr="TALN-RECITAL 2013" startWordPosition="2092" endWordPosition="2093">tice of extracting bilingual phrases from the parallel data usually consists of three steps: ﬁrst, words in bilingual sentence pairs are aligned using state-of-the-art automatic word alignment tools, such as GIZA++ (Och and Ney, 2003), in both directions; second, word alignment links are reﬁned using heuristics, such as Grow-Diagonal-Final (GDF) method; third, bilingual phrases are extracted from the parallel data based on the reﬁned word alignments with predeﬁned constraints (Och and Ney, 200 3). The trigram language models are implemented using the SRILM toolkit (Stolcke, 2002). 624 © ATALA TALN-RECITAL 2013, 17-21 Iuin, Les Sables d’Olonne Moses4 (Koehn et al., 2007), an open source toolkit for phrase-based SMT system, was used as a decoder. These steps of building a translation system are considered as a common practice in the state-of-the-art of phrase-based SMT systems. Our research for improving the ArabicFrench SMT system was emphasized more on the pre-processing part of the SMT system. We have measured the effect of the proposed pre-processing steps on data sparseness, based on the percentage of unknown unigrams (OOVs) on a development set (dev set). Table 2 summarizes the ﬁndings on the d</context>
<context position="16308" citStr="TALN-RECITAL 2013" startWordPosition="2475" endWordPosition="2476">ich includes performing re-casing and removing white space before punctuation, (b) Nopunct; in which punctuation is stripped and evaluation is performed on the lexical text only, and (c) Nopunctcase in which, in addition to removing punctuation, all words are lower-cased. We can see from Table 3 that the Baseline experiment produces the lowest results, and that the tokenization scheme is a big leap with a 7.2 BLEU scores of improvement (25.9 vs. 33.1), which means that performing tokenization is a really a necessary step for translating 4 Available on http://www.staImt.org/ mosesl 625 © ATALA TALN-RECITAL 2013, 17-21 Iuin, Les Sables d’Olonne from Arabic, an that the morphological complexity of Arabic could be a hindrance to quality automatic translation. While tokenization leads to considerable improvement, morphological reduction fares even better with a 7.4 BLEU score higher than the baseline. This could be due to the fact the morphological reduction reduces the number of unknown words even further than tokenization alone. Swapping elements to match the target language, which is built upon tokenization and morphological reduction, leads to a deterioration of the results a little as it cancels ou</context>
</contexts>
<marker>TALN-RECITAL, 2013</marker>
<rawString>626 © ATALA TALN-RECITAL 2013, 17-21 Iuin, Les Sables d’Olonne EMAD, M. et KUBLER, S. (2010). Is Arabic Part of Speech Tagging Feasible Without Word Segmentation? In HLT/ACL 2010, Human Language Technologies: The 2010 Annual Conference of the North American Chapter of the ACL, pages 705-708, Los Angeles, California, ]une 2010.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>A EL ISBIHANI</author>
<author>S KHADIVI</author>
<author>BENDER</author>
</authors>
<title>Morpho-syntactic Arabic Preprocessing for Arabic to English Statistical Machine Translation.</title>
<date>2006</date>
<booktitle>In Human Language Technology Conf. / North American Chapter of the Assoc. for Computational Linguistics Annual Meeting (HLT-NAACL), Workshop on Statistical Machine Translation,</booktitle>
<pages>15--22</pages>
<location>New York City,</location>
<marker>EL ISBIHANI, KHADIVI, BENDER, 2006</marker>
<rawString>EL ISBIHANI, A., KHADIVI, S., BENDER, 0., ET NEY, H. (2006). Morpho-syntactic Arabic Preprocessing for Arabic to English Statistical Machine Translation. In Human Language Technology Conf. / North American Chapter of the Assoc. for Computational Linguistics Annual Meeting (HLT-NAACL), Workshop on Statistical Machine Translation, New York City, pages 15-22.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>S et MCCLOSKY GOLDWATER</author>
<author>D</author>
</authors>
<title>Improving Statistical MT through Morphological Analysis.</title>
<date>2005</date>
<booktitle>In Proc. of Empirical Methods in Natural Language Processing (EMNLP),</booktitle>
<location>Vancouver, Canada.</location>
<marker>GOLDWATER, D, 2005</marker>
<rawString>GOLDWATER, S. et MCCLOSKY, D. (2005). Improving Statistical MT through Morphological Analysis. In Proc. of Empirical Methods in Natural Language Processing (EMNLP), Vancouver, Canada.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>N et SADAT HABASH</author>
<author>F</author>
</authors>
<title>Arabic Preprocessing Schemes for Statistical Machine Translation.</title>
<date>2006</date>
<journal>HABASH, N., RAMBOW, 0. et RYAN R.</journal>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of NAACL 2006,</booktitle>
<volume>2</volume>
<pages>5--7</pages>
<location>New York (USA).</location>
<marker>HABASH, F, 2006</marker>
<rawString>HABASH, N. et SADAT, F. (2006). Arabic Preprocessing Schemes for Statistical Machine Translation. In Proceedings of NAACL 2006, New York (USA). ]une 5-7. HABASH, N., RAMBOW, 0. et RYAN R. (2 010). The MADA and TOKAN Manual.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>S HASAN</author>
<author>A et NEY EL ISBIHANI</author>
<author>H</author>
</authors>
<title>Creating a Large-Scale Arabic to French Statistical Machine Translation System.</title>
<date>2006</date>
<booktitle>In International Conference on Language resources and Evaluation (LREC),</booktitle>
<pages>855--858</pages>
<location>Genoa, Italy,</location>
<marker>HASAN, EL ISBIHANI, H, 2006</marker>
<rawString>HASAN, S., EL ISBIHANI, A. et NEY, H. (2006). Creating a Large-Scale Arabic to French Statistical Machine Translation System. In International Conference on Language resources and Evaluation (LREC), Genoa, Italy, pages 855-858.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>O ZENS AR</author>
<author>R CONSTANTIN</author>
<author>A HERBST</author>
<author>MORAN C et BIRCH E</author>
<author>A</author>
</authors>
<title>Moses: Open source toolkit for statistical machine translation.</title>
<date>2007</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of ACL</booktitle>
<marker>AR, CONSTANTIN, HERBST, E, A, 2007</marker>
<rawString>KOEHN, P., SHEN, W., FEDERICO, M,. BERTOLDI, N., CALLISON-BURCH, C., C0wAN, B., DYER, C., HOANG, H., B0]AR, O. ZENS, R., CONSTANTIN, A., HERBST, E., MORAN C. et BIRCH, A. (2007). Moses: Open source toolkit for statistical machine translation. In Proceedings of ACL 2007.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Y LEE</author>
</authors>
<title>Morphological Analysis for Statistical Machine Translation.</title>
<date>2004</date>
<booktitle>In Proc. of NAACL,</booktitle>
<location>Boston, MA.</location>
<marker>LEE, 2004</marker>
<rawString>LEE, Y. (2004). Morphological Analysis for Statistical Machine Translation. In Proc. of NAACL, Boston, MA.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>et NEY</author>
<author>H</author>
</authors>
<title>A Systematic Comparison of Various Statistical Alignment Models.</title>
<date>2003</date>
<journal>Computational linguistics</journal>
<volume>29</volume>
<issue>1</issue>
<pages>pages</pages>
<marker>NEY, H, 2003</marker>
<rawString>OCH, F., ]. et NEY,H. (2003). A Systematic Comparison of Various Statistical Alignment Models. Computational linguistics 29 (1), pages 19-51.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>K PAPINENI</author>
<author>S ROUKOs</author>
<author>T et ZHU WARD</author>
<author>W</author>
</authors>
<title>Bleu: a Method for Automatic Evaluation of Machine Translation.</title>
<date>2001</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of CO LING-ACL 2 006,</booktitle>
<tech>Technical Report RC22176(W0109-022),</tech>
<volume>1</volume>
<issue>2</issue>
<pages>006</pages>
<institution>IBM Research Division,</institution>
<location>Yorktown</location>
<marker>PAPINENI, ROUKOs, WARD, W, 2001</marker>
<rawString>PAPINENI, K., ROUKOs, S., WARD, T. et ZHU, W. (2001). Bleu: a Method for Automatic Evaluation of Machine Translation. Technical Report RC22176(W0109-022), IBM Research Division, Yorktown Heights, NY. SADAT, F. et HABASH, H. Arabic Preprocessing for Statistical Machine Translation: Schemes and Techniques. In Proceedings of CO LING-ACL 2 006, Sydney, Australia. ]uly 1 7-2 1 (2 006).</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<title>Translation model adaptation for an Arabic/French news translation system by lightly-supervised training.</title>
<date>2009</date>
<booktitle>In MTSummit STOLCKE, A.</booktitle>
<marker>2009</marker>
<rawString>SCHWENK, H. et SENELLART, ]. (2009). Translation model adaptation for an Arabic/French news translation system by lightly-supervised training. In MTSummit STOLCKE, A. (2002). SRILM-An Extensible Language Modeling Toolkit. In Proc. Of the International Conference on Spoken language Processing</rawString>
</citation>
</citationList>
</algorithm>
</algorithms>