<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<algorithms version="110505">
<algorithm name="ParsCit" version="110505">
<citationList>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>A ABEILLÉ</author>
<author>L et KINYON CLÉMENT</author>
<author>A</author>
</authors>
<title>Building a treebank for french.</title>
<date>2000</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the 2nd International Conference on Language Ressources and Evaluation (LREC),</booktitle>
<pages>1251--1254</pages>
<location>Athènes, Grèce.</location>
<marker>ABEILLÉ, CLÉMENT, A, 2000</marker>
<rawString>ABEILLÉ, A., CLÉMENT, L. et KINYON, A. (2000). Building a treebank for french. In Proceedings of the 2nd International Conference on Language Ressources and Evaluation (LREC), pages 1251– 1254, Athènes, Grèce.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>F BENARMARA</author>
<author>N HATOUT</author>
<author>P et OZDOWSKA MULLER</author>
<author>S</author>
</authors>
<date>2007</date>
<booktitle>Actes de TALN 2007 (Traitement automatique des langues naturelles),</booktitle>
<location>Toulouse. ATALA, IRIT.</location>
<marker>BENARMARA, HATOUT, MULLER, S, 2007</marker>
<rawString>BENARMARA, F., HATOUT, N., MULLER, P. et OZDOWSKA, S., éditeurs (2007). Actes de TALN 2007 (Traitement automatique des langues naturelles), Toulouse. ATALA, IRIT.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>S et MARSI BUCHHOLZ</author>
<author>E</author>
</authors>
<title>Conll-x shared task on multilingual dependency parsing.</title>
<date>2006</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the 10th Conference on Computational Natural Language Learning (CoNLL-X),</booktitle>
<pages>149--164</pages>
<location>New York</location>
<marker>BUCHHOLZ, E, 2006</marker>
<rawString>BUCHHOLZ, S. et MARSI, E. (2006). Conll-x shared task on multilingual dependency parsing. In Proceedings of the 10th Conference on Computational Natural Language Learning (CoNLL-X), pages 149–164, New York City. Association for Computational Linguistics. http ://acl.ldc.upenn.edu/W/W06/W06-2920.pdf.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>M CANDITO</author>
<author>B et FALCO CRABBÉ</author>
<author>M</author>
</authors>
<title>Dépendances syntaxiques de surface pour le français - Schéma d’annotation pour un corpus en dépendances obtenu par conversion du FrenchTreebank.</title>
<date>2011</date>
<note>http ://alpage.inria.fr/statgram/frdep/fr_stat_dep_parsing.html.</note>
<marker>CANDITO, CRABBÉ, M, 2011</marker>
<rawString>CANDITO, M., CRABBÉ, B. et FALCO, M. (2011). Dépendances syntaxiques de surface pour le français - Schéma d’annotation pour un corpus en dépendances obtenu par conversion du FrenchTreebank. http ://alpage.inria.fr/statgram/frdep/fr_stat_dep_parsing.html.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>M CANDITO</author>
<author>J NIVRE</author>
<author>P et ANGUIANO DENIS</author>
<author>E H</author>
</authors>
<title>Benchmarking of statistical dependency parsers for french.</title>
<date>2010</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the 23rd International Conference on Computational Linguistics : Posters, COLING ’10,</booktitle>
<pages>108--116</pages>
<publisher>Association</publisher>
<institution>for Computational Linguistics.</institution>
<location>Stroudsburg, PA, USA.</location>
<marker>CANDITO, NIVRE, DENIS, H, 2010</marker>
<rawString>CANDITO, M., NIVRE, J., DENIS, P. et ANGUIANO, E. H. (2010). Benchmarking of statistical dependency parsers for french. In Proceedings of the 23rd International Conference on Computational Linguistics : Posters, COLING ’10, pages 108–116, Stroudsburg, PA, USA. Association for Computational Linguistics.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>M et SEDDAH CANDITO</author>
<author>D</author>
</authors>
<title>Le corpus sequoia : annotation syntaxique et exploitation pour l’adaptation d’analyseur par pont lexical.</title>
<date>2012</date>
<booktitle>In Actes de TALN’2012,</booktitle>
<location>Grenoble, France.</location>
<marker>CANDITO, D, 2012</marker>
<rawString>CANDITO, M. et SEDDAH, D. (2012). Le corpus sequoia : annotation syntaxique et exploitation pour l’adaptation d’analyseur par pont lexical. In Actes de TALN’2012, Grenoble, France.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>J CARROLL</author>
<author>G et BRISCOE MINNEN</author>
<author>T</author>
</authors>
<title>Corpus annotation for parser evaluation. In</title>
<date>1999</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the EACL workshop on Linguistically Interpreted Corpora (LINC).</booktitle>
<marker>CARROLL, MINNEN, T, 1999</marker>
<rawString>CARROLL, J., MINNEN, G. et BRISCOE, T. (1999). Corpus annotation for parser evaluation. In In Proceedings of the EACL workshop on Linguistically Interpreted Corpora (LINC).</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="false">
<authors>
<author>R KAPLAN</author>
<author>S RIEZLER</author>
<author>Tracy Holloway KING</author>
<author>John T MAXWELL</author>
<author>A et CROUCH VASSERMAN</author>
<author>R</author>
</authors>
<title>Speed and accuracy in shallow and deep stochastic parsing.</title>
<date>2004</date>
<booktitle>In SUSAN DUMAIS, D. M. et appel au TreeTagger et au lemmatiseur Flemm 681 c ATALA TALN-RÉCITAL 2013, 17-21 Juin, Les Sables d’Olonne ROUKOS, S., éditeurs : HLT-NAACL 2004 : Main Proceedings,</booktitle>
<pages>97--104</pages>
<publisher>Association</publisher>
<institution>for Computational Linguistics.</institution>
<location>Boston, Massachusetts, USA.</location>
<marker>KAPLAN, RIEZLER, KING, MAXWELL, VASSERMAN, R, 2004</marker>
<rawString>KAPLAN, R., RIEZLER, S., Tracy Holloway KING, John T MAXWELL, VASSERMAN, A. et CROUCH, R. (2004). Speed and accuracy in shallow and deep stochastic parsing. In SUSAN DUMAIS, D. M. et appel au TreeTagger et au lemmatiseur Flemm 681 c ATALA TALN-RÉCITAL 2013, 17-21 Juin, Les Sables d’Olonne ROUKOS, S., éditeurs : HLT-NAACL 2004 : Main Proceedings, pages 97–104, Boston, Massachusetts, USA. Association for Computational Linguistics.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>J MAKHOUL</author>
<author>F KUBALA</author>
<author>R et WEISCHEDEL SCHWARTZ</author>
<author>R</author>
</authors>
<title>Performance measures for information extraction.</title>
<date>1999</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of DARPA Broadcast News Workshop,</booktitle>
<location>Herndnon VA.</location>
<marker>MAKHOUL, KUBALA, SCHWARTZ, R, 1999</marker>
<rawString>MAKHOUL, J., KUBALA, F., SCHWARTZ, R. et WEISCHEDEL, R. (1999). Performance measures for information extraction. In Proceedings of DARPA Broadcast News Workshop, Herndnon VA.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>DE LA CLERGERIE</author>
<author>E HAMON</author>
<author>O MOSTEFA</author>
<author>D AYACHE</author>
<author>C PAROUBEK</author>
<author>P et VILNAT</author>
<author>A</author>
</authors>
<title>PASSAGE : from French Parser Evaluation to Large Sized Treebank.</title>
<date>2008</date>
<booktitle>In ELRA, éditeur : In proceedings of the sixth international conference on Language Resources and Evaluation (LREC),</booktitle>
<location>Marrakech, Morroco.</location>
<marker>CLERGERIE, HAMON, MOSTEFA, AYACHE, PAROUBEK, VILNAT, A, 2008</marker>
<rawString>DE LA CLERGERIE, E., HAMON, O., MOSTEFA, D., AYACHE, C., PAROUBEK, P. et VILNAT, A. (2008). PASSAGE : from French Parser Evaluation to Large Sized Treebank. In ELRA, éditeur : In proceedings of the sixth international conference on Language Resources and Evaluation (LREC), Marrakech, Morroco.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>M-C de MARNEFFE et C D MANNING</author>
</authors>
<title>The Stanford typed dependencies representation.</title>
<date>2008</date>
<marker>MANNING, 2008</marker>
<rawString>M.-C. de MARNEFFE et C D MANNING (2008). The Stanford typed dependencies representation.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<date>2008</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the Workshop on Cross-Framework and Cross-Domain Parser Evaluation at COLING</booktitle>
<pages>1--8</pages>
<institution>Manchester. Association for Computational Linguistics.</institution>
<marker>2008</marker>
<rawString>In Proceedings of the Workshop on Cross-Framework and Cross-Domain Parser Evaluation at COLING 2008, pages 1–8, Manchester. Association for Computational Linguistics.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Tracy Holloway KING</author>
<author>R CROUCH</author>
<author>S RIEZLER</author>
<author>M et Ronald M KAPLAN DALRYMPLE</author>
</authors>
<date>2003</date>
<marker>KING, CROUCH, RIEZLER, DALRYMPLE, 2003</marker>
<rawString>Tracy Holloway KING, CROUCH, R., RIEZLER, S., DALRYMPLE, M. et Ronald M KAPLAN (2003).</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<title>The parc 700 dependency bank.</title>
<date>2003</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of 4th International Workshop on Linguistically Interpreted Corpora (LINC-03) at EACL</booktitle>
<marker>2003</marker>
<rawString>The parc 700 dependency bank. In Proceedings of 4th International Workshop on Linguistically Interpreted Corpora (LINC-03) at EACL 2003.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Y MIYAO</author>
<author>T NINOMIYA</author>
<author>et TSUJII</author>
<author>J</author>
</authors>
<title>Corpus-oriented grammar development for acquiring a head-driven phrase structure grammar from the penn treebank.</title>
<date>2004</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the First International Joint Conference on Natural Language Processing (IJCNLP-04), numéro 3248 de Lecture Notes in Computer Science,</booktitle>
<publisher>Processing, Springer.</publisher>
<location>Hainan Island,</location>
<marker>MIYAO, NINOMIYA, TSUJII, J, 2004</marker>
<rawString>MIYAO, Y., NINOMIYA, T., et TSUJII, J. (2004). Corpus-oriented grammar development for acquiring a head-driven phrase structure grammar from the penn treebank. In Proceedings of the First International Joint Conference on Natural Language Processing (IJCNLP-04), numéro 3248 de Lecture Notes in Computer Science, Hainan Island, China. Asia Federation of Natural Language Processing, Springer.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>P PAROUBEK</author>
<author>DE LA CLERGERIE</author>
<author>E LOISEAU</author>
<author>S VILNAT</author>
<author>A et FRANCOPOULO</author>
<author>G</author>
</authors>
<title>The PASSAGE Syntactic Representation.</title>
<date>2009</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the 7th International Workshop on Treebanks and Linguistic Theories,</booktitle>
<pages>91--102</pages>
<institution>Gröningen. Netherlands Graduate Schools of Linguistics (LOT).</institution>
<marker>PAROUBEK, CLERGERIE, LOISEAU, VILNAT, FRANCOPOULO, G, 2009</marker>
<rawString>PAROUBEK, P., DE LA CLERGERIE, E., LOISEAU, S., VILNAT, A. et FRANCOPOULO, G. (2009). The PASSAGE Syntactic Representation. In Proceedings of the 7th International Workshop on Treebanks and Linguistic Theories, pages 91–102, Gröningen. Netherlands Graduate Schools of Linguistics (LOT).</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>P PAROUBEK</author>
<author>I ROBBA</author>
<author>A et AYACHE VILNAT</author>
<author>C</author>
</authors>
<title>Data, Annotations and Measures in EASY - the Evaluation Campaign for Parsers of French.</title>
<date>2006</date>
<booktitle>In proceedings of the fifth international conference on Language Resources and Evaluation (LREC</booktitle>
<pages>315--320</pages>
<location>Genoa, Italy. ELRA.</location>
<marker>PAROUBEK, ROBBA, VILNAT, C, 2006</marker>
<rawString>PAROUBEK, P., ROBBA, I., VILNAT, A. et AYACHE, C. (2006). Data, Annotations and Measures in EASY - the Evaluation Campaign for Parsers of French. In proceedings of the fifth international conference on Language Resources and Evaluation (LREC 2006), pages 315–320, Genoa, Italy. ELRA.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>K SAGAE</author>
<author>Y MIYAO</author>
<author>T MATSUZAKI</author>
<author>et TSUJII</author>
<author>J</author>
</authors>
<title>Challenges in mapping of syntactic representations for framework-independent parser evaluation.</title>
<date>2008</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the Workshop on Automated Syntatic Annotations for Interoperable Language Resources at the First International Conference on Global Interoperability for Language Resources (ICGL’08), Hong-Kong.</booktitle>
<marker>SAGAE, MIYAO, MATSUZAKI, TSUJII, J, 2008</marker>
<rawString>SAGAE, K., MIYAO, Y., MATSUZAKI, T., et TSUJII, J. (2008). Challenges in mapping of syntactic representations for framework-independent parser evaluation. In Proceedings of the Workshop on Automated Syntatic Annotations for Interoperable Language Resources at the First International Conference on Global Interoperability for Language Resources (ICGL’08), Hong-Kong.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="false">
<authors>
<author>A VILNAT</author>
<author>P PAROUBEK</author>
<author>de la CLERGERIE</author>
<author>E V</author>
<author>G et GUÉNOT FRANCOPOULO</author>
<author>M-L</author>
</authors>
<title>PASSAGE Syntactic Representation : a Minimal Common Ground for Evaluation. In CHAIR),</title>
<date>2010</date>
<journal>N. C. C., CHOUKRI, K., MAEGAARD, B., MARIANI, J., ODIJK, J., PIPERIDIS, S., ROSNER, M. et TAPIAS, D., éditeurs</journal>
<booktitle>Proceedings of the Seventh conference on International Language Resources and Evaluation (LREC’10),</booktitle>
<location>Valletta,</location>
<marker>VILNAT, PAROUBEK, CLERGERIE, V, FRANCOPOULO, M-L, 2010</marker>
<rawString>VILNAT, A., PAROUBEK, P., de la CLERGERIE, E. V., FRANCOPOULO, G. et GUÉNOT, M.-L. (2010). PASSAGE Syntactic Representation : a Minimal Common Ground for Evaluation. In CHAIR), N. C. C., CHOUKRI, K., MAEGAARD, B., MARIANI, J., ODIJK, J., PIPERIDIS, S., ROSNER, M. et TAPIAS, D., éditeurs : Proceedings of the Seventh conference on International Language Resources and Evaluation (LREC’10), Valletta, Malta. European Language Resources Association (ELRA). 682 c ATALA</rawString>
</citation>
</citationList>
</algorithm>
</algorithms>