<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<algorithms version="110505">
<algorithm name="ParsCit" version="110505">
<citationList>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>TALN-RÉCITAL</author>
</authors>
<title>17-21 Juin, Les Sables d’Olonne Références CUXAC,</title>
<date>2000</date>
<booktitle>In Faits de langues, numéro 15–16. Ophrys.</booktitle>
<location>C.</location>
<marker>TALN-RÉCITAL, 2000</marker>
<rawString>TALN-RÉCITAL 2013, 17-21 Juin, Les Sables d’Olonne Références CUXAC, C. (2000). La langue des signes française (lsf) : les voies de l’iconocité. In Faits de langues, numéro 15–16. Ophrys.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>K DUARTE</author>
</authors>
<title>Motion capture and avatars as portals for analyzing the linguistic structure of signed languages. In</title>
<date>2012</date>
<tech>PhD thesis,</tech>
<institution>Université de Bretagne Sud.</institution>
<marker>DUARTE, 2012</marker>
<rawString>DUARTE, K. (2012). Motion capture and avatars as portals for analyzing the linguistic structure of signed languages. In PhD thesis, Université de Bretagne Sud.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>R ELLIOTT</author>
<author>J R W GLAUERT</author>
<author>J R KENNAWAY</author>
<author>I et SAFAR MARSHALL</author>
<author>E</author>
</authors>
<title>Linguistic modelling and language-processing technologies for avatar-based sign language presentation.</title>
<date>2008</date>
<booktitle>In Universal Access in the Information Society,</booktitle>
<volume>6</volume>
<pages>375--391</pages>
<marker>ELLIOTT, GLAUERT, KENNAWAY, MARSHALL, E, 2008</marker>
<rawString>ELLIOTT, R., GLAUERT, J. R. W., KENNAWAY, J. R., MARSHALL, I. et SAFAR, E. (2008). Linguistic modelling and language-processing technologies for avatar-based sign language presentation. In Universal Access in the Information Society, volume 6, pages 375–391.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>M FILHOL</author>
</authors>
<title>Modèle descriptif des signes pour un traitement automatique des langues des signes.</title>
<date>2008</date>
<booktitle>In Thèse de doctorat, Université Paris-Sud.</booktitle>
<marker>FILHOL, 2008</marker>
<rawString>FILHOL, M. (2008). Modèle descriptif des signes pour un traitement automatique des langues des signes. In Thèse de doctorat, Université Paris-Sud.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>S GIBET</author>
<author>N COURTY</author>
<author>K et NAOUR DUARTE</author>
<author>T L</author>
</authors>
<title>The signcom system for datadriven animation of interactive virtual signers : Methodology and evaluation.</title>
<date>2011</date>
<publisher></publisher>
<marker>GIBET, COURTY, DUARTE, L, 2011</marker>
<rawString>GIBET, S., COURTY, N., DUARTE, K. et NAOUR, T. L. (2011). The signcom system for datadriven animation of interactive virtual signers : Methodology and evaluation. .</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>S GIBET</author>
<author>T et MARTEAU LEBOURQUE</author>
<author>P</author>
</authors>
<title>High level specification and animation of communicative gestures.</title>
<date>2001</date>
<journal>In Journal of Visual Languages and Computing,</journal>
<volume>12</volume>
<pages>657--687</pages>
<marker>GIBET, LEBOURQUE, P, 2001</marker>
<rawString>GIBET, S., LEBOURQUE, T. et MARTEAU, P. (2001). High level specification and animation of communicative gestures. In Journal of Visual Languages and Computing, volume 12, pages 657–687.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>A HÉLOIR</author>
</authors>
<title>Système de communication par agent virtuel, aide à la communication des personnes sourdes.</title>
<date>2008</date>
<booktitle>In Thèse de doctorat, Université de Bretagne Sud,</booktitle>
<pages>168--171</pages>
<marker>HÉLOIR, 2008</marker>
<rawString>HÉLOIR, A. (2008). Système de communication par agent virtuel, aide à la communication des personnes sourdes. In Thèse de doctorat, Université de Bretagne Sud, pages 168–171.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>M HUENERFAUTH</author>
</authors>
<title>Generating american sign language classifier predicates for english-to-asl machine translation. In Thèse de doctorat,</title>
<date>2006</date>
<institution>University of Pennsylvania.</institution>
<marker>HUENERFAUTH, 2006</marker>
<rawString>HUENERFAUTH, M. (2006). Generating american sign language classifier predicates for english-to-asl machine translation. In Thèse de doctorat, University of Pennsylvania.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>L KERVAJAN</author>
</authors>
<title>Contribution à la traduction automatique francais / langue des signes française (lsf) au moyen de personnages virtuels. In</title>
<date>2011</date>
<tech>PhD thesis,</tech>
<institution>Université d’Aix/Marseille.</institution>
<marker>KERVAJAN, 2011</marker>
<rawString>KERVAJAN, L. (2011). Contribution à la traduction automatique francais / langue des signes française (lsf) au moyen de personnages virtuels. In PhD thesis, Université d’Aix/Marseille.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>B et DALLE LENSEIGNE</author>
<author>P</author>
</authors>
<title>Using signing space as a representation for sign language processing.</title>
<date>2006</date>
<booktitle>In GIBET, S. et al., éditeurs : Gesture in Human-Computer Interaction and Simulation, GW, Lecture Notes in Computer Science,</booktitle>
<volume>3881</volume>
<pages>256--260</pages>
<publisher>Kluwer Academic.</publisher>
<marker>LENSEIGNE, P, 2006</marker>
<rawString>LENSEIGNE, B. et DALLE, P. (2006). Using signing space as a representation for sign language processing. In GIBET, S. et al., éditeurs : Gesture in Human-Computer Interaction and Simulation, GW, Lecture Notes in Computer Science, volume 3881, pages 256–260. Kluwer Academic.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>S K et Johnson LIDDELL</author>
<author>R E</author>
</authors>
<title>American sign language : The phonological base.</title>
<date>1989</date>
<booktitle>In Studies in the Linguistic Sciences,</booktitle>
<volume>64</volume>
<pages>197--277</pages>
<marker>LIDDELL, E, 1989</marker>
<rawString>LIDDELL, S K et Johnson, R. E. (1989). American sign language : The phonological base. In Studies in the Linguistic Sciences, volume 64, pages 197–277.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>O LOSSON</author>
</authors>
<title>Modélisation du geste communicatif et réalisation d’un signeur virtuel de phrases en langue des signes française. In</title>
<date>2000</date>
<tech>PhD thesis,</tech>
<institution>Université de Lille.</institution>
<marker>LOSSON, 2000</marker>
<rawString>LOSSON, O. (2000). Modélisation du geste communicatif et réalisation d’un signeur virtuel de phrases en langue des signes française. In PhD thesis, Université de Lille.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>A M PARISOT</author>
<author>R S</author>
<author>V et A S</author>
<author>V</author>
</authors>
<title>Construire et déconstruire l’espace dans une langue des signes : démonstration d’un protocole d’enregistrement simultané des mouvements des membres supèrieurs et du globe oculaire.</title>
<date>2010</date>
<booktitle>In Atelier TALS</booktitle>
<marker>PARISOT, S, S, V, 2010</marker>
<rawString>PARISOT, A. M., S, R., S, V. et A, V. (2010). Construire et déconstruire l’espace dans une langue des signes : démonstration d’un protocole d’enregistrement simultané des mouvements des membres supèrieurs et du globe oculaire. In Atelier TALS 2010 dans le cadre du congrès TALN 2010.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>S PRILLWITZ</author>
<author>R LEVEN</author>
<author>H ZIENERT</author>
<author>T et HENNING HANKE</author>
<author>J</author>
</authors>
<title>Hamburg Notation System for Sign Languages - An Introductory Guide.</title>
<date>1989</date>
<publisher>University of Hamburg Press.</publisher>
<marker>PRILLWITZ, LEVEN, ZIENERT, HANKE, J, 1989</marker>
<rawString>PRILLWITZ, S., LEVEN, R., ZIENERT, H., HANKE, T. et HENNING, J. (1989). Hamburg Notation System for Sign Languages - An Introductory Guide. University of Hamburg Press.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>W C STOKOE</author>
</authors>
<title>Sign language structure : an outline of the communication systems of the american deaf.</title>
<date>2005</date>
<journal>In Linguistics, Occasional Papers</journal>
<booktitle>Journal of Deaf Studies and Deaf Education,</booktitle>
<volume>8</volume>
<pages>3--37</pages>
<marker>STOKOE, 2005</marker>
<rawString>STOKOE, W. C. (2005). Sign language structure : an outline of the communication systems of the american deaf. In Linguistics, Occasional Papers 8 (1960), Journal of Deaf Studies and Deaf Education, volume 10, pages 3–37.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>C VOGLER</author>
</authors>
<title>American sign language recognition : Reducing the complexity of the task with phoneme-based modeling and parallel hidden markov models. In</title>
<date>2003</date>
<tech>PhD Thesis,</tech>
<institution>University of Pennsylvania.</institution>
<note>554 c ATALA</note>
<marker>VOGLER, 2003</marker>
<rawString>VOGLER, C. (2003). American sign language recognition : Reducing the complexity of the task with phoneme-based modeling and parallel hidden markov models. In PhD Thesis, University of Pennsylvania. 554 c ATALA</rawString>
</citation>
</citationList>
</algorithm>
</algorithms>