<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<algorithms version="110505">
<algorithm name="ParsCit" version="110505">
<citationList>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>R Barzilay</author>
<author>M Elhadad</author>
</authors>
<title>Using Lexical Chains for Text Summarization.</title>
<date>1997</date>
<booktitle>Proc. of the ACL’97/EACL’97 Workshop on Intelligent Scalable Text Summarization,</booktitle>
<pages>10--17</pages>
<location>Madrid, Spain,</location>
<contexts>
<context position="1998" citStr="Barzilay &amp; Elhadad, 1997" startWordPosition="286" endWordPosition="289">f document and abstract, this reconnaissance study reports on some preferred patterns in aggregation when authors write abstracts for journal articles on biology. The paper also discusses some prerequisites and difficulties anticipated for abstracting systems. More sentences were aggregated without than with the use of an explicit sign, such as a connective or a (semi-)colon. Mots-clés - Keywords abstracting, sentence, aggregation, synonymy, conﬂation 1 Introduction and Motivation Research on automatic abstracting has mainly stopped at content selectionl (see Kupiec et al., 1995; Marcu, 1997; Barzilay &amp; Elhadad, 1997). While there are notable contributions on 1 Summarization proper may be divided into two stages of content selection and content condensation. Choy—Kim CH UAH aggregation from text generation (see Dalianis, 1999; Shaw, 1998; Dalianis &amp; Hovy, 1993), the work is of little immediate benefit to summarization by sentence extraction. The simple made-up sentences aggregated (see Dalianis, l999:386) do not reﬂect the complex state of affairs in documents such as scientific and technical journal articles with urgent need for abstracts2. If studies on summarization are to benefit real applications, the</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Barzilay, Elhadad, 1997</marker>
<rawString>Barzilay, R. &amp; Elhadad, M. (1997) Using Lexical Chains for Text Summarization. Proc. of the ACL’97/EACL’97 Workshop on Intelligent Scalable Text Summarization, pp. 10-17, Universidad Nacional de Educacion a Distancia, Madrid, Spain, July 11.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Choy-Kim CH UAH Chuah</author>
<author>C</author>
</authors>
<title>Linguistic Processes for Content Condensation in Abstracting Scientific Texts.</title>
<date>2001</date>
<tech>PhD thesis.</tech>
<institution>Universite de Montreal</institution>
<note>(to appear).</note>
<marker>Chuah, C, 2001</marker>
<rawString>Choy-Kim CH UAH Chuah, C. (2001) Linguistic Processes for Content Condensation in Abstracting Scientific Texts. PhD thesis. Universite de Montreal (to appear).</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>D Crystal</author>
</authors>
<title>A Dictionary of Linguistics and Phonetics, 4th edn.</title>
<date>1997</date>
<publisher>Blackwell.</publisher>
<location>Oxford:</location>
<marker>Crystal, 1997</marker>
<rawString>Crystal, D. (1997) A Dictionary of Linguistics and Phonetics, 4th edn. Oxford: Blackwell.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>H Dalianis</author>
</authors>
<title>Aggregation in Natural Language Generation.</title>
<date>1999</date>
<journal>Computational Intelligence.</journal>
<pages>15--4</pages>
<contexts>
<context position="2210" citStr="Dalianis, 1999" startWordPosition="319" endWordPosition="320"> anticipated for abstracting systems. More sentences were aggregated without than with the use of an explicit sign, such as a connective or a (semi-)colon. Mots-clés - Keywords abstracting, sentence, aggregation, synonymy, conﬂation 1 Introduction and Motivation Research on automatic abstracting has mainly stopped at content selectionl (see Kupiec et al., 1995; Marcu, 1997; Barzilay &amp; Elhadad, 1997). While there are notable contributions on 1 Summarization proper may be divided into two stages of content selection and content condensation. Choy—Kim CH UAH aggregation from text generation (see Dalianis, 1999; Shaw, 1998; Dalianis &amp; Hovy, 1993), the work is of little immediate benefit to summarization by sentence extraction. The simple made-up sentences aggregated (see Dalianis, l999:386) do not reﬂect the complex state of affairs in documents such as scientific and technical journal articles with urgent need for abstracts2. If studies on summarization are to benefit real applications, then research must reﬂect real contexts. In the aforementioned studies, sentences are almost always aggregated with the use of an explicit sign, a connective or a (semi-)colon. But explicit signs restrict the number</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Dalianis, 1999</marker>
<rawString>Dalianis, H. (1999) Aggregation in Natural Language Generation. Computational Intelligence. 15(4):384-415.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>H Dalianis</author>
<author>E Hovy</author>
</authors>
<title>Aggregation in Natural Language Generation.</title>
<date>1993</date>
<booktitle>In Giovanni Adorni and Michael Zock (eds.) Trends in Natural Language Generation: An Artificial Intelligence Perspective.</booktitle>
<contexts>
<context position="2246" citStr="Dalianis &amp; Hovy, 1993" startWordPosition="323" endWordPosition="326"> systems. More sentences were aggregated without than with the use of an explicit sign, such as a connective or a (semi-)colon. Mots-clés - Keywords abstracting, sentence, aggregation, synonymy, conﬂation 1 Introduction and Motivation Research on automatic abstracting has mainly stopped at content selectionl (see Kupiec et al., 1995; Marcu, 1997; Barzilay &amp; Elhadad, 1997). While there are notable contributions on 1 Summarization proper may be divided into two stages of content selection and content condensation. Choy—Kim CH UAH aggregation from text generation (see Dalianis, 1999; Shaw, 1998; Dalianis &amp; Hovy, 1993), the work is of little immediate benefit to summarization by sentence extraction. The simple made-up sentences aggregated (see Dalianis, l999:386) do not reﬂect the complex state of affairs in documents such as scientific and technical journal articles with urgent need for abstracts2. If studies on summarization are to benefit real applications, then research must reﬂect real contexts. In the aforementioned studies, sentences are almost always aggregated with the use of an explicit sign, a connective or a (semi-)colon. But explicit signs restrict the number of units that may be combined at an</context>
<context position="3819" citStr="Dalianis &amp; Hovy (1993" startWordPosition="566" endWordPosition="569"> abstracting reports on some preferred patterns in aggregation, and prerequisites and difficulties that an abstracting system might face. The paper does not propose which pattern or connective to use, both of which depends in part on what and how one wants to communicate selected information. While Section 2 describes the study method, Section 3 gives some data on the distribution of number of full text (ft-) sentences used to write a sentence in an abstract (ab-) and common patterns in abstracting. The paper ends with a discussion and suggestions for future work. 1.2 Aggregation: A Deﬁnition Dalianis &amp; Hovy (1993:90), who worked on “removal of redundancy” during generation, say that Mann &amp; Moore (1980) were the first to use aggregation, although Paice (1981) was reported (in Paice, l990:l75) to have coined the term to mean “the idea of adding adjacent sentences”. To refer to this sub-process in the context of abstracting, the term with the underlying meaning of ‘combining sentences’ will be retained, but with the stipulations of “removal of redundancy”, and “adjacent” removed. Not only is deletion not necessarily implicated3, but sentences aggregated need not be adjacent. For a survey of definitions f</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Dalianis, Hovy, 1993</marker>
<rawString>Dalianis, H. &amp; Hovy, E. (1993) Aggregation in Natural Language Generation. In Giovanni Adorni and Michael Zock (eds.) Trends in Natural Language Generation: An Artificial Intelligence Perspective.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<date>1993</date>
<booktitle>Fourth European Workshop, EWNLG ’93,</booktitle>
<pages>88--105</pages>
<location>Pisa, Italy,</location>
<marker>1993</marker>
<rawString>Fourth European Workshop, EWNLG ’93, Pisa, Italy, April 1993, pp. 88-105.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>E Ehrlich</author>
<author>D Murphy</author>
</authors>
<title>Concise Index to English.</title>
<date>1974</date>
<publisher>McGraW-Hill Book Co..</publisher>
<location>New York:</location>
<contexts>
<context position="16290" citStr="Ehrlich &amp; Murphy (1974" startWordPosition="2513" endWordPosition="2516">n Author Abstracting the sex ratio biasing mechanism in Sdumicola cannot be modiﬁed to control the sex or the sex ratio variance . [D-6-2] A The sex ratio biasing mechanism in this species, therefore, apparently only allows control of the mean sex ratio but not of its variance. [A-1-7; besl-9946237] 3. 2.3 VVith (Semi—)c0l0n In aggregations with a semi-colon or colon, the punctuation substitutes for the implicit semantic relation which has been expressly omitted. Aggregations with a (semi-)colon as with other aggregation types, are accompanied by Various condensation sub-processes. Semi-colon Ehrlich &amp; Murphy (1974:111) say that “When no close relationship exists between two independent clauses, a semicolon can be used to join them”. C3: [X]g + [Y]g A [X (semi-)colon Y]g While this makes the semicolon a convenient means for combining just about any two clauses, most of the clauses aggregated in the present study are related. (10) The most abundant prey organisms brought to the nest were Aphidoidea (48.1%), followed by Psocoptera (12.5%), [R-9-4] Only three spiders (two lycosids and one salticid) were brought to the nests. [R-9-5] A The majority of prey captured by ants were Aphidoidea (48.1%) and Psocop</context>
<context position="17847" citStr="Ehrlich &amp; Murphy, 1974" startWordPosition="2762" endWordPosition="2765">mpty balloon produced by some species of empidine ﬂies has been hypothesized to be a sexually selected trait. [D-4- 1] A Both male body size and balloon size are important components in determining male mating success; &lt;semi-colon&gt; however, the empty balloon does not appear to play a typical role as a sexually selected ornament. [A-1-11; besl-9945161] Colon Colons are used “to set off a series of words, phrases, or clauses from the rest of a sentence, to restate, explain or illustrate a statement immediately before it; to replace a semicolon for stylistic purposes [to break between clauses]” (Ehrlich &amp; Murphy, 1974:25-27). In the study corpus, there were more examples of aggregation with a colon than with a semi-colon. (12) a conspicuous male secondary sexual characteristic i-i=i—t-he-eeui=t-sl=i-i-p of the wolf spider Schizocosa ocreata (-I=Iei=it-z-) (Araneae: Lycosidae). [I-3-2] &apos; . , -- - :- &apos; :- &apos; -;. --= =- -- - amale secondarysexual characteristic, a conspicuous tuft of bristles and dark pigmentation on the tibia a1=id—patel-1-a of the first pair of legs of ma_t_u_r_e male S. ocreata, [I-5-3] A Males of the brush-legged wolf spider, Schizocosa ocreata (Araneae: Lycosidae), possess a conspicuous m</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Ehrlich, Murphy, 1974</marker>
<rawString>Ehrlich, E. &amp; Murphy, D. (1974) Concise Index to English. New York: McGraW-Hill Book Co..</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>J Kupiec</author>
<author>J Pedersen</author>
</authors>
<title>A Trainable Document Summarizer.</title>
<date>1995</date>
<booktitle>Proc. of the 18th Annual Intl. ACM SIGIR Conference on Research and Development on Information Retrieval,</booktitle>
<pages>68--73</pages>
<location>Seattle, Washington USA.</location>
<marker>Kupiec, Pedersen, 1995</marker>
<rawString>Kupiec, J., Pedersen, J ., &amp; Chen, F. (1995) A Trainable Document Summarizer. Proc. of the 18th Annual Intl. ACM SIGIR Conference on Research and Development on Information Retrieval, pp. 68-73. Seattle, Washington USA. July 1995.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>G Leech</author>
<author>J Svartvik</author>
</authors>
<title>Communicative Grammar of English.</title>
<date>1975</date>
<publisher>Longman.</publisher>
<location>London:</location>
<marker>Leech, Svartvik, 1975</marker>
<rawString>Leech, G. &amp; Svartvik, J . (1975)A Communicative Grammar of English. London: Longman.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>W C Mann</author>
<author>J A Moore</author>
</authors>
<title>Computer as Author - Results and Prospects. Research report ISI/RR-79-82,</title>
<date>1980</date>
<institution>University of Southern California Information Sciences Institute, Marina del Rey.</institution>
<contexts>
<context position="3910" citStr="Mann &amp; Moore (1980)" startWordPosition="580" endWordPosition="583">lties that an abstracting system might face. The paper does not propose which pattern or connective to use, both of which depends in part on what and how one wants to communicate selected information. While Section 2 describes the study method, Section 3 gives some data on the distribution of number of full text (ft-) sentences used to write a sentence in an abstract (ab-) and common patterns in abstracting. The paper ends with a discussion and suggestions for future work. 1.2 Aggregation: A Deﬁnition Dalianis &amp; Hovy (1993:90), who worked on “removal of redundancy” during generation, say that Mann &amp; Moore (1980) were the first to use aggregation, although Paice (1981) was reported (in Paice, l990:l75) to have coined the term to mean “the idea of adding adjacent sentences”. To refer to this sub-process in the context of abstracting, the term with the underlying meaning of ‘combining sentences’ will be retained, but with the stipulations of “removal of redundancy”, and “adjacent” removed. Not only is deletion not necessarily implicated3, but sentences aggregated need not be adjacent. For a survey of definitions for aggregation, see Reape &amp; Mellish (1999). 2 Method Fifty-seven articles from two journals</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Mann, Moore, 1980</marker>
<rawString>Mann, W.C. &amp; Moore, J .A (1980) Computer as Author - Results and Prospects. Research report ISI/RR-79-82, University of Southern California Information Sciences Institute, Marina del Rey.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>D Marcu</author>
</authors>
<title>From Discourse Structures to Text Summaries.</title>
<date>1997</date>
<booktitle>Proc. of the ACL’97/EACL’97 Workshop on Intelligent Scalable Text Summarization,</booktitle>
<pages>82--88</pages>
<location>Madrid,</location>
<contexts>
<context position="1971" citStr="Marcu, 1997" startWordPosition="284" endWordPosition="285"> comparison of document and abstract, this reconnaissance study reports on some preferred patterns in aggregation when authors write abstracts for journal articles on biology. The paper also discusses some prerequisites and difficulties anticipated for abstracting systems. More sentences were aggregated without than with the use of an explicit sign, such as a connective or a (semi-)colon. Mots-clés - Keywords abstracting, sentence, aggregation, synonymy, conﬂation 1 Introduction and Motivation Research on automatic abstracting has mainly stopped at content selectionl (see Kupiec et al., 1995; Marcu, 1997; Barzilay &amp; Elhadad, 1997). While there are notable contributions on 1 Summarization proper may be divided into two stages of content selection and content condensation. Choy—Kim CH UAH aggregation from text generation (see Dalianis, 1999; Shaw, 1998; Dalianis &amp; Hovy, 1993), the work is of little immediate benefit to summarization by sentence extraction. The simple made-up sentences aggregated (see Dalianis, l999:386) do not reﬂect the complex state of affairs in documents such as scientific and technical journal articles with urgent need for abstracts2. If studies on summarization are to ben</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Marcu, 1997</marker>
<rawString>Marcu, D. (1997) From Discourse Structures to Text Summaries. Proc. of the ACL’97/EACL’97 Workshop on Intelligent Scalable Text Summarization, pp. 82-88, Universidad Nacional de Educacion a Distancia, Madrid, Spain. July 11.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>C D Paice</author>
</authors>
<title>The Automatic Generation of Literature Abstracts: An Approach Based on the Identification of Self-Indicating Phrases.</title>
<date>1981</date>
<booktitle>Information Retrieval Research,</booktitle>
<pages>172--191</pages>
<editor>In R.N. Oddy, Robertson, S.E., van Rijsbergen, C.J. &amp; Williams, P.W. (eds.)</editor>
<contexts>
<context position="3967" citStr="Paice (1981)" startWordPosition="591" endWordPosition="592">propose which pattern or connective to use, both of which depends in part on what and how one wants to communicate selected information. While Section 2 describes the study method, Section 3 gives some data on the distribution of number of full text (ft-) sentences used to write a sentence in an abstract (ab-) and common patterns in abstracting. The paper ends with a discussion and suggestions for future work. 1.2 Aggregation: A Deﬁnition Dalianis &amp; Hovy (1993:90), who worked on “removal of redundancy” during generation, say that Mann &amp; Moore (1980) were the first to use aggregation, although Paice (1981) was reported (in Paice, l990:l75) to have coined the term to mean “the idea of adding adjacent sentences”. To refer to this sub-process in the context of abstracting, the term with the underlying meaning of ‘combining sentences’ will be retained, but with the stipulations of “removal of redundancy”, and “adjacent” removed. Not only is deletion not necessarily implicated3, but sentences aggregated need not be adjacent. For a survey of definitions for aggregation, see Reape &amp; Mellish (1999). 2 Method Fifty-seven articles from two journals, Behavioral Ecology and Sociobiology (bes) and Oecologia</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Paice, 1981</marker>
<rawString>Paice, C.D. (1981) The Automatic Generation of Literature Abstracts: An Approach Based on the Identification of Self-Indicating Phrases. In R.N. Oddy, Robertson, S.E., van Rijsbergen, C.J. &amp; Williams, P.W. (eds.) Information Retrieval Research, pp. 172-191.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>C D Paice</author>
</authors>
<title>Constructing Literature Abstracts by Computer:</title>
<date>1990</date>
<booktitle>Techniques and Prospects. Info. Processing &amp; Management</booktitle>
<volume>26</volume>
<issue>1</issue>
<pages>171--186</pages>
<marker>Paice, 1990</marker>
<rawString>Paice, C.D. (1990) Constructing Literature Abstracts by Computer: Techniques and Prospects. Info. Processing &amp; Management 26(1): 171-186.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>M Reape</author>
<author>C Mellish</author>
</authors>
<title>Just What is Aggregation Anyway?</title>
<date>1999</date>
<booktitle>Proc. of the 7th European Workshop on Natural Language Generation,</booktitle>
<pages>20--29</pages>
<location>Toulouse,</location>
<contexts>
<context position="4461" citStr="Reape &amp; Mellish (1999)" startWordPosition="666" endWordPosition="669">“removal of redundancy” during generation, say that Mann &amp; Moore (1980) were the first to use aggregation, although Paice (1981) was reported (in Paice, l990:l75) to have coined the term to mean “the idea of adding adjacent sentences”. To refer to this sub-process in the context of abstracting, the term with the underlying meaning of ‘combining sentences’ will be retained, but with the stipulations of “removal of redundancy”, and “adjacent” removed. Not only is deletion not necessarily implicated3, but sentences aggregated need not be adjacent. For a survey of definitions for aggregation, see Reape &amp; Mellish (1999). 2 Method Fifty-seven articles from two journals, Behavioral Ecology and Sociobiology (bes) and Oecologia (oec) (Springer-Verlag Publications) were downloaded for the study. All articles have the basic sections of Abstract (A), Introduction (1), Method (M), Results (R) and Discussion (D). For identification purposes, all sentences in full text and abstract were given a code which indicates its location in the document. For example, a sentence with location code [R-2-1] is the first sentence in the second paragraph of the Results section. On the basis of verbatim matches, similarity in stem an</context>
<context position="7941" citStr="Reape &amp; Mellish (1999" startWordPosition="1212" endWordPosition="1215">n _ Section Sectlon Introduction Method Results Discussion Introduction 57+(28.9) Method 12 ( 6.1) 10 ( 5.1) Results 5 ( 2.5) 9 (4.6) 31 (15.7) Discussion 11( 5.6) 5 (2.5) 27 (13.7) 30 (15.2) + No. of sentences (percentage) Eighteen percent of ab-sentences has its source in sentences that were immediately adjacent. The implication for aggregation is that adjacent sentences are more likely to be on Ch0y—Kim CH UAH the same topic than sentences from different paragraphs/sections, and the anaphor probably refers to an element mentioned in the preceding sentence. 3.2 Categorization of aggregation Reape &amp; Mellish (1999:23-25) proposed a four-category typology for aggregation. Conceptual aggregation was distinguished from semantic and lexical aggregations. While the latter two presumptively involve linguistic knowledge, the examples given do not appear to be far different from that of conceptual aggregation which implicates world/domain. However, on the basis of whether an explicit sign was used or not, we propose three categories of aggregation. If the explicit sign is a connective or (semi-)colon, then CONNECTIVE or (SEMI-)COLON respectively, and if no sign was used, then CONFLATION. In the last category o</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Reape, Mellish, 1999</marker>
<rawString>Reape, M. &amp; Mellish, C. (1999) Just What is Aggregation Anyway? Proc. of the 7th European Workshop on Natural Language Generation, pp. 20-29, Toulouse, France, 13-14 May, 1999.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>J Shaw</author>
</authors>
<title>Clause Aggregation Using Linguistic Knowledge.</title>
<date>1998</date>
<booktitle>Proc. of the 9th International Workshop on Natural Language Processing,</booktitle>
<pages>138--147</pages>
<location>Niagara-on-Lake, Ontario, Canada,</location>
<contexts>
<context position="2222" citStr="Shaw, 1998" startWordPosition="321" endWordPosition="322"> abstracting systems. More sentences were aggregated without than with the use of an explicit sign, such as a connective or a (semi-)colon. Mots-clés - Keywords abstracting, sentence, aggregation, synonymy, conﬂation 1 Introduction and Motivation Research on automatic abstracting has mainly stopped at content selectionl (see Kupiec et al., 1995; Marcu, 1997; Barzilay &amp; Elhadad, 1997). While there are notable contributions on 1 Summarization proper may be divided into two stages of content selection and content condensation. Choy—Kim CH UAH aggregation from text generation (see Dalianis, 1999; Shaw, 1998; Dalianis &amp; Hovy, 1993), the work is of little immediate benefit to summarization by sentence extraction. The simple made-up sentences aggregated (see Dalianis, l999:386) do not reﬂect the complex state of affairs in documents such as scientific and technical journal articles with urgent need for abstracts2. If studies on summarization are to benefit real applications, then research must reﬂect real contexts. In the aforementioned studies, sentences are almost always aggregated with the use of an explicit sign, a connective or a (semi-)colon. But explicit signs restrict the number of units th</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Shaw, 1998</marker>
<rawString>Shaw, J. (1998) Clause Aggregation Using Linguistic Knowledge. Proc. of the 9th International Workshop on Natural Language Processing, pp. 138-147, Niagara-on-Lake, Ontario, Canada, 5-7 Aug. Appendix Table A1. Statistics on corpus Full-text Abstract Reduction factor (RF) Corpus size 7938 sn+; 175,613 wd 534 sn; 11,975 wd 7938:534 = 15:1;</rawString>
</citation>
</citationList>
</algorithm>
</algorithms>