<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<algorithms version="110505">
<algorithm name="ParsCit" version="110505">
<citationList>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Pierre Baldi</author>
<author>Soren Brunak</author>
</authors>
<title>Bioinformatics: The Machine Learning Approach (Adaptive Computation and Machine Learning).</title>
<date>1998</date>
<publisher>MIT Press.</publisher>
<marker>Baldi, Brunak, 1998</marker>
<rawString>Baldi, Pierre and Soren Brunak. 1998. Bioinformatics: The Machine Learning Approach (Adaptive Computation and Machine Learning). MIT Press.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Jean Berstel</author>
</authors>
<title>Transductions and Context-Free Languages. Teubner Studienbucher:</title>
<date>1979</date>
<location>Stuttgart.</location>
<marker>Berstel, 1979</marker>
<rawString>Berstel, Jean. 1979. Transductions and Context-Free Languages. Teubner Studienbucher: Stuttgart.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Corinna Cortes</author>
<author>Mehryar Mohri</author>
</authors>
<title>Context-Free Recognition with Weighted Automata.</title>
<date>2000</date>
<journal>Grammars,</journal>
<pages>3--2</pages>
<marker>Cortes, Mohri, 2000</marker>
<rawString>Cortes, Corinna and Mehryar Mohri. 2000. Context-Free Recognition with Weighted Automata. Grammars, 3(2-3).</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Culik Karel</author>
<author>Jarkko Kari</author>
</authors>
<title>Digital images and formal languages.</title>
<date>1997</date>
<booktitle>In Grzegorz Rozenberg and Arto Salomaa, editors, Handbook of Formal Languages.</booktitle>
<pages>599--616</pages>
<publisher>Springer,</publisher>
<marker>Karel, Kari, 1997</marker>
<rawString>Culik II, Karel and Jarkko Kari. 1997. Digital images and formal languages. In Grzegorz Rozenberg and Arto Salomaa, editors, Handbook of Formal Languages. Springer, pages 599-616.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Samuel Eilenberg</author>
</authors>
<date>1974</date>
<journal>Automata, Languages and Machines,</journal>
<volume>volume</volume>
<publisher>A. Academic Press.</publisher>
<marker>Eilenberg, 1974</marker>
<rawString>Eilenberg, Samuel. 1974. Automata, Languages and Machines, volume A. Academic Press.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Grimley Evans</author>
<author>E</author>
</authors>
<title>Approximating context-free grammars with a ﬁnite-state calculus.</title>
<date>1997</date>
<booktitle>In 35th Annual Meeting of the ACL,</booktitle>
<pages>452--459</pages>
<marker>Evans, E, 1997</marker>
<rawString>Grimley Evans, E. 1997. Approximating context-free grammars with a ﬁnite-state calculus. In 35th Annual Meeting of the ACL, pages 452-459.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>M Johnson</author>
</authors>
<title>Finite-state approximation of constraint-based grammars using left-corner grammar transforms.</title>
<date>1998</date>
<booktitle>In 36th Annual Meeting of the ACL and I 7th International Conference on Computational Linguistics,</booktitle>
<volume>1</volume>
<pages>619--623</pages>
<marker>Johnson, 1998</marker>
<rawString>Johnson, M. 1998. Finite-state approximation of constraint-based grammars using left-corner grammar transforms. In 36th Annual Meeting of the ACL and I 7th International Conference on Computational Linguistics, volume 1, pages 619-623.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Mehryar Mohri</author>
</authors>
<date>1997</date>
<booktitle>Finite-State Transducers in Language and Speech Processing. Computational Linguistics,</booktitle>
<pages>23--2</pages>
<marker>Mohri, 1997</marker>
<rawString>Mohri, Mehryar. 1997. Finite-State Transducers in Language and Speech Processing. Computational Linguistics, 23:2.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Mehryar Mohri</author>
</authors>
<title>General Algebraic Frameworks and Algorithms for Shortest-Distance Problems.</title>
<date>1998</date>
<journal>Technical Memorandum 981210-10TM, AT&amp;T Labs - Research,</journal>
<volume>62</volume>
<pages>pages.</pages>
<marker>Mohri, 1998</marker>
<rawString>Mohri, Mehryar. 1998. General Algebraic Frameworks and Algorithms for Shortest-Distance Problems. Technical Memorandum 981210-10TM, AT&amp;T Labs - Research, 62 pages.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Mehryar Mohri</author>
</authors>
<title>Generic Epsilon-Removal Algorithm for Weighted Automata.</title>
<date>2000</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the Fifth International Conference on Implementation and Application of Automata (CIAA’2000),</booktitle>
<location>London, Ontario, Canada,</location>
<marker>Mohri, 2000</marker>
<rawString>Mohri, Mehryar. 2000a. Generic Epsilon-Removal Algorithm for Weighted Automata. In Proceedings of the Fifth International Conference on Implementation and Application of Automata (CIAA’2000), London, Ontario, Canada, July.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Mehryar Mohri Mohri</author>
<author>Mehryar</author>
</authors>
<title>Minimization algorithms for sequential transducers.</title>
<date>2000</date>
<journal>Theoretical Computer Science,</journal>
<volume>234</volume>
<pages>177--201</pages>
<marker>Mohri, Mehryar, 2000</marker>
<rawString>Mehryar Mohri Mohri, Mehryar. 2000b. Minimization algorithms for sequential transducers. Theoretical Computer Science, 234: 177-201, March.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Mehryar Mohri</author>
</authors>
<title>Weighted Grammar Tools: the GRM Library.</title>
<date>2001</date>
<booktitle>In Jean claude Junqua and Gertjan</booktitle>
<pages>165--186</pages>
<editor>van Noord, editors,</editor>
<publisher>Kluwer Academic Publishers, The Netherlands,</publisher>
<marker>Mohri, 2001</marker>
<rawString>Mohri, Mehryar. 2001. Weighted Grammar Tools: the GRM Library. In Jean claude Junqua and Gertjan van Noord, editors, Robustness in Language and Speech Technology. Kluwer Academic Publishers, The Netherlands, pages 165-186.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Mehryar Mohri</author>
<author>Mark-Jan Nederhof</author>
</authors>
<title>Regular Approximation of Context-Free Grammars through Transformation.</title>
<date>2001</date>
<booktitle>In Jean claude Junqua and Gertjan</booktitle>
<pages>153--163</pages>
<editor>van Noord, editors,</editor>
<publisher>Kluwer Academic Publishers, The Netherlands,</publisher>
<marker>Mohri, Nederhof, 2001</marker>
<rawString>Mohri, Mehryar and Mark-Jan Nederhof. 2001. Regular Approximation of Context-Free Grammars through Transformation. In Jean claude Junqua and Gertjan van Noord, editors, Robustness in Language and Speech Technology. Kluwer Academic Publishers, The Netherlands, pages 153-163.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Mehryar Mohri</author>
<author>Fernando C N Pereira</author>
</authors>
<title>Dynamic Compilation of Weighted Context-Free Grammars.</title>
<date>1998</date>
<booktitle>In 36th Meeting of the Association for Computational Linguistics (ACL ’98), Proceedings of the Conference,</booktitle>
<publisher>ACL.</publisher>
<location>Montréal, Québec, Canada.</location>
<marker>Mohri, Pereira, 1998</marker>
<rawString>Mohri, Mehryar and Fernando C. N. Pereira. 1998. Dynamic Compilation of Weighted Context-Free Grammars. In 36th Meeting of the Association for Computational Linguistics (ACL ’98), Proceedings of the Conference, Montréal, Québec, Canada. ACL.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Mehryar Mohri</author>
<author>Fernando C N Pereira</author>
<author>Michael Riley</author>
</authors>
<title>Weighted Automata in Text and Speech Processing.</title>
<date>1996</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the 12th biennial European Conference on Artiﬁcial Intelligence (ECAI-96), Workshop on Extended ﬁnite state models of language,</booktitle>
<publisher>ECAI.</publisher>
<location>Budapest, Hungary.</location>
<marker>Mohri, Pereira, Riley, 1996</marker>
<rawString>Mohri, Mehryar, Fernando C. N. Pereira, and Michael Riley. 1996. Weighted Automata in Text and Speech Processing. In Proceedings of the 12th biennial European Conference on Artiﬁcial Intelligence (ECAI-96), Workshop on Extended ﬁnite state models of language, Budapest, Hungary. ECAI.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Mehryar Mohri</author>
<author>Michael Riley</author>
</authors>
<title>Integrated Context-Dependent Networks in Very Large Vocabulary Speech Recognition.</title>
<date>1999</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the 6th European Conference on Speech Communication and Technology (Eurospeech ’99),</booktitle>
<location>Budapest, Hungary.</location>
<marker>Mohri, Riley, 1999</marker>
<rawString>Mohri, Mehryar and Michael Riley. 1999. Integrated Context-Dependent Networks in Very Large Vocabulary Speech Recognition. In Proceedings of the 6th European Conference on Speech Communication and Technology (Eurospeech ’99), Budapest, Hungary.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Mehryar Mohri</author>
<author>Michael Riley</author>
<author>Don Hindle</author>
<author>Andrej Ljolje</author>
<author>Fernando C N Pereira</author>
</authors>
<title>Full Expansion of Context-Dependent Networks in Large Vocabulary Speech Recognition.</title>
<date>1998</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the International Conference on Acoustics, Speech, and Signal Processing (ICASSP ’98),</booktitle>
<location>Seattle, Washington.</location>
<contexts>
<context position="5909" citStr="Mohri et al. 1998" startWordPosition="907" endWordPosition="910"> at that state. Each transition is labeled with :3 : y / 11) where :3 is the input label, y the output label and 11) its weight. The symbol 6 denotes the empty string. a e/1.882 data/10.89 data/6.603 data/9_26g 0 good/11.11 0 good/9.394 4 e/3.537 day/13.97 8/3.961 Figure 2: Toy bigram model represented by a weighted automaton. 2.2 Speech recognition components Weighted ﬁnite-state transducers provide a common and natural representation for all the components used in the search stage of speech recognition systems: HMM models, context-dependency, pronunciation dictionaries, and language models (Mohri et al. 1998). We brieﬂy illustrate this in the following. Most statistical grammars used in speech recognition can be represented by weighted automata. Figure 2 shows a toy grammar corresponding to an n-gram model restricted to a few words. In particular, n-gram models can be represented very naturally by weighted automata. The construction is based on associating one state to each possible (n — 1)-gram sequence. For example, in the bigram model of ﬁgure 2, state 1 corresponds to the word “good”, state 2 to the word “day” and state 3 to the word “data”. More general weighted grammars such as weighted cont</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Mohri, Riley, Hindle, Ljolje, Pereira, 1998</marker>
<rawString>Mohri, Mehryar, Michael Riley, Don Hindle, Andrej Ljolje, and Fernando C. N. Pereira. 1998. Full Expansion of Context-Dependent Networks in Large Vocabulary Speech Recognition. In Proceedings of the International Conference on Acoustics, Speech, and Signal Processing (ICASSP ’98), Seattle, Washington.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Mehryar Mohri</author>
<author>Richard Sproat</author>
</authors>
<title>An Efﬁcient Compiler for Weighted Rewrite Rules.</title>
<date>1996</date>
<booktitle>In 34th Meeting of the Association for Computational Linguistics (ACL ’96), Proceedings of the Conference,</booktitle>
<publisher>ACL.</publisher>
<location>Santa Cruz, California.</location>
<marker>Mohri, Sproat, 1996</marker>
<rawString>Mohri, Mehryar and Richard Sproat. 1996. An Efﬁcient Compiler for Weighted Rewrite Rules. In 34th Meeting of the Association for Computational Linguistics (ACL ’96), Proceedings of the Conference, Santa Cruz, California. ACL.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>M-J Nederhof</author>
</authors>
<title>Practical experiments with regular approximation of context-free languages.</title>
<date>2000</date>
<journal>Computational Linguistics,</journal>
<volume>26</volume>
<issue>1</issue>
<marker>Nederhof, 2000</marker>
<rawString>Nederhof, M.-J. 2000. Practical experiments with regular approximation of context-free languages. Computational Linguistics, 26(1).</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>F C N Pereira</author>
<author>R N Wright</author>
</authors>
<title>Finite-state approximation of phrase-structure grammars.</title>
<date>1997</date>
<booktitle>Finite-State Language Processing.</booktitle>
<pages>149--173</pages>
<editor>In E. Roche and Y. Schabes, editors,</editor>
<publisher>MIT Press,</publisher>
<marker>Pereira, Wright, 1997</marker>
<rawString>Pereira, F.C.N. and R.N. Wright. 1997. Finite-state approximation of phrase-structure grammars. In E. Roche and Y. Schabes, editors, Finite-State Language Processing. MIT Press, pages 149-173.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Fernando C N Pereira</author>
<author>Michael Riley</author>
</authors>
<title>Finite State Language Processing, chapter Weighted Rational Transductions and their Application to Human Language Processing.</title>
<date>1997</date>
<publisher>The MIT Press.</publisher>
<marker>Pereira, Riley, 1997</marker>
<rawString>Pereira, Fernando C. N. and Michael Riley, 1997. Finite State Language Processing, chapter Weighted Rational Transductions and their Application to Human Language Processing. The MIT Press.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Vladimir Vapnik</author>
</authors>
<title>The Nature of Statistical Learning Theory. Springer-Verlag:</title>
<date>1995</date>
<location>BerlinNew York.</location>
<marker>Vapnik, 1995</marker>
<rawString>Vapnik, Vladimir. 1995. The Nature of Statistical Learning Theory. Springer-Verlag: BerlinNew York.</rawString>
</citation>
</citationList>
</algorithm>
</algorithms>