<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<algorithms version="110505">
<algorithm name="ParsCit" version="110505">
<citationList>
<citation valid="false">
<title>0 Computational semantics: the semantics of the temporal expressions (for example, the set of expressions referring to past events) along with the semantics of grammatical tenses 4The goal of the presented system is to detect only the expressions which modify the temporal parameters of the sentence. Hence, unlike some other studies on temporal tagging or armotaiton (Mani et al.2001), we deliberately ruled out expressions which do not answer to the question when. Nikolai Vazov is a constituent element of the aspecto-temporal value of the sentence (Battistelli2000; Vazov1999).</title>
<marker></marker>
<rawString>(Ben Hazez and Minel2000). 0 Computational semantics: the semantics of the temporal expressions (for example, the set of expressions referring to past events) along with the semantics of grammatical tenses 4The goal of the presented system is to detect only the expressions which modify the temporal parameters of the sentence. Hence, unlike some other studies on temporal tagging or armotaiton (Mani et al.2001), we deliberately ruled out expressions which do not answer to the question when. Nikolai Vazov is a constituent element of the aspecto-temporal value of the sentence (Battistelli2000; Vazov1999).</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<title>o Parsing: the temporal expressions are syntactic constituents whose identiﬁcation by parsD. Battistelli.</title>
<date>2000</date>
<tech>Ph.D. thesis,</tech>
<institution>Université Paris - Sorbonne.</institution>
<marker>2000</marker>
<rawString>o Parsing: the temporal expressions are syntactic constituents whose identiﬁcation by parsD. Battistelli. 2000. Passer du texte a une se’quence d ’images, analyse spatio-temporelle de textes, modelisation et réalisation informatique (systéme SPAT). Ph.D. thesis, Université Paris - Sorbonne.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>S Ben Hazez</author>
<author>J -L Minel</author>
</authors>
<title>Designing tasks of identiﬁcation of complex patterns used for text-ﬁltering.</title>
<date>2000</date>
<booktitle>In RIAO,</booktitle>
<pages>1558--1567</pages>
<marker>Hazez, Minel, 2000</marker>
<rawString>S. Ben Hazez and J .-L. Minel. 2000. Designing tasks of identiﬁcation of complex patterns used for text-ﬁltering. In RIAO, pages 1558-1567.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>E Cartier Berri</author>
<author>J -P Desclés</author>
<author>A Jackiewicz</author>
<author>J -L Minel</author>
</authors>
<title>Filtrage automatique des textes.</title>
<date>1996</date>
<booktitle>In Natural Language Processing and Industrial Applications,</booktitle>
<pages>22--35</pages>
<location>Moncton, N.B.,</location>
<marker>Berri, Desclés, Jackiewicz, Minel, 1996</marker>
<rawString>J . Berri, E. Cartier, J .-P. Desclés, A. Jackiewicz, and J .-L. Minel. 1996. Filtrage automatique des textes. In Natural Language Processing and Industrial Applications, pages 22-35, Moncton, N.B., Canada.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>M Bras</author>
<author>F Molinés</author>
</authors>
<title>Adverbials of temporal location: Linguisitic description and automatic processing.</title>
<date>1993</date>
<booktitle>Akten des 26 Linguistischen Kolloquium,</booktitle>
<pages>137--146</pages>
<editor>In J . Darski and Z. Vetulani, editors, Sprache-Kommunikation-Informatik,</editor>
<publisher>Max Niemeyer Verlag.</publisher>
<marker>Bras, Molinés, 1993</marker>
<rawString>M. Bras and F. Molinés. 1993. Adverbials of temporal location: Linguisitic description and automatic processing. In J . Darski and Z. Vetulani, editors, Sprache-Kommunikation-Informatik, Akten des 26 Linguistischen Kolloquium, pages 137-146. Max Niemeyer Verlag.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>M Charolles</author>
</authors>
<title>Reconnaissance et délimitation des univers d’énonciation introduits par une expresion selon x et contraction automatique de textes.</title>
<date>1997</date>
<booktitle>In Joumee d’etude, Filtrage des informations dans les textes, Paris. Association pour le Traitement Automatique des Langues (ATALA).</booktitle>
<marker>Charolles, 1997</marker>
<rawString>M. Charolles. 1997. Reconnaissance et délimitation des univers d’énonciation introduits par une expresion selon x et contraction automatique de textes. In Joumee d’etude, Filtrage des informations dans les textes, Paris. Association pour le Traitement Automatique des Langues (ATALA).</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>J-P Desclés</author>
<author>E Cartier</author>
<author>A Jackiewicz</author>
<author>J -L Minel</author>
</authors>
<title>Textual processing and contextual exploration method.</title>
<date>1997</date>
<booktitle>In CONTEXT’97,</booktitle>
<pages>189--197</pages>
<note>Brasil. Universidade Federal do Rio de Janeiro.</note>
<marker>Desclés, Cartier, Jackiewicz, Minel, 1997</marker>
<rawString>J.-P Desclés, E. Cartier, A. Jackiewicz, and J .-L. Minel. 1997. Textual processing and contextual exploration method. In CONTEXT’97, pages 189-197, Brasil. Universidade Federal do Rio de Janeiro.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>J -P Desclés</author>
</authors>
<title>Syste‘mes d ’exploration contextuelle. Co-texte et calcul du sens,</title>
<date>1997</date>
<pages>215--232</pages>
<institution>Presses Universitaires de Caen.</institution>
<marker>Desclés, 1997</marker>
<rawString>J .-P. Desclés, 1997. Syste‘mes d ’exploration contextuelle. Co-texte et calcul du sens, pages 215-232. Presses Universitaires de Caen.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>M Gagnon</author>
<author>G Lapalme</author>
</authors>
<title>From conceptual time to linguistic time.</title>
<date>1996</date>
<journal>Computational Linguistics,</journal>
<pages>22--1</pages>
<marker>Gagnon, Lapalme, 1996</marker>
<rawString>M. Gagnon and G. Lapalme. 1996. From conceptual time to linguistic time. Computational Linguistics, 22(1):91-127.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>L Gosselin</author>
</authors>
<title>Sémantique de la temporalité en francais, Un modele calculatoire et cognitif du temps et de l ’aspect. Champs linguistiques.</title>
<date>1996</date>
<publisher>Duculot.</publisher>
<marker>Gosselin, 1996</marker>
<rawString>L. Gosselin. 1996. Sémantique de la temporalité en francais, Un modele calculatoire et cognitif du temps et de l ’aspect. Champs linguistiques. Duculot.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>I Mani</author>
<author>L Ferro</author>
<author>B Sundheim</author>
<author>G Wilson</author>
</authors>
<title>Guidelines for armotating temporal information.</title>
<date>2001</date>
<booktitle>In Notebook Proceedings of Human Language Technology Conference</booktitle>
<pages>299--302</pages>
<location>San Diego, California,</location>
<marker>Mani, Ferro, Sundheim, Wilson, 2001</marker>
<rawString>I. Mani, L. Ferro, B. Sundheim, and G. Wilson. 2001. Guidelines for armotating temporal information. In Notebook Proceedings of Human Language Technology Conference 2001, pages 299-302, San Diego, California, March 18-21.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>J -L Minel</author>
<author>J-P Desclés</author>
</authors>
<title>Résumé Automatique et Filtrage des textes. Ingénierie des langues. Editions Hermes,</title>
<date>2000</date>
<location>Paris.</location>
<marker>Minel, Desclés, 2000</marker>
<rawString>J -L. Minel and J-P. Desclés. 2000. Résumé Automatique et Filtrage des textes. Ingénierie des langues. Editions Hermes, Paris.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>J -L Minel</author>
<author>J -P Desclés</author>
<author>E Cartier</author>
<author>G Crispino</author>
<author>S Ben Hazez</author>
<author>A Jackiewicz</author>
</authors>
<title>Résumé automatique par ﬁltrage sémantique d’informaitons dans des textes.</title>
<date>2000</date>
<journal>TSI,</journal>
<pages>1--23</pages>
<marker>Minel, Desclés, Cartier, Crispino, Hazez, Jackiewicz, 2000</marker>
<rawString>J .-L. Minel, J .-P. Desclés, E. Cartier, G. Crispino, S. Ben Hazez, and A. Jackiewicz. 2000. Résumé automatique par ﬁltrage sémantique d’informaitons dans des textes. TSI, X(X):1-23.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>N Vazov</author>
</authors>
<title>Context-scarming strategy in temporal reasoning.</title>
<date>1999</date>
<booktitle>In Modeling and Using Context ( Second Intemational and Interdisciplinary Conference, CONTEXT’99),</booktitle>
<pages>389--402</pages>
<publisher>Springer-Verlag.</publisher>
<marker>Vazov, 1999</marker>
<rawString>N. Vazov. 1999. Context-scarming strategy in temporal reasoning. In Modeling and Using Context ( Second Intemational and Interdisciplinary Conference, CONTEXT’99), pages 389-402. Springer-Verlag.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>H Verkuyl</author>
</authors>
<title>A theory of aspectuality. The interaction between temporal and atemporal structure. Cambridge Studies in Lingustics.</title>
<date>1993</date>
<publisher>Cambridge University Press.</publisher>
<marker>Verkuyl, 1993</marker>
<rawString>H. Verkuyl. 1993. A theory of aspectuality. The interaction between temporal and atemporal structure. Cambridge Studies in Lingustics. Cambridge University Press.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>B Webber</author>
</authors>
<title>Tense as discourse anaphor.</title>
<date>1988</date>
<journal>Computational Linguistics,</journal>
<pages>14--2</pages>
<marker>Webber, 1988</marker>
<rawString>B. Webber. 1988. Tense as discourse anaphor. Computational Linguistics, 14(2):61-73.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>D Wonsever</author>
<author>J -L Minel</author>
</authors>
<title>Contextual rules for text analysis.</title>
<date>2001</date>
<booktitle>In 2nd International conference on Intelligent Text Processing and Computational Linguistics CICLing-2001,</booktitle>
<location>Mexico City.</location>
<marker>Wonsever, Minel, 2001</marker>
<rawString>D. Wonsever and J .-L. Minel. 2001. Contextual rules for text analysis. In 2nd International conference on Intelligent Text Processing and Computational Linguistics CICLing-2001, Mexico City.</rawString>
</citation>
</citationList>
</algorithm>
</algorithms>