<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<algorithms version="110505">
<algorithm name="ParsCit" version="110505">
<citationList>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>J Cowie</author>
<author>L Guthrie</author>
<author>G Guthrie</author>
</authors>
<title>Lexical disambiguation using semantic annealing.</title>
<date>1992</date>
<booktitle>Proceedings of Coling-92,</booktitle>
<pages>359--365</pages>
<location>Nante,</location>
<contexts>
<context position="3648" citStr="Cowie et al., 1992" startWordPosition="532" endWordPosition="535">sted as early as in (Lesk, 1986) and (Hirst, 1987). An advantage of knowledge-rich approaches is their clarity and explicitness: it is easy to see why the algorithm makes a decision and on what information the decision is based. Additionally, as more lexical resources become available, knowledge-rich approaches become more affordable. Because of this, some recent works have presented modifications of the original Lesk’s algorithm based on the use of thesaurus, synonym dictionaries, different kinds of morphological normalization, etc. (VVilks and Stevenson, 1998, 1999), (Mahesh et al., 1997), (Cowie et al., 1992), (Yarowsky, 1992), (Pook and Catlett, 1988). In Lesk’s algorithm, a word sense is represented as the set of strings that form the definition of the sense: e.g., bankl = {“ﬁnanciaf’, “institute”}. The algorithm calculates the scores of a word sense on the basis of the intersection of this set with the senses of the words in the context and chooses the sense with the best scores. We improved the algorithm by introducing fuzzy comparison between such strings based on the use of a large synonym dictionary and derivational morphological normalization. We apply this improved algorithm to a large Sp</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Cowie, Guthrie, Guthrie, 1992</marker>
<rawString>Cowie J., Guthrie, L., and Guthrie, G. (1992) Lexical disambiguation using semantic annealing. Proceedings of Coling-92, Nante, France, pp. 359-365.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>G Hirst</author>
</authors>
<title>Semantic interpretation and resolution of ambiguity. Cambridge,</title>
<date>1987</date>
<publisher>Cambridge University Press.</publisher>
<contexts>
<context position="3079" citStr="Hirst, 1987" startWordPosition="452" endWordPosition="453">ries) still strings rather than senses: in the definition of bankl, is institute a school, a research center, a social structure, or an organization? Any NLP application of an explanatory dictionary requires sense disambiguation (VVSD) in such definitions. The problem of WSD is well investigated. The prevailing approaches are knowledge-poor statistical approaches (Manning and Shutze, 1999) based on bayesian classifiers, neural networks, support vector machines, and other purely statistical techniques. On the other hand, knowledge-rich approaches were suggested as early as in (Lesk, 1986) and (Hirst, 1987). An advantage of knowledge-rich approaches is their clarity and explicitness: it is easy to see why the algorithm makes a decision and on what information the decision is based. Additionally, as more lexical resources become available, knowledge-rich approaches become more affordable. Because of this, some recent works have presented modifications of the original Lesk’s algorithm based on the use of thesaurus, synonym dictionaries, different kinds of morphological normalization, etc. (VVilks and Stevenson, 1998, 1999), (Mahesh et al., 1997), (Cowie et al., 1992), (Yarowsky, 1992), (Pook and C</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Hirst, 1987</marker>
<rawString>Hirst, G. (1987) Semantic interpretation and resolution of ambiguity. Cambridge, Cambridge University Press.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Sh Edelman</author>
</authors>
<title>Similarity-based word-sense disambiguation.</title>
<date>1998</date>
<journal>Computational linguistics,</journal>
<volume>24</volume>
<pages>41--59</pages>
<marker>Edelman, 1998</marker>
<rawString>Karov, Ya. and Edelman, Sh. (1998), Similarity-based word-sense disambiguation. Computational linguistics, Vol. 24, pp. 41-59.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>M Lesk</author>
</authors>
<title>Automatic sense disambiguation using machine readable dictionaries: how to tell a pine cone from an ice cream cone.</title>
<date>1986</date>
<booktitle>Proceedings of ACM SIGDOC Conference.</booktitle>
<pages>24--26</pages>
<location>Toronto, Canada,</location>
<contexts>
<context position="3061" citStr="Lesk, 1986" startWordPosition="449" endWordPosition="450">existing dictionaries) still strings rather than senses: in the definition of bankl, is institute a school, a research center, a social structure, or an organization? Any NLP application of an explanatory dictionary requires sense disambiguation (VVSD) in such definitions. The problem of WSD is well investigated. The prevailing approaches are knowledge-poor statistical approaches (Manning and Shutze, 1999) based on bayesian classifiers, neural networks, support vector machines, and other purely statistical techniques. On the other hand, knowledge-rich approaches were suggested as early as in (Lesk, 1986) and (Hirst, 1987). An advantage of knowledge-rich approaches is their clarity and explicitness: it is easy to see why the algorithm makes a decision and on what information the decision is based. Additionally, as more lexical resources become available, knowledge-rich approaches become more affordable. Because of this, some recent works have presented modifications of the original Lesk’s algorithm based on the use of thesaurus, synonym dictionaries, different kinds of morphological normalization, etc. (VVilks and Stevenson, 1998, 1999), (Mahesh et al., 1997), (Cowie et al., 1992), (Yarowsky, </context>
</contexts>
<marker>Lesk, 1986</marker>
<rawString>Lesk, M. (1986), Automatic sense disambiguation using machine readable dictionaries: how to tell a pine cone from an ice cream cone. Proceedings of ACM SIGDOC Conference. Toronto, Canada, pp. 24-26.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>K Mahesh</author>
<author>S Nirenburg</author>
<author>S Beale</author>
<author>V Raskin</author>
<author>B Onyshkevich</author>
</authors>
<title>Word sense disambiguation: Why have statistics when we have these numbers?</title>
<date>1997</date>
<booktitle>Proceedings of 7”’ International Conference on Theoretical and methodological issues in machine translation. Santa Fe, NM,</booktitle>
<pages>151--159</pages>
<contexts>
<context position="3626" citStr="Mahesh et al., 1997" startWordPosition="528" endWordPosition="531">h approaches were suggested as early as in (Lesk, 1986) and (Hirst, 1987). An advantage of knowledge-rich approaches is their clarity and explicitness: it is easy to see why the algorithm makes a decision and on what information the decision is based. Additionally, as more lexical resources become available, knowledge-rich approaches become more affordable. Because of this, some recent works have presented modifications of the original Lesk’s algorithm based on the use of thesaurus, synonym dictionaries, different kinds of morphological normalization, etc. (VVilks and Stevenson, 1998, 1999), (Mahesh et al., 1997), (Cowie et al., 1992), (Yarowsky, 1992), (Pook and Catlett, 1988). In Lesk’s algorithm, a word sense is represented as the set of strings that form the definition of the sense: e.g., bankl = {“ﬁnanciaf’, “institute”}. The algorithm calculates the scores of a word sense on the basis of the intersection of this set with the senses of the words in the context and chooses the sense with the best scores. We improved the algorithm by introducing fuzzy comparison between such strings based on the use of a large synonym dictionary and derivational morphological normalization. We apply this improved a</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Mahesh, Nirenburg, Beale, Raskin, Onyshkevich, 1997</marker>
<rawString>Mahesh, K., Nirenburg, S., Beale, S., Raskin, V., and Onyshkevich, B. (1997) Word sense disambiguation: Why have statistics when we have these numbers? Proceedings of 7”’ International Conference on Theoretical and methodological issues in machine translation. Santa Fe, NM, pp. 151-159.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>C D Manning</author>
<author>H Shutze</author>
</authors>
<title>Foundations of statistical natural language processing.</title>
<date>1999</date>
<pages>680</pages>
<publisher>The MIT press,</publisher>
<location>Cambridge, MA,</location>
<contexts>
<context position="2859" citStr="Manning and Shutze, 1999" startWordPosition="419" endWordPosition="422">eﬁning words and the words being defined. But it is not: in fact, what is defined are not words but word senses: bankl is a ﬁnancial institute, while bank; is the edge of a river. However, the defining words are (in existing dictionaries) still strings rather than senses: in the definition of bankl, is institute a school, a research center, a social structure, or an organization? Any NLP application of an explanatory dictionary requires sense disambiguation (VVSD) in such definitions. The problem of WSD is well investigated. The prevailing approaches are knowledge-poor statistical approaches (Manning and Shutze, 1999) based on bayesian classifiers, neural networks, support vector machines, and other purely statistical techniques. On the other hand, knowledge-rich approaches were suggested as early as in (Lesk, 1986) and (Hirst, 1987). An advantage of knowledge-rich approaches is their clarity and explicitness: it is easy to see why the algorithm makes a decision and on what information the decision is based. Additionally, as more lexical resources become available, knowledge-rich approaches become more affordable. Because of this, some recent works have presented modifications of the original Lesk’s algori</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Manning, Shutze, 1999</marker>
<rawString>Manning, C. D. and Shutze, H. (1999), Foundations of statistical natural language processing. Cambridge, MA, The MIT press, 680 p.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>S McRoy</author>
</authors>
<title>Using multiple knowledge sources for word sense disambiguation.</title>
<date>1992</date>
<journal>Computational Linguistics,</journal>
<volume>18</volume>
<issue>1</issue>
<pages>1--30</pages>
<marker>McRoy, 1992</marker>
<rawString>McRoy, S. (1992) Using multiple knowledge sources for word sense disambiguation. Computational Linguistics, Vol. 18(1), pp. 1-30.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>S L Pook</author>
<author>J Catlett</author>
</authors>
<title>Making sense out of searching. Information outline 88, Sydney,</title>
<date>1988</date>
<booktitle>Proceedings of ACL 36/Coling I</booktitle>
<volume>7</volume>
<pages>148--157</pages>
<contexts>
<context position="3692" citStr="Pook and Catlett, 1988" startWordPosition="538" endWordPosition="541">rst, 1987). An advantage of knowledge-rich approaches is their clarity and explicitness: it is easy to see why the algorithm makes a decision and on what information the decision is based. Additionally, as more lexical resources become available, knowledge-rich approaches become more affordable. Because of this, some recent works have presented modifications of the original Lesk’s algorithm based on the use of thesaurus, synonym dictionaries, different kinds of morphological normalization, etc. (VVilks and Stevenson, 1998, 1999), (Mahesh et al., 1997), (Cowie et al., 1992), (Yarowsky, 1992), (Pook and Catlett, 1988). In Lesk’s algorithm, a word sense is represented as the set of strings that form the definition of the sense: e.g., bankl = {“ﬁnanciaf’, “institute”}. The algorithm calculates the scores of a word sense on the basis of the intersection of this set with the senses of the words in the context and chooses the sense with the best scores. We improved the algorithm by introducing fuzzy comparison between such strings based on the use of a large synonym dictionary and derivational morphological normalization. We apply this improved algorithm to a large Spanish explanatory dictionary (30000 entries)</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Pook, Catlett, 1988</marker>
<rawString>Pook, S. L. and Catlett, J. (1988) Making sense out of searching. Information outline 88, Sydney, pp 148-157 Wilks, Y. and Stevenson, M. (1998), Word sense disambiguation using optimized combination of knowledge sources. Proceedings of ACL 36/Coling I 7, 1398-1402.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Y Wilks</author>
<author>M Stevenson</author>
</authors>
<title>Combining weak knowledge sources for sense disambiguation.</title>
<date>1999</date>
<booktitle>Proceedings of IJCA1-99,</booktitle>
<pages>884--889</pages>
<marker>Wilks, Stevenson, 1999</marker>
<rawString>Wilks, Y. and Stevenson, M. (1999), Combining weak knowledge sources for sense disambiguation. Proceedings of IJCA1-99, 884-889.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<title>WordNet.&apos; an electronic lexical database.</title>
<date>1998</date>
<volume>423</volume>
<pages>p.</pages>
<editor>C. Fellbaum (ed.), MIT,</editor>
<marker>1998</marker>
<rawString>WordNet.&apos; an electronic lexical database. (1998), C. Fellbaum (ed.), MIT, 423 p.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>D Yarowksy</author>
</authors>
<title>Word-sense disambiguation using statistical models of Roget’s categories trained on large corpora.</title>
<date>1992</date>
<booktitle>Proceeding of Coling-92,</booktitle>
<pages>454--460</pages>
<location>Nante,</location>
<marker>Yarowksy, 1992</marker>
<rawString>Yarowksy, D. (1992) Word-sense disambiguation using statistical models of Roget’s categories trained on large corpora. Proceeding of Coling-92, Nante, France, pp. 454-460.</rawString>
</citation>
</citationList>
</algorithm>
</algorithms>