<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<algorithms version="110505">
<algorithm name="ParsCit" version="110505">
<citationList>
<citation valid="false">
<authors>
<author>P&amp;R</author>
</authors>
<title>Remerciements Nous tenons a remercier les rapporteurs pour leurs commentaires</title>
<publisher>Références</publisher>
<marker>P&amp;R, </marker>
<rawString> P&amp;R. Remerciements Nous tenons a remercier les rapporteurs pour leurs commentaires et M. Lamontagne, du CRDV. Références</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>J Aberdeen</author>
</authors>
<title>MITRE: Description of the Alembic System as Used for MUC6. Dans</title>
<date></date>
<marker>[ABD+95]</marker>
<rawString>J. Aberdeen et al. MITRE: Description of the Alembic System as Used for MUC6. Dans (MUC95).</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="false">
<authors>
<author>D Appelt</author>
</authors>
<booktitle>SRI International FASTUS system: MUC-6 test results and analysis. Dans (MUC95).</booktitle>
<marker>[AHB+95]</marker>
<rawString>D. Appelt et al. SRI International FASTUS system: MUC-6 test results and analysis. Dans (MUC95).</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>A Cucchiarelli</author>
<author>D Luzi et P Velardi</author>
</authors>
<title>Automatic semantic tagging of unknown proper names. Dans Actes ACL-COLING</title>
<date>1998</date>
<pages>286--292</pages>
<location>Montreal, Canada.</location>
<marker>[CLV98]</marker>
<rawString>A. Cucchiarelli, D. Luzi et P. Velardi. Automatic semantic tagging of unknown proper names. Dans Actes ACL-COLING 1998, pp 286-292, Montreal, Canada.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>D Appelt et D Martin</author>
</authors>
<title>Named Entity Recognition in Speech: Approach and results using the TextPro System. Dans</title>
<date>1999</date>
<booktitle>Proceedings of the DARPA Broadcast News Workshop.</booktitle>
<location>Herndon, Virginia,</location>
<marker>[AM99]</marker>
<rawString>D. Appelt et D. Martin. Named Entity Recognition in Speech: Approach and results using the TextPro System. Dans Proceedings of the DARPA Broadcast News Workshop. Herndon, Virginia, 1999.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>B Daille</author>
<author>B Habert</author>
<author>C Jacquemin et J</author>
</authors>
<title>Empirical observation of term Variations and principles for their description.</title>
<date>1996</date>
<journal>Terminology,</journal>
<volume>3</volume>
<issue>2</issue>
<marker>[DHJR96]</marker>
<rawString>B. Daille, B. Habert, C. Jacquemin et J . Royaute. Empirical observation of term Variations and principles for their description. Terminology, 3(2):l97—258, 1996.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>L Kosseim et G Lapalme</author>
</authors>
<title>Exibum: Un systeme experimental d’extraction d’information bilingue. Dans Actes de la Rencontre Internationale sur l’extraction, le Filtrage et le Resume Automatique (RIFRA-98),</title>
<date>1998</date>
<pages>129--140</pages>
<location>Sfax, Tunisie,</location>
<marker>[KL98]</marker>
<rawString>L. Kosseim et G. Lapalme. Exibum: Un systeme experimental d’extraction d’information bilingue. Dans Actes de la Rencontre Internationale sur l’extraction, le Filtrage et le Resume Automatique (RIFRA-98), pp 129-140, Sfax, Tunisie, 1998.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>F Kubala</author>
<author>R Schwartz</author>
<author>R Stone et R Weischedel</author>
</authors>
<title>Named Entity Extraction from Speech.</title>
<date>1998</date>
<booktitle>Dans Proceedings of the DARPA Broadcast News Workshop.</booktitle>
<location>Herndon, Virginia,</location>
<marker>[KSSW98]</marker>
<rawString>F. Kubala, R. Schwartz, R. Stone et R. Weischedel. Named Entity Extraction from Speech. Dans Proceedings of the DARPA Broadcast News Workshop. Herndon, Virginia, 1998.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>T Mitchell</author>
</authors>
<title>Machine Learning.</title>
<date>1997</date>
<publisher>McGraw-Hill,</publisher>
<location>New York,</location>
<marker>[Mit97]</marker>
<rawString>T. Mitchell. Machine Learning. McGraw-Hill, New York, 1997.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<date>1995</date>
<booktitle>Proceedings of the 6”‘ Message Understanding Conference,</booktitle>
<publisher>Morgan Kaufmarm.</publisher>
<marker>[MUC95]</marker>
<rawString>Proceedings of the 6”‘ Message Understanding Conference, 1995. Morgan Kaufmarm.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="false">
<booktitle>Proceedings of the 7”‘ Message Understanding Conference, http://www.itl.nist.goV/iad/894.02/related _proj ects/muc/proceedings/muc .7 _toc.html.</booktitle>
<marker>[MUC98]</marker>
<rawString>Proceedings of the 7”‘ Message Understanding Conference, http://www.itl.nist.goV/iad/894.02/related _proj ects/muc/proceedings/muc .7 _toc.html.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>M-P Pery-Wooodley</author>
</authors>
<title>Textual signalling in written texts: a corpus-based approach. Dans Actes ACL-COLING 1998, workshop Discourse relations and discourse markers,</title>
<date></date>
<location>Montreal,</location>
<marker>[Per98]</marker>
<rawString>M.-P. Pery-Wooodley. Textual signalling in written texts: a corpus-based approach. Dans Actes ACL-COLING 1998, workshop Discourse relations and discourse markers, Montreal, Canada. Extraction de noms propres it pattir de textes variés: problématique et enjeux</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>T Poibeau</author>
</authors>
<title>Le repérage des entités nommées: un enjeu pour les systémes de Veille. Dans Terminologies Nouvelles (Actes du colloque</title>
<date>1999</date>
<journal>Terminologie et Intelligence Artiﬁcielle, TIA ’99, Nantes),</journal>
<volume>19</volume>
<pages>43--51</pages>
<location>Nantes, France,</location>
<marker>[Poi99]</marker>
<rawString>T. Poibeau. Le repérage des entités nommées: un enjeu pour les systémes de Veille. Dans Terminologies Nouvelles (Actes du colloque Terminologie et Intelligence Artiﬁcielle, TIA ’99, Nantes), n. 19, pp 43-51, Nantes, France, 1999.</rawString>
</citation>
</citationList>
</algorithm>
</algorithms>