<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<algorithms version="110505">
<algorithm name="ParsCit" version="110505">
<citationList>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>mation extraction</author>
</authors>
<date></date>
<booktitle>Dans Proceeding of IJCAI-99,</booktitle>
<pages>890--895</pages>
<location>Stockholm,</location>
<marker>extraction, </marker>
<rawString> mation extraction. Dans Proceeding of IJCAI-99, pp. 890–895, Stockholm, Sweden.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>W Cohen</author>
</authors>
<title>Learning rules that classify e-mail.</title>
<date>1996</date>
<booktitle>Dans Proceeding of the 1996 AAAI Spring Symposium on Machine Learning in Information Access,</booktitle>
<marker>[Coh96]</marker>
<rawString>W. Cohen. Learning rules that classify e-mail. Dans Proceeding of the 1996 AAAI Spring Symposium on Machine Learning in Information Access, 1996.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>M Collot et N Belmore</author>
</authors>
<title>Electronic Language: A New Variety of English.</title>
<date>1998</date>
<journal>Dans S. Herring, editeur, Computer-Mediated Communications: Linguistic, Social and Cross-Cultural Perspertives,</journal>
<pages>13--28</pages>
<location>John Benjamins.</location>
<marker>[CB96]</marker>
<rawString>M. Collot et N. Belmore. (1998) Electronic Language: A New Variety of English. Dans S. Herring, editeur, Computer-Mediated Communications: Linguistic, Social and Cross-Cultural Perspertives, pp. 13–28, John Benjamins.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>L Capus et N Tourigny</author>
</authors>
<title>Générer de façon automatique des résumés grâce à des expériences similaires. Dans Actes de la Conférence internationale sur le traitement des langues naturelles et ses applications industrielles,</title>
<date>1998</date>
<pages>183--187</pages>
<location>Moncton, Canada.</location>
<marker>[CT98]</marker>
<rawString>L. Capus et N. Tourigny. (1998) Générer de façon automatique des résumés grâce à des expériences similaires. Dans Actes de la Conférence internationale sur le traitement des langues naturelles et ses applications industrielles, pp. 183–187, Moncton, Canada.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<title>http://www.islanddata.com/ site visité en décembre.</title>
<date>2000</date>
<marker>[Exp00]</marker>
<rawString>(2000) http://www.islanddata.com/ site visité en décembre.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>L Kosseim</author>
<author>S Beauregard et G Lapalme</author>
</authors>
<title>Using information extraction and natural language generation to answer e-mail.</title>
<date>2000</date>
<booktitle>Dans Proceedings of NLDB’2000,</booktitle>
<location>Versailles,</location>
<marker>[KBL00]</marker>
<rawString>L. Kosseim, S. Beauregard et G. Lapalme. (2000) Using information extraction and natural language generation to answer e-mail. Dans Proceedings of NLDB’2000, Versailles, France. Critères de sélection d’une approche pour le suivi automatique du courriel</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Y Lallement et M Fox</author>
</authors>
<title>Interact: A Staged Approach to Customer Service Automation. Dans H.</title>
<date>2000</date>
<journal>Hamilton et Q. Yang, editeurs, Canadian AI</journal>
<volume>1822</volume>
<pages>164--175</pages>
<publisher>Springler-Verlag.</publisher>
<marker>[LF00]</marker>
<rawString>Y. Lallement et M. Fox. (2000) Interact: A Staged Approach to Customer Service Automation. Dans H. Hamilton et Q. Yang, editeurs, Canadian AI 2000, LNAI 1822, pp. 164–175. Springler-Verlag.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<date>1998</date>
<booktitle>Proceedings of the Seventh Message Understanding Conference (MUC-7).</booktitle>
<note>http://www.itl.nist.gov/iad/894.02/related projects/muc/proceedings/muc 7 toc.html.</note>
<marker>[MUC98]</marker>
<rawString>(1998) Proceedings of the Seventh Message Understanding Conference (MUC-7). http://www.itl.nist.gov/iad/894.02/related projects/muc/proceedings/muc 7 toc.html.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<date>1999</date>
<booktitle>Proceedings of the Text Retrieval Conference (TREC-8),</booktitle>
<location>Gaithersburg, Maryland.</location>
<marker>[TRE99]</marker>
<rawString>(1999) Proceedings of the Text Retrieval Conference (TREC-8), Gaithersburg, Maryland.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<date>2000</date>
<booktitle>Proceedings of the Text Retrieval Conference (TREC-9),</booktitle>
<location>Gaithersburg, Maryland.</location>
<marker>[TRE00]</marker>
<rawString>(2000) Proceedings of the Text Retrieval Conference (TREC-9), Gaithersburg, Maryland.</rawString>
</citation>
</citationList>
</algorithm>
</algorithms>