<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<algorithms version="110505">
<algorithm name="ParsCit" version="110505">
<citationList>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>S Ait-Mokhtar</author>
</authors>
<title>Incremental Finite-State Parsing,</title>
<date></date>
<booktitle>in Proceedings of the 5th ACL Conference on Application of Natural Language Processing,</booktitle>
<pages>72--79</pages>
<location>Washington,</location>
<marker>Ait-Mokhtar, </marker>
<rawString>S.Ait-Mokhtar, J.-P.Chan0d — Incremental Finite-State Parsing, in Proceedings of the 5th ACL Conference on Application of Natural Language Processing, March 1997, Washington, pp. 72-79.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="false">
<authors>
<author>J Ambr0ziak</author>
</authors>
<title>W.W00ds — Natural Language Technology in Precision Content Retrieval,</title>
<date>1998</date>
<booktitle>in Proceedings of the International Conference on Natural Language Processing and Industrial Applications (NLP+IA 98),</booktitle>
<location>Moncton, New Brunswick, CANADA</location>
<marker>Ambr0ziak, 1998</marker>
<rawString>J.Ambr0ziak, W.W00ds — Natural Language Technology in Precision Content Retrieval, in Proceedings of the International Conference on Natural Language Processing and Industrial Applications (NLP+IA 98), August 18-21, 1998, Moncton, New Brunswick, CANADA A.Todirascu et F.Rousse1ot F.Baader, B.H0llunder — A terminological Knowledge Representation systems with Complete Inference Algorithms, Workshop on Processing Declarative Knowledge, PDK’91.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<title>B.Bachim0nt — Engagement se’mantique et engagement ontologique: conception et re’alisation d ’ontologies en inge’nierie des connaissances,</title>
<date>2000</date>
<booktitle>in J.Charlet, M.Zacklad, G.Kassel, D.B0urigault (eds.) — Inge’nierie des connaissances - Evolutions re’centes et nouveaux de’ﬁs, Eyrolles</booktitle>
<pages>305--324</pages>
<publisher>Publishing House,</publisher>
<marker>2000</marker>
<rawString>B.Bachim0nt — Engagement se’mantique et engagement ontologique: conception et re’alisation d ’ontologies en inge’nierie des connaissances, in J.Charlet, M.Zacklad, G.Kassel, D.B0urigault (eds.) — Inge’nierie des connaissances - Evolutions re’centes et nouveaux de’ﬁs, Eyrolles Publishing House, 2000, pp. 305-324.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>B Habert J B0uaud</author>
</authors>
<title>A.Nazarenk0, P.ZWeigenbaum — Regroupements issus de de’pendances syntaxiques sur un corpus de spe’cialite’.&apos; cate’gorisation et confrontation a deux conceptualisations du domaine,</title>
<date>2000</date>
<booktitle>in J.Charlet, M.Zacklad, G.Kassel, D.B0urigault (eds.) — Inge’nierie des connaissances - Evolutions récentes et nouveaux de’ﬁs, Eyrolles</booktitle>
<pages>275--290</pages>
<publisher>Publishing House,</publisher>
<marker>B0uaud, 2000</marker>
<rawString>J.B0uaud, B.Habert, A.Nazarenk0, P.ZWeigenbaum — Regroupements issus de de’pendances syntaxiques sur un corpus de spe’cialite’.&apos; cate’gorisation et confrontation a deux conceptualisations du domaine, in J.Charlet, M.Zacklad, G.Kassel, D.B0urigault (eds.) — Inge’nierie des connaissances - Evolutions récentes et nouveaux de’ﬁs, Eyrolles Publishing House, 2000, pp. 275-290.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="false">
<title>N .Capp0ni, Y.T0ussaint — Interpre’tation de classes de termes par ge’ne’ralisation de structures pre’dicat-argument,</title>
<date>1998</date>
<booktitle>P.B11itelaar — CORELEX: Systematic Polysemy and Underspeciﬁcation, Ph.D. thesis,</booktitle>
<pages>337--356</pages>
<editor>in J .Charlet, M.Zacklad, G.Kassel, D.B0urigault (eds.)</editor>
<publisher>Publishing House,</publisher>
<institution>Brandeis University, Department of Computer Science,</institution>
<marker>1998</marker>
<rawString>P.B11itelaar — CORELEX: Systematic Polysemy and Underspeciﬁcation, Ph.D. thesis, Brandeis University, Department of Computer Science, 1998 N .Capp0ni, Y.T0ussaint — Interpre’tation de classes de termes par ge’ne’ralisation de structures pre’dicat-argument, in J .Charlet, M.Zacklad, G.Kassel, D.B0urigault (eds.) — Ingénierie des connaissances - Evolutions re’centes et nouveaux de’ﬁs, Eyrolles Publishing House, 2000, pp. 337-356.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<title>TREC: A status report.</title>
<date>1993</date>
<booktitle>The First Text Retrieval Conference (TREC-I),</booktitle>
<pages>500--207</pages>
<editor>S.Dumais — LSI meets</editor>
<location>Gaithersburg, MD,</location>
<marker>1993</marker>
<rawString>S.Dumais — LSI meets TREC: A status report. In D.K.HarInan, ed. — The First Text Retrieval Conference (TREC-I), 500-207, pp. 137-207, Gaithersburg, MD, March 1993. NIST Special publication. C.Jacquemin — Improving Automatic Indexing through Concept Combination and Term Enrichmentin Proceedings of the I7th International Conference on Computational Linguistics (COLING’98), pages 595-599, Montréal.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<date>1998</date>
<booktitle>J.Lec0mte — Le Catégoriseur BRILLI4-JL5/WINBRILL-0.3, InaLF, InaLF/CNRS report,</booktitle>
<marker>1998</marker>
<rawString>J.Lec0mte — Le Catégoriseur BRILLI4-JL5/WINBRILL-0.3, InaLF, InaLF/CNRS report, December 1998.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="false">
<title>JaBot.&apos;a multilingual Java-based inteligent agent for Web sites, in COLING’98,</title>
<date>1998</date>
<booktitle>T.Strzalk0Wski, Natural Language Information Retrieval,</booktitle>
<volume>33</volume>
<issue>10</issue>
<pages>10--14</pages>
<editor>T.Read, E.Barcena</editor>
<publisher>Kluwer Academic Publishers,</publisher>
<location>Montreal, Canada,</location>
<marker>1998</marker>
<rawString>T.Read, E.Barcena — JaBot.&apos;a multilingual Java-based inteligent agent for Web sites, in COLING’98, Montreal, Canada, 10-14 August 1998 E. Riloff, J.L0renzen — Extraction-based Text Categorization Generating Domain-Speciﬁc Role Relationships Automatically, in ed. T.Strzalk0Wski, Natural Language Information Retrieval, Kluwer Academic Publishers, 1999 D.Rudl0ff, F. de Beuvron, M.Schlick — Extending Tableaux Calculus with Limited Regular Expression for Role Path .&apos; an Application to Natural Language Processing, DL’98, Trento, Italy, 1998 P.V0ssen — EuroWordNet - A Multilingual Database with Lexical Semantic Networks, Kluwer Academic Publishers, 1998 C. Welty, N. Ide — Using the right tools.‘ enhancing retrieval from marked-up documents, in J. Computers and the Humanities, Kluwer, 33(10):59—84. April, 1999.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>J Zh0u</author>
</authors>
<title>Phrasal Terms in Real- Word IR Applications,</title>
<date>1999</date>
<booktitle>in T.Strzalk0Wski — Natural Language Information Retrieval,</booktitle>
<publisher>Kluwer Academic Publishers,</publisher>
<marker>Zh0u, 1999</marker>
<rawString>J.Zh0u — Phrasal Terms in Real- Word IR Applications, in T.Strzalk0Wski — Natural Language Information Retrieval, Kluwer Academic Publishers, 1999</rawString>
</citation>
</citationList>
</algorithm>
</algorithms>