<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<algorithms version="110505">
<algorithm name="ParsCit" version="110505">
<citationList>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>S BANERJEE</author>
<author>A LAVIE</author>
</authors>
<title>METEOR: An Automatic Metric for MT Evaluation with Improved Correlation with Human Judgments.</title>
<date>2005</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of Workshop on Intrinsic and Extrinsic Evaluation Measures for MT and/or Summarization at the 43th Annual Meeting of the Association of Computational Linguistics (ACL-05),</booktitle>
<pages>65--72</pages>
<location>Ann Arbor, MI.</location>
<marker>BANERJEE, LAVIE, 2005</marker>
<rawString>BANERJEE S. &amp; LAVIE A. (2005). METEOR: An Automatic Metric for MT Evaluation with Improved Correlation with Human Judgments. In Proceedings of Workshop on Intrinsic and Extrinsic Evaluation Measures for MT and/or Summarization at the 43th Annual Meeting of the Association of Computational Linguistics (ACL-05), p. 65–72, Ann Arbor, MI.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>D M BIKEL</author>
</authors>
<title>Design of a Multi-lingual, Parallel-processing Statistical Parsing Engine.</title>
<date>2002</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the 2nd International Conference on Human Language Technology Research,</booktitle>
<pages>24--27</pages>
<location>San Francisco, CA.</location>
<marker>BIKEL, 2002</marker>
<rawString>BIKEL D. M. (2002). Design of a Multi-lingual, Parallel-processing Statistical Parsing Engine. In Proceedings of the 2nd International Conference on Human Language Technology Research, p. 24–27, San Francisco, CA.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>D BOURIGAULT</author>
<author>C FABRE</author>
<author>C FRÉROT</author>
<author>M-P JACQUES</author>
<author>S OZDOWSKA</author>
</authors>
<title>SYNTEX, analyseur syntaxique de corpus.</title>
<date>2005</date>
<booktitle>In Atelier EASy, Actes de la Conférence Traitement Automatique des Langues Naturelles,</booktitle>
<location>Dourdan, France.</location>
<marker>BOURIGAULT, FABRE, FRÉROT, JACQUES, OZDOWSKA, 2005</marker>
<rawString>BOURIGAULT D., FABRE C., FRÉROT C., JACQUES M.-P. &amp; OZDOWSKA S. (2005). SYNTEX, analyseur syntaxique de corpus. In Atelier EASy, Actes de la Conférence Traitement Automatique des Langues Naturelles, Dourdan, France.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Y-C CHIAO</author>
<author>O KRAIF</author>
<author>D LAURENT</author>
<author>T M H NGUYEN</author>
<author>N SEMMAR</author>
<author>F STUCK</author>
<author>J VÉRONIS</author>
<author>W ZAGHOUANI</author>
</authors>
<title>Evaluation of multilingual text alignment systems: the ARCADE II project.</title>
<date>2006</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the 5th Conference on Language Resources and Evaluation (LREC’06),</booktitle>
<pages>1975--1978</pages>
<location>Genoa, Italy.</location>
<marker>CHIAO, KRAIF, LAURENT, NGUYEN, SEMMAR, STUCK, VÉRONIS, ZAGHOUANI, 2006</marker>
<rawString>CHIAO Y.-C., KRAIF O., LAURENT D., NGUYEN T. M. H., SEMMAR N., STUCK F., VÉRONIS J. &amp; ZAGHOUANI W. (2006). Evaluation of multilingual text alignment systems: the ARCADE II project. In Proceedings of the 5th Conference on Language Resources and Evaluation (LREC’06), p. 1975–1978, Genoa, Italy.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>G DODDINGTON</author>
</authors>
<title>Automatic Evaluation of Machine Translation Quality Using Ngram Co-Occurrence Statistics.</title>
<date>2002</date>
<booktitle>In Human Language Technology: Notebook Proceedings,</booktitle>
<pages>128--132</pages>
<location>San Diego, CA.</location>
<marker>DODDINGTON, 2002</marker>
<rawString>DODDINGTON G. (2002). Automatic Evaluation of Machine Translation Quality Using Ngram Co-Occurrence Statistics. In Human Language Technology: Notebook Proceedings, p. 128–132, San Diego, CA.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Mary Hearne</author>
<author>Sylwia Ozdowska</author>
<author>John Tinsley GROVES D</author>
<author>A WAY</author>
</authors>
<title>Hybrid Example-Based SMT: the Best of Both Worlds?</title>
<date>2005</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of ACL 2005 Workshop on Building and Using Parallel Texts: Data-Driven Machine Translation and Beyond,</booktitle>
<pages>183--190</pages>
<location>Ann Arbor, MI.</location>
<marker>Hearne, Ozdowska, D, WAY, 2005</marker>
<rawString>Mary Hearne, Sylwia Ozdowska and John Tinsley GROVES D. &amp; WAY A. (2005). Hybrid Example-Based SMT: the Best of Both Worlds? In Proceedings of ACL 2005 Workshop on Building and Using Parallel Texts: Data-Driven Machine Translation and Beyond, p. 183–190, Ann Arbor, MI.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>P KOEHN</author>
<author>H HOANG</author>
<author>A BIRCH</author>
<author>C CALLISON-BURCH</author>
<author>M FEDERICO</author>
<author>N BERTOLDI</author>
<author>B COWAN</author>
<author>W SHEN</author>
<author>C MORAN</author>
<author>R ZENS</author>
<author>C DYER</author>
<author>O BOJAR</author>
<author>A CONSTANTIN</author>
<author>E HERBST</author>
</authors>
<title>Moses: Open source toolkit for statistical machine translation.</title>
<date>2007</date>
<booktitle>In Annual Meeting of the Association for Computational Linguistics (ACL), demonstration session,</booktitle>
<pages>177--180</pages>
<location>Prague, Czech Republic.</location>
<marker>KOEHN, HOANG, BIRCH, CALLISON-BURCH, FEDERICO, BERTOLDI, COWAN, SHEN, MORAN, ZENS, DYER, BOJAR, CONSTANTIN, HERBST, 2007</marker>
<rawString>KOEHN P., HOANG H., BIRCH A., CALLISON-BURCH C., FEDERICO M., BERTOLDI N., COWAN B., SHEN W., MORAN C., ZENS R., DYER C., BOJAR O., CONSTANTIN A. &amp; HERBST E. (2007). Moses: Open source toolkit for statistical machine translation. In Annual Meeting of the Association for Computational Linguistics (ACL), demonstration session, p. 177–180, Prague, Czech Republic.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>P KOEHN</author>
<author>F J OCH</author>
<author>D MARCU</author>
</authors>
<title>Statistical Phrase-Based Translation.</title>
<date>2003</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the 2003 Conference of the North American Chapter of the Association for Computational Linguistics on Human Language Technology (NAACL ’03),</booktitle>
<pages>48--54</pages>
<location>Edmonton, Canada.</location>
<marker>KOEHN, OCH, MARCU, 2003</marker>
<rawString>KOEHN P., OCH F. J. &amp; MARCU D. (2003). Statistical Phrase-Based Translation. In Proceedings of the 2003 Conference of the North American Chapter of the Association for Computational Linguistics on Human Language Technology (NAACL ’03), p. 48–54, Edmonton, Canada.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>M MARCUS</author>
<author>G KIM</author>
<author>M A MARCINKIEWICZ</author>
<author>R MACINTYRE</author>
<author>A BIES</author>
<author>M FERGUSON</author>
<author>K KATZ</author>
<author>B SCHASBERGER</author>
</authors>
<title>The Penn Treebank: Annotating Predicate Argument Structure.</title>
<date>1994</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the ARPA Workshop on Human Language Technology,</booktitle>
<pages>110--115</pages>
<location>Princeton, NJ.</location>
<marker>MARCUS, KIM, MARCINKIEWICZ, MACINTYRE, BIES, FERGUSON, KATZ, SCHASBERGER, 1994</marker>
<rawString>MARCUS M., KIM G., MARCINKIEWICZ M. A., MACINTYRE R., BIES A., FERGUSON M., KATZ K. &amp; SCHASBERGER B. (1994). The Penn Treebank: Annotating Predicate Argument Structure. In Proceedings of the ARPA Workshop on Human Language Technology, p. 110–115, Princeton, NJ.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>F J OCH</author>
<author>H NEY</author>
</authors>
<title>A Systematic Comparison of Various Statistical Alignment Models.</title>
<date>2003</date>
<journal>Computational Linguistics,</journal>
<volume>29</volume>
<issue>1</issue>
<marker>OCH, NEY, 2003</marker>
<rawString>OCH F. J. &amp; NEY H. (2003). A Systematic Comparison of Various Statistical Alignment Models. Computational Linguistics, 29(1), 19–51.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>S OZDOWSKA</author>
</authors>
<title>ALIBI, un système d’ALIgnement BIlingue à base de règles de propagation syntaxique.</title>
<date>2006</date>
<tech>Phd. Thesis,</tech>
<institution>University Toulouse-Le Mirail,</institution>
<marker>OZDOWSKA, 2006</marker>
<rawString>OZDOWSKA S. (2006). ALIBI, un système d’ALIgnement BIlingue à base de règles de propagation syntaxique. Phd. Thesis, University Toulouse-Le Mirail, France.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>K PAPINENI</author>
<author>S ROUKOS</author>
<author>T WARD</author>
<author>W-J ZHU</author>
</authors>
<title>BLEU: a Method for Automatic Evaluation of Machine Translation.</title>
<date>2002</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the 40th Annual Meeting of the Association for Computational Linguistics (ACL-02),</booktitle>
<pages>311--318</pages>
<location>Philadelphia, PA.</location>
<marker>PAPINENI, ROUKOS, WARD, ZHU, 2002</marker>
<rawString>PAPINENI K., ROUKOS S., WARD T. &amp; ZHU W.-J. (2002). BLEU: a Method for Automatic Evaluation of Machine Translation. In Proceedings of the 40th Annual Meeting of the Association for Computational Linguistics (ACL-02), p. 311–318, Philadelphia, PA.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>P PAROUBEK</author>
<author>A VILNAT</author>
<author>I ROBBA</author>
<author>C AYACHE</author>
</authors>
<title>Les résultats de la campagne EASy d’évaluation des analyseurs syntaxiques du français.</title>
<date>2007</date>
<booktitle>In Actes de la Conférence Traitement Automatique des Langues Naturelles,</booktitle>
<location>Toulouse, France.</location>
<marker>PAROUBEK, VILNAT, ROBBA, AYACHE, 2007</marker>
<rawString>PAROUBEK P., VILNAT A., ROBBA I. &amp; AYACHE C. (2007). Les résultats de la campagne EASy d’évaluation des analyseurs syntaxiques du français. In Actes de la Conférence Traitement Automatique des Langues Naturelles, Toulouse, France.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>N SCHLUTER</author>
<author>J VAN GENABITH</author>
</authors>
<title>Preparing, Restructuring and Augmenting a French Treebank: Lexicalised Parsing or Coherent Treebanks?</title>
<date>2007</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the 10th Conference of the Pacific Association of Computational Linguistics (PACLING</booktitle>
<location>Melbourne, Australia.</location>
<marker>SCHLUTER, VAN GENABITH, 2007</marker>
<rawString>SCHLUTER N. &amp; VAN GENABITH J. (2007). Preparing, Restructuring and Augmenting a French Treebank: Lexicalised Parsing or Coherent Treebanks? In Proceedings of the 10th Conference of the Pacific Association of Computational Linguistics (PACLING 2007), Melbourne, Australia.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>J TINSLEY</author>
<author>M HEARNE</author>
<author>A WAY</author>
</authors>
<title>Exploiting Parallel Treebanks to Improve Phrase-Based Statistical Machine Translation.</title>
<date>2007</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of The Sixth International Workshop on Treebanks and Linguistic Theories (TLT-07),</booktitle>
<location>Bergen, Norway.</location>
<marker>TINSLEY, HEARNE, WAY, 2007</marker>
<rawString>TINSLEY J., HEARNE M. &amp; WAY A. (2007a). Exploiting Parallel Treebanks to Improve Phrase-Based Statistical Machine Translation. In Proceedings of The Sixth International Workshop on Treebanks and Linguistic Theories (TLT-07), Bergen, Norway.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>J TINSLEY</author>
<author>V ZHECHEV</author>
<author>M HEARNE</author>
<author>A WAY</author>
</authors>
<title>Robust Language PairIndependent Sub-Tree Alignment.</title>
<date>2007</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of MT</booktitle>
<location>Summit XI, Copenhagen, Denmark.</location>
<marker>TINSLEY, ZHECHEV, HEARNE, WAY, 2007</marker>
<rawString>TINSLEY J., ZHECHEV V., HEARNE M. &amp; WAY A. (2007b). Robust Language PairIndependent Sub-Tree Alignment. In Proceedings of MT Summit XI, Copenhagen, Denmark.</rawString>
</citation>
</citationList>
</algorithm>
</algorithms>