<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<algorithms version="110505">
<algorithm name="ParsCit" version="110505">
<citationList>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>X GAO</author>
<author>L STERLING</author>
</authors>
<title>Semi-Structured Data Extraction from Heterogeneous Sources.</title>
<date>1999</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of 2cd International Workshop on Innovative Internet Information Systems (IIIS&apos;99) in conjunction with the European Conference on Information Systems (ECIS&apos;99),</booktitle>
<location>Copenhagen, Denmark.</location>
<marker>GAO, STERLING, 1999</marker>
<rawString>GAO X., STERLING L. (1999). Semi-Structured Data Extraction from Heterogeneous Sources. In Proceedings of 2cd International Workshop on Innovative Internet Information Systems (IIIS&apos;99) in conjunction with the European Conference on Information Systems (ECIS&apos;99), Copenhagen, Denmark.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>D W EMBLEY</author>
<author>D M CAMPBELL</author>
<author>R D SMITH</author>
<author>S W LIDDLE</author>
</authors>
<title>Ontology-Based Extraction and Structuring of Information from Data-Rich Unstructured Documents.</title>
<date>1998</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the International Conference on Knowledge Management.</booktitle>
<editor>In G. Gardarin, J.C. French, N. Pissinou, K. Makki and L. Bouganim, editors,</editor>
<publisher>ACM.</publisher>
<marker>EMBLEY, CAMPBELL, SMITH, LIDDLE, 1998</marker>
<rawString>EMBLEY D. W., CAMPBELL D. M., SMITH R. D. and LIDDLE S. W. (1998). Ontology-Based Extraction and Structuring of Information from Data-Rich Unstructured Documents. In G. Gardarin, J.C. French, N. Pissinou, K. Makki and L. Bouganim, editors, In Proceedings of the International Conference on Knowledge Management. ACM.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>R A PELEATO</author>
<author>J-C CHAPPELIER</author>
<author>M RAJMAN</author>
</authors>
<title>Automated Information Extraction out of Classified Advertisements.</title>
<date>2000</date>
<booktitle>In Natural Language Processing and Information Systems : 5th International Conference on Applications of Natural Language to Information Systems, NLDB</booktitle>
<location>Versailles, France.</location>
<marker>PELEATO, CHAPPELIER, RAJMAN, 2000</marker>
<rawString>PELEATO R. A., CHAPPELIER J.-C., and RAJMAN M. (2000). Automated Information Extraction out of Classified Advertisements. In Natural Language Processing and Information Systems : 5th International Conference on Applications of Natural Language to Information Systems, NLDB 2000, Versailles, France.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>H SEO</author>
<author>J YANG</author>
<author>J CHOI</author>
</authors>
<title>Knowledge-based Wrapper Generation by Using XML.</title>
<date>2001</date>
<marker>SEO, YANG, CHOI, 2001</marker>
<rawString>SEO H., YANG J., and CHOI J. (2001), Knowledge-based Wrapper Generation by Using XML.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="false">
<booktitle>In IJCAI-2001 Workshop on Adaptive Text Extraction and Mining,</booktitle>
<location>Seattle, Washington.</location>
<marker></marker>
<rawString>In IJCAI-2001 Workshop on Adaptive Text Extraction and Mining, Seattle, Washington.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>C D MANNING</author>
<author>H SCHÜTZE</author>
</authors>
<title>Foundations of statistical natural language processing.</title>
<date>1999</date>
<volume>620</volume>
<pages>p.,</pages>
<publisher>MIT Press,</publisher>
<location>Cambridge, MA.</location>
<marker>MANNING, SCHÜTZE, 1999</marker>
<rawString>MANNING C. D., SCHÜTZE H. (1999). Foundations of statistical natural language processing. MIT Press, 620 p., Cambridge, MA.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>A VITERBI</author>
</authors>
<title>Error bounds for convolutional codes and an asymptotically optimum decoding algorithm.</title>
<date>1967</date>
<journal>IEEE Transactions on Information Theory.</journal>
<marker>VITERBI, 1967</marker>
<rawString>VITERBI A. (1967). Error bounds for convolutional codes and an asymptotically optimum decoding algorithm. IEEE Transactions on Information Theory.</rawString>
</citation>
</citationList>
</algorithm>
</algorithms>