<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<algorithms version="110505">
<algorithm name="ParsCit" version="110505">
<citationList>
<citation valid="false">
<authors>
<author>A COLLINS</author>
<author>M R QUILLIAN</author>
</authors>
<title>Retrieval time from semantic memory, Journal of verbal learning and verbal behaviour,</title>
<date>1969</date>
<journal>RAFFINEMENTS D’UN TERME A PARTIR DE SON ARBRE DES USAGES NOMMES LIEBERMAN</journal>
<booktitle>International Conference on Intelligent User Interfaces (IUI’07), Hawaii, USA MEL’CUK I.A., CLAS A., POLGUERE A.</booktitle>
<volume>8</volume>
<issue>2</issue>
<pages>240--248</pages>
<location>Sydney,</location>
<marker>COLLINS, QUILLIAN, 1969</marker>
<rawString>COLLINS A., QUILLIAN M.R. (1969) Retrieval time from semantic memory, Journal of verbal learning and verbal behaviour, 8 (2), pp. 240-248 FAIRON C., HO N.D. (2004) Quantité d’information échangée : une nouvelle mesure de la similarité des mots, Journées internationales d’Analyses statistiques des Données Textuelles (JADT’04), Louvainla-Neuve (Belgique) LAFOURCADE M., JOUBERT A. (2009) Similitude entre les sens d’usage d’un terme dans un réseau lexical, Traitement Automatique des Langues, vol.50/1, pp. 177-200 LAFOURCADE M., JOUBERT A. (2010) Construction de l’arbre des usages nommés d’un terme dans un réseau lexical évolutif, Journées internationales d’Analyses statistiques des Données Textuelles (JADT’10), Rome (à paraître) RAFFINEMENTS D’UN TERME A PARTIR DE SON ARBRE DES USAGES NOMMES LIEBERMAN H., SMITH D.A., TEETERS A. (2007) Common Consensus: a web-based game for collecting commonsense goals, International Conference on Intelligent User Interfaces (IUI’07), Hawaii, USA MEL’CUK I.A., CLAS A., POLGUERE A. (1995) Introduction à la lexicologie explicative et combinatoire, Editions Duculot AUPELF-UREF PLOUX S., VICTORRI B. (1998) Construction d’espaces sémantiques à l’aide de dictionnaires de synonymes, Traitement Automatique des Langues, vol.39/1, pp. 161-182 POLGUERE A. (2006) Structural properties of Lexical Systems: Monolingual and Multilingual Perspectives, Proceedings of the Workshop on Multilingual Language Resources and Interoperability (COLING/ACL 2006), Sydney, pp. 50-59.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>A TVERSKY</author>
</authors>
<title>Features of similarity,</title>
<date>1977</date>
<journal>Psychological Review,</journal>
<booktitle>Corpus linguistics’ 2001 Conference,</booktitle>
<volume>84</volume>
<pages>327--352</pages>
<location>Lancaster, U.K.</location>
<marker>TVERSKY, 1977</marker>
<rawString>TVERSKY A. (1977) Features of similarity, Psychological Review, 84, pp. 327-352 VÉRONIS J. (2001) Sense tagging: does it make sense?, Corpus linguistics’ 2001 Conference, Lancaster, U.K.</rawString>
</citation>
</citationList>
</algorithm>
</algorithms>