<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<algorithms version="110505">
<algorithm name="ParsCit" version="110505">
<citationList>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>C BARRIÈRE</author>
<author>A AGBAGO</author>
</authors>
<title>TerminoWeb: a software environment for term study in rich contexts.</title>
<date>2006</date>
<booktitle>Proceedings of the International Conference on Terminology, Standardization and Technology Transfer,</booktitle>
<pages>103--113</pages>
<location>Beijing,</location>
<marker>BARRIÈRE, AGBAGO, 2006</marker>
<rawString>BARRIÈRE, C., AGBAGO, A. (2006). TerminoWeb: a software environment for term study in rich contexts. Proceedings of the International Conference on Terminology, Standardization and Technology Transfer, Beijing, 103-113.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>C BARRIÈRE</author>
</authors>
<title>The Web as a source of informative background knowledge, Proccedings of the Workshop “Beyond Translation Memories: New Tools for Translators”,</title>
<date>2009</date>
<location>MT Summit</location>
<marker>BARRIÈRE, 2009</marker>
<rawString>BARRIÈRE, C. (2009a). The Web as a source of informative background knowledge, Proccedings of the Workshop “Beyond Translation Memories: New Tools for Translators”, MT Summit 2009, Ottawa, Canada.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>C BARRIÈRE</author>
</authors>
<title>Finding domain specific collocations and concordances on the Web,</title>
<date>2009</date>
<booktitle>Proceedings of the Workshop “Natural Language Processing methods and corpora in translation, lexicography and language learning”, RANLP’2009, Borovets,</booktitle>
<marker>BARRIÈRE, 2009</marker>
<rawString>BARRIÈRE, C. (2009b). Finding domain specific collocations and concordances on the Web, Proceedings of the Workshop “Natural Language Processing methods and corpora in translation, lexicography and language learning”, RANLP’2009, Borovets, Bulgaria.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>I MEYER</author>
</authors>
<title>Extracting knowledge-rich contexts for terminography, in</title>
<date>2001</date>
<booktitle>L&apos;Homme M.C. (eds) Recent Advances in Computational Terminology, chapter 14,</booktitle>
<location>John Benjamins.</location>
<marker>MEYER, 2001</marker>
<rawString>MEYER, I. (2001). Extracting knowledge-rich contexts for terminography, in D. Bourigault, C. Jacquemin, L&apos;Homme M.C. (eds) Recent Advances in Computational Terminology, chapter 14, John Benjamins.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>F SMADJA</author>
</authors>
<title>Retrieving collocations from text:</title>
<date>1993</date>
<journal>Xtract. Computational Linguistics</journal>
<volume>7</volume>
<issue>4</issue>
<pages>143--177</pages>
<marker>SMADJA, 1993</marker>
<rawString>SMADJA F. (1993) Retrieving collocations from text: Xtract. Computational Linguistics 7(4): 143-177.</rawString>
</citation>
</citationList>
</algorithm>
</algorithms>