<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<algorithms version="110505">
<algorithm name="ParsCit" version="110505">
<citationList>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>C BOITET</author>
<author>Y BEY et K KAGEURA</author>
</authors>
<title>Main research issues in building web services for mutualized, non-commercial translation.</title>
<date>2005</date>
<booktitle>Proc. SNLP-05,</booktitle>
<volume>13</volume>
<pages>p.</pages>
<location>Bangkok, Chulalongkorn university,</location>
<marker>BOITET, KAGEURA, 2005</marker>
<rawString>BOITET, C., Y. BEY et K. KAGEURA (2005) Main research issues in building web services for mutualized, non-commercial translation. Proc. SNLP-05, Bangkok, Chulalongkorn university, 13 p.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>C BOITET</author>
<author>V BELLYNCK</author>
<author>M MANGEOT et C RAMISCH</author>
</authors>
<title>Towards Higher Quality Internal and Outside Multilingualization of Web Sites.</title>
<date>2008</date>
<booktitle>Proc. ONII-08 (Summer Workshop on Ontology, NLP, Personalization and IE/IR), Mumbai, Centre for Indian Language Technology (CFILT), IITB (Indian Institute of Technology Bombay),</booktitle>
<volume>9</volume>
<pages>p.</pages>
<marker>BOITET, BELLYNCK, RAMISCH, 2008</marker>
<rawString>BOITET, C., V. BELLYNCK, M. MANGEOT et C. RAMISCH (2008) Towards Higher Quality Internal and Outside Multilingualization of Web Sites. Proc. ONII-08 (Summer Workshop on Ontology, NLP, Personalization and IE/IR), Mumbai, Centre for Indian Language Technology (CFILT), IITB (Indian Institute of Technology Bombay), 9 p.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>C P Phap Boitet</author>
<author>H T Nguyen</author>
<author>V Bellynck HUYNH</author>
<author>C BOITET et H BLANCHON C-P</author>
</authors>
<title>Demo on iMAGs (interactive Multilingual Access Gateways)</title>
<date>2008</date>
<booktitle>Proc. LREC-08, Marrakech,</booktitle>
<volume>8</volume>
<pages>p.</pages>
<marker>Boitet, Nguyen, HUYNH, C-P, 2008</marker>
<rawString>Demo on iMAGs (interactive Multilingual Access Gateways) Ch. Boitet, C. P. Phap, H. T. Nguyen, V.!Bellynck HUYNH, C.-P., C. BOITET et H. BLANCHON (2008) SECTra_w : an Online Collaborative System for Evaluating, Post-editing and Presenting MT Translation Corpora. Proc. LREC-08, Marrakech, 8 p.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>H-T NGUYEN</author>
<author>C BOITET et G SÉRASSET</author>
</authors>
<title>PIVAX, an online contributive lexical database for heterogeneous MT systems using a lexical pivot.</title>
<date>2007</date>
<booktitle>Proc. SNLP-07,</booktitle>
<volume>6</volume>
<pages>p.</pages>
<institution>Pattaya, Kasetsart University,</institution>
<marker>NGUYEN, SÉRASSET, 2007</marker>
<rawString>NGUYEN, H.-T., C. BOITET et G. SÉRASSET (2007) PIVAX, an online contributive lexical database for heterogeneous MT systems using a lexical pivot. Proc. SNLP-07, Pattaya, Kasetsart University, 6 p. Appendix: screenshots of two other iMAGs / images d&apos;écran de deux autres iMAG</rawString>
</citation>
</citationList>
</algorithm>
</algorithms>