<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<algorithms version="110505">
<algorithm name="ParsCit" version="110505">
<citationList>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Simon CHAREST</author>
<author>Éric BRUNELLE</author>
<author>Jean FONTAINE Références BANERJEE S</author>
<author>T PEDERSEN</author>
</authors>
<title>druides sans qui Antidote HD n’aurait pu voir le</title>
<date>2003</date>
<booktitle>The Design, Implementation and Use of the Ngram Statistics Package. Proceedings of the Fourth International Conference on Intelligent Text Processing and Computational Linguistics,</booktitle>
<pages>370--381</pages>
<marker>CHAREST, BRUNELLE, S, PEDERSEN, 2003</marker>
<rawString>druides sans qui Antidote HD n’aurait pu voir le jour. Simon CHAREST, Éric BRUNELLE, Jean FONTAINE Références BANERJEE S., PEDERSEN T. (2003). The Design, Implementation and Use of the Ngram Statistics Package. Proceedings of the Fourth International Conference on Intelligent Text Processing and Computational Linguistics, 370–381.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>D BLAHETA</author>
<author>M JOHNSON</author>
</authors>
<title>Unsupervised learning of multi-word verbs.</title>
<date>2001</date>
<booktitle>Proceedings of the ACL Workshop on Collocations,</booktitle>
<pages>54--60</pages>
<marker>BLAHETA, JOHNSON, 2001</marker>
<rawString>BLAHETA D., JOHNSON M. (2001). Unsupervised learning of multi-word verbs. Proceedings of the ACL Workshop on Collocations, 54–60.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>S CHAREST</author>
<author>É BRUNELLE</author>
<author>J FONTAINE</author>
<author>B PELLETIER</author>
</authors>
<title>Élaboration automatique d’un dictionnaire de cooccurrences grand public. Actes de la 14e conférence sur le Traitement Automatique des Langues Naturelles (TALN</title>
<date>2007</date>
<pages>283--292</pages>
<marker>CHAREST, BRUNELLE, FONTAINE, PELLETIER, 2007</marker>
<rawString>CHAREST S., BRUNELLE É., FONTAINE J., PELLETIER, B. (2007). Élaboration automatique d’un dictionnaire de cooccurrences grand public. Actes de la 14e conférence sur le Traitement Automatique des Langues Naturelles (TALN 2007), 283–292.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>G DIAS</author>
<author>S GUILLORE</author>
<author>PEREIRA LOPES</author>
<author>J G</author>
</authors>
<title>Normalization of Association Measures for Multiword Lexical Unit Extraction.</title>
<date>2000</date>
<booktitle>International Conference on Artificial and Computational Intelligence for Decision Control and Automation in Engineering and Industrial Applications (ACIDCA</booktitle>
<pages>207--216</pages>
<marker>DIAS, GUILLORE, LOPES, G, 2000</marker>
<rawString>DIAS G., GUILLORE S., PEREIRA LOPES, J. G. (2000). Normalization of Association Measures for Multiword Lexical Unit Extraction. International Conference on Artificial and Computational Intelligence for Decision Control and Automation in Engineering and Industrial Applications (ACIDCA 2000), 207-216.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>T DUNNING</author>
</authors>
<title>Accurate methods for the statistics of surprise and coincidence.</title>
<date>1993</date>
<journal>Computational Linguistics</journal>
<volume>19</volume>
<pages>61--74</pages>
<marker>DUNNING, 1993</marker>
<rawString>DUNNING, T. (1993). Accurate methods for the statistics of surprise and coincidence. Computational Linguistics 19, 61-74.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>S EVERT</author>
</authors>
<title>The Statistics of Word Cooccurrences : Word Pairs and Collocations. Thèse de doctorat,</title>
<date>2005</date>
<institution>Université de Stuttgart.</institution>
<marker>EVERT, 2005</marker>
<rawString>EVERT S. (2005). The Statistics of Word Cooccurrences : Word Pairs and Collocations. Thèse de doctorat, Université de Stuttgart.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>S GRIES</author>
</authors>
<title>Dispersions and adjusted frequencies in corpora.</title>
<date>2008</date>
<journal>International Journal of Corpus Linguistics,</journal>
<volume>13</volume>
<pages>403--437</pages>
<marker>GRIES, 2008</marker>
<rawString>GRIES, S. (2008). Dispersions and adjusted frequencies in corpora. International Journal of Corpus Linguistics, vol. 13, no 4, 403–437.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>C MANNING</author>
<author>H SCHÜTZE</author>
</authors>
<title>Foundations of Statistical Natural Language Processing. Cambridge :</title>
<date>1999</date>
<publisher>The MIT Press.</publisher>
<marker>MANNING, SCHÜTZE, 1999</marker>
<rawString>MANNING C., SCHÜTZE H. (1999). Foundations of Statistical Natural Language Processing. Cambridge : The MIT Press.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>R C MOORE</author>
</authors>
<title>On log-likelihood-ratios and the significance of rare events.</title>
<date>2004</date>
<booktitle>Proceedings of the 2004 Conference on EMNLP,</booktitle>
<pages>333--340</pages>
<marker>MOORE, 2004</marker>
<rawString>MOORE R. C. (2004). On log-likelihood-ratios and the significance of rare events. Proceedings of the 2004 Conference on EMNLP, 333-340.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>P PECINA</author>
<author>P SCHLESINGER</author>
</authors>
<title>Combining association measures for collocation extraction.</title>
<date>2006</date>
<marker>PECINA, SCHLESINGER, 2006</marker>
<rawString>PECINA P., SCHLESINGER P. (2006). Combining association measures for collocation extraction.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<date>2006</date>
<booktitle>Proceedings of the 21th International Conference on Computational Linguistics and 44th Annual Meeting of the Association for Computational Linguistics (COLING/ACL</booktitle>
<pages>651--658</pages>
<contexts>
<context position="4096" citStr="(2006)" startWordPosition="584" endWordPosition="584">ons de collocations ou comme des collocations récursives, tandis que quelques cas sont de vraies collocations n-aires, où la séquence ne peut pas être décomposée. Dans la tâche d’extraction de collocations à partir de corpus, les mesures statistiques d’association employées pour quantifier le degré de cohésion – et donc de pertinence – des combinaisons candidates sont pour la plupart formulées pour évaluer les associations de deux éléments (ou bigrammes). De nombreuses études ont comparé les performances de diverses mesures d’association. Dans l’une des plus ambitieuses, Pecina et Schlesinger (2006) ont évalué 82 mesures dans une tâche d’extraction de collocations en tchèque, et ont combiné les plus performantes à l’aide de techniques d’apprentissage. Les choses se compliquent lorsque vient le temps de mesurer la force d’association de combinaisons de plus de deux mots. Deux grandes approches sont possibles : 1) employer des mesures statistiques plus 1 Logiciel d’aide à la rédaction grand pulic (www.antidote.info), sixième édition. 2 Par cooccurrence, nous entendons la présence simultanée et statistiquement significative, dans un corpus, de deux unités linguistiques ou plus en relation s</context>
</contexts>
<marker>2006</marker>
<rawString>Proceedings of the 21th International Conference on Computational Linguistics and 44th Annual Meeting of the Association for Computational Linguistics (COLING/ACL 2006), 651-658.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>V SERETAN</author>
</authors>
<title>Collocation extraction based on syntactic parsing. Thèse de doctorat, Université de Genève.</title>
<date>2008</date>
<marker>SERETAN, 2008</marker>
<rawString>SERETAN V. (2008). Collocation extraction based on syntactic parsing. Thèse de doctorat, Université de Genève.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>V SERETAN</author>
<author>L NERIMA</author>
<author>E WEHRLI</author>
</authors>
<title>Extraction of Multi-Word Collocations Using Syntactic Bigram Composition.</title>
<date>2003</date>
<booktitle>Proceedings of the Fourth International Conference on Recent Advances in NLP (RANLP-2003),</booktitle>
<pages>424--431</pages>
<marker>SERETAN, NERIMA, WEHRLI, 2003</marker>
<rawString>SERETAN V., NERIMA L., WEHRLI E. (2003). Extraction of Multi-Word Collocations Using Syntactic Bigram Composition. Proceedings of the Fourth International Conference on Recent Advances in NLP (RANLP-2003), 424–431.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>J SILVA</author>
<author>G DIAS</author>
<author>S GUILLORE</author>
<author>PEREIRA LOPES</author>
<author>J G</author>
</authors>
<title>Using LocalMaxs Algorithm for the Extraction of Contiguous and Non-contiguous Multiword Lexical Units.</title>
<date>1999</date>
<booktitle>Proceedings of 9th Portuguese Conference in Artificial Intelligence,</booktitle>
<pages>21--24</pages>
<marker>SILVA, DIAS, GUILLORE, LOPES, G, 1999</marker>
<rawString>SILVA J., DIAS G., GUILLORE S., PEREIRA LOPES, J. G. (1999). Using LocalMaxs Algorithm for the Extraction of Contiguous and Non-contiguous Multiword Lexical Units. Proceedings of 9th Portuguese Conference in Artificial Intelligence, 21-24.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>A TUTIN</author>
</authors>
<title>For an extended definition of lexical collocations.</title>
<date>2008</date>
<booktitle>Proceedings of the XIII Euralex International Congress</booktitle>
<pages>1453--1460</pages>
<location>Barcelona,</location>
<marker>TUTIN, 2008</marker>
<rawString>TUTIN A. (2008). For an extended definition of lexical collocations. Proceedings of the XIII Euralex International Congress (Barcelona, 15-19 July 2008), 1453-1460.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>VILLADA MOIRON B</author>
</authors>
<title>Data-driven Identification of fixed expressions and their modifiability. Thèse de doctorat, Université de Groningue.</title>
<date>2005</date>
<marker>B, 2005</marker>
<rawString>VILLADA MOIRON B. (2005). Data-driven Identification of fixed expressions and their modifiability. Thèse de doctorat, Université de Groningue.</rawString>
</citation>
</citationList>
</algorithm>
</algorithms>