<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<algorithms version="110505">
<algorithm name="ParsCit" version="110505">
<citationList>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>V PALLOTTA</author>
<author>R DELMONTE</author>
<author>A BISTROT</author>
</authors>
<title>Abstractive Summarization of Voice Communications. In Vetulani Z. (Ed.) Human Language Technology: challenges for the information society.</title>
<date>2011</date>
<booktitle>LNCS n.</booktitle>
<pages>6562</pages>
<publisher>Springer Verlag.</publisher>
<marker>PALLOTTA, DELMONTE, BISTROT, 2011</marker>
<rawString>PALLOTTA V., DELMONTE R., BISTROT A. Abstractive Summarization of Voice Communications. In Vetulani Z. (Ed.) Human Language Technology: challenges for the information society. LNCS n. 6562, Springer Verlag. April, 2011.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="false">
<authors>
<author>V PALLOTTA</author>
</authors>
<title>Content-based retrieval of distributed multimedia conversational data. In</title>
<booktitle>Information Retrieval and Mining in Distributed Environments, Springer Verlag series: Studies in Computational Intelligence, 2011, Volume 324/2011,</booktitle>
<pages>183--212</pages>
<editor>A. Soro, E. Vargiu, G. Armano, G. Paddeu (eds.)</editor>
<marker>PALLOTTA, </marker>
<rawString>PALLOTTA V. Content-based retrieval of distributed multimedia conversational data. In A. Soro, E. Vargiu, G. Armano, G. Paddeu (eds.) Information Retrieval and Mining in Distributed Environments, Springer Verlag series: Studies in Computational Intelligence, 2011, Volume 324/2011, pp. 183-212, 1st Edition, ISBN: 978-3-642-16088-2.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>R DELMONTE</author>
<author>A BRISTOT</author>
<author>G VOLTOLINA</author>
<author>V PALLOTTA</author>
</authors>
<title>Scaling up a NLU system from text to dialogue understanding.</title>
<date>2009</date>
<booktitle>Proceedings of the NAACL HLT Workshop on Software Engineering, Testing, and Quality Assurance for Natural Language Processing,</booktitle>
<pages>40--41</pages>
<location>Boulder, Colorado,</location>
<marker>DELMONTE, BRISTOT, VOLTOLINA, PALLOTTA, 2009</marker>
<rawString>DELMONTE R., BRISTOT A., VOLTOLINA G., PALLOTTA V. Scaling up a NLU system from text to dialogue understanding. Proceedings of the NAACL HLT Workshop on Software Engineering, Testing, and Quality Assurance for Natural Language Processing, pages 40–41, Boulder, Colorado, June 2009. Association for Computational Linguistics.</rawString>
</citation>
</citationList>
</algorithm>
</algorithms>