<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<algorithms version="110505">
<algorithm name="ParsCit" version="110505">
<citationList>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>A BADDELEY</author>
</authors>
<title>Working memory.</title>
<date>1992</date>
<journal>Science,</journal>
<booktitle>In Proceedings Interdisciplinary Workshop on Theoretical Issues in Natural Language Processing.</booktitle>
<volume>255</volume>
<pages>70--73</pages>
<location>Cambridge, Massachusets</location>
<marker>BADDELEY, 1992</marker>
<rawString>BADDELEY, A. (1992). Working memory. Science, 255, 556–559 BECKER, J. (1975). The Phrasal Lexicon. In Proceedings Interdisciplinary Workshop on Theoretical Issues in Natural Language Processing. Cambridge, Massachusets June 70-73.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="false">
<authors>
<author>J BERKO</author>
</authors>
<title>The Child&apos;s Learning of English Morphology.</title>
<date>1958</date>
<journal>Word,</journal>
<volume>14</volume>
<pages>8--30</pages>
<publisher>Academic Press.</publisher>
<location>Paris, Didier BOCK, J.K.</location>
<marker>BERKO, 1958</marker>
<rawString>BERKO, J. (1958). The Child&apos;s Learning of English Morphology. Word, 14, 150 177 BESSE, H. (1975) De la pratique aux théories des exercices structuraux. Etudes de Linguistique Appliquée, 20, 8-30. Paris, Didier BOCK, J.K. (1995). Sentence production: From mind to mouth. In J. L. Miller &amp; P.D. Eimas (Ed.), Handbook of perception and cognition. Vol. 11: Speech, language and communication. Orlando, FL: Academic Press.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>C BOITET</author>
<author>P BHATTACHARYYA</author>
<author>E BLANC</author>
<author>BOUDDH MEENA</author>
<author>S FAFIOTTE</author>
<author>G</author>
<author>A FALAISE</author>
<author>V VACCHANI</author>
</authors>
<title>Building Hindi-French-English-UNL resources for SurviTra-CIFLI, a linguistic survival system under construction, actes de SNLP,</title>
<date>2007</date>
<publisher>Prentice-Hall.</publisher>
<location>Pattaya, Thaïlande</location>
<marker>BOITET, BHATTACHARYYA, BLANC, MEENA, FAFIOTTE, G, FALAISE, VACCHANI, 2007</marker>
<rawString>BOITET, C., BHATTACHARYYA, P., BLANC, E., MEENA, BOUDDH, S., FAFIOTTE, G. &amp; FALAISE, A. &amp; V. VACCHANI (2007). Building Hindi-French-English-UNL resources for SurviTra-CIFLI, a linguistic survival system under construction, actes de SNLP, Pattaya, Thaïlande BROWN, H. 1987 Principles of Language Learning and Language Teaching. Englewood Cliffs, NJ: Prentice-Hall.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>C CHAPELLE</author>
</authors>
<title>Computer applications in second langage acquisition: Foundations for teaching, testing and research.</title>
<date>2001</date>
<publisher>CUP.</publisher>
<marker>CHAPELLE, 2001</marker>
<rawString>CHAPELLE, C. (2001). Computer applications in second langage acquisition: Foundations for teaching, testing and research. CUP.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>D CRYSTAL</author>
</authors>
<title>Language and the Internet.</title>
<date>2001</date>
<publisher>CUP.</publisher>
<marker>CRYSTAL, 2001</marker>
<rawString>CRYSTAL, D. (2001). Language and the Internet. CUP.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="false">
<authors>
<author>K de BOT</author>
</authors>
<title>A bilingual production model: Levelt !s ‘speaking’ model adapted. In</title>
<date>2000</date>
<journal>Reprinted from Applied Linguistics,</journal>
<booktitle>In M. Fayol (Ed.), Production du langage. Traité des Sciences Cognitives</booktitle>
<volume>13</volume>
<pages>420--442</pages>
<location>London; New York: Routledge.</location>
<marker>de BOT, 2000</marker>
<rawString>de BOT, K. (2000). A bilingual production model: Levelt !s ‘speaking’ model adapted. In L. Wei (Ed.), The bilingualism reader (pp. 420-442). London; New York: Routledge. (Reprinted from Applied Linguistics, 13, 1992, 1-24.) FAFIOTTE, G. FALAISE, A. &amp; J. GOULIAN. (2009). CIFLI-SurviTra, deux facettes : démonstrateur de composants de TA fondée sur UNL, et phrasebook multilingue, actes de TALN, Senlis FERRAND, L. (2002). Les modèles de la production de la parole. In M. Fayol (Ed.), Production du langage. Traité des Sciences Cognitives (pp. 27-44). Paris: Hermès.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>MICHAEL ZOCK</author>
<author>GUY LAPALME FROMKIN</author>
<author>V</author>
</authors>
<title>Speech Production. In Psycholinguistics.</title>
<date>1993</date>
<journal>J. Berko Gleason &amp; N. Bernstein Ratner,</journal>
<publisher>Harcourt,</publisher>
<location>Eds. Fort Worth, TX:</location>
<marker>ZOCK, FROMKIN, V, 1993</marker>
<rawString>MICHAEL ZOCK, GUY LAPALME FROMKIN, V. (1993). Speech Production. In Psycholinguistics. J. Berko Gleason &amp; N. Bernstein Ratner, Eds. Fort Worth, TX: Harcourt, Brace, Jovanovich.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>M F</author>
</authors>
<title>Levels of processing in sentence production. In</title>
<date>1980</date>
<pages>177--220</pages>
<publisher>Academic Press</publisher>
<location>London:</location>
<marker>F, 1980</marker>
<rawString>GARRETT. M. F. (1980). Levels of processing in sentence production. In B. Butterworth (Ed.), Language production (pp. 177-220). London: Academic Press GETHIN, A. &amp; E. GUNNEMARK. 1995. The Art and Science of Learning Languages. Intellect books, Headington, Oxford.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="false">
<authors>
<author>M HOLLAND</author>
<author>J KAPLAN</author>
<author>M</author>
</authors>
<title>SAMS (Eds.).1995.Intelligent Language Tutors.</title>
<location>Hillsdale, NJ.: LawrenceErlbaum Associates.</location>
<marker>HOLLAND, KAPLAN, M, </marker>
<rawString>HOLLAND, M., J. KAPLAN &amp; M. SAMS (Eds.).1995.Intelligent Language Tutors. Hillsdale, NJ.: LawrenceErlbaum Associates.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>S KRASHEN</author>
</authors>
<title>http://www.sdkrashen.com/SL_Acquisition_and_Learning/index.html, Second Language Acquisition and Second Language Learning.</title>
<date>1981</date>
<marker>KRASHEN, 1981</marker>
<rawString>KRASHEN, S. (1981). http://www.sdkrashen.com/SL_Acquisition_and_Learning/index.html, Second Language Acquisition and Second Language Learning.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>M L LE ROUZO</author>
</authors>
<title>Y a-t-il une justification psychologique à la pratique des exercices structuraux ? Etudes de Linguistique Appliquée,</title>
<date>1975</date>
<booktitle>Studies in Second Language Acquisition,</booktitle>
<volume>20</volume>
<pages>37--51</pages>
<location>Paris, Didier LEVELT, W.</location>
<marker>LE ROUZO, 1975</marker>
<rawString>LE ROUZO, M. L. (1975). Y a-t-il une justification psychologique à la pratique des exercices structuraux ? Etudes de Linguistique Appliquée, 20, 37-51. Paris, Didier LEVELT, W. (1970). Skill theory and language teaching. Studies in Second Language Acquisition, 1(1), 53– 70.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>W LEVELT</author>
</authors>
<date>1989</date>
<publisher>Speaking. MIT Press,</publisher>
<location>Cambridge, Mass.</location>
<marker>LEVELT, 1989</marker>
<rawString>LEVELT, W. (1989). Speaking. MIT Press, Cambridge, Mass.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<title>Lexique anglais/français des sports olympiques: jeux d&apos;été, Insep Publications,</title>
<date>2000</date>
<location>Paris</location>
<contexts>
<context position="7681" citStr="(2000)" startWordPosition="1168" endWordPosition="1168">un pont entre les deux, pour que l&apos;ensemble des phrases puisse être utilisé par l&apos;apprenant pour s&apos;exercer soit en mode traduction, soit en mode production de phrase. Nous présentons ici un générateur d’exercices dont la vocation est d’aider des adolescents ou des adultes à apprendre à s’exprimer à un débit ‘normal’ en langue étrangère. Le niveau visé étant celui de la survie, nous envisageons un vocabulaire et 1 Si jamais le chiffre avancé vous paraît élevé, il est bon de savoir que le “Lexique anglais/français des sports olympiques”, destiné aux journalistes ayant couvert les jeux de Sidney (2000), contenait déjà pratiquement 14 000 mots, avec 1000 entrées rien que pour les sports aquatiques (rubrique natation). 2 Un ‘phrasebook’ est une collection de phrases traduites et organisées par thèmes. Ce type de recueil existe depuis fort longtemps en version papier, et plus récemment sous forme électronique (Fafiotte et al. 2009, Boitet et al. 2007). Ceux intéressés par une version commerciale consulteront http://speak.econtrader.com/ RENDRE LES PHRASEBOOKS GENERIQUES des structures en nombre et complexité limités. Avant de décrire notre proposition, voyons deux modèles très influents, carac</context>
<context position="12031" citStr="(2000)" startWordPosition="1797" endWordPosition="1797">lle de la phrase. A l’étape suivante (encodage phonologique) on détermine la représentation positionnelle, c’est-à- dire, on récupère la forme phonologique, les caractéristiques segmentales et prosodiques des lemmes (qui, du coup deviennent des lexèmes) et on spécifie l’ordre des mots en les intégrant dans la structure spécifiée à l’étape précédente. L’articulateur doit transformer les symboles du module précédent en sons, afin d’évoquer chez l’auditeur des idées correspondantes à celles ayant donné naissance aux paroles du locuteur. 2.2 Le modèle de Reiter et Dale Le modèle de Reiter et Dale (2000) se décompose également en trois étapes : planification globale, planification locale et formulation. Bien qu’existant dans certains systèmes, la synthèse de la parole, dernier élément de la chaîne, est rarement implémentée. 3 Pour voir une comparaison des différentes approches on consultera Fromkin (1993), pour des propositions pour un modèle de production bilingue, voir (de Bot, 2000 ; Marini et Fabbro, 2007). 4 Ce qui implique tout ce qu’on sait des imperfections liées à la performance : surcharge de la mémoire de travail, incapacités d’accéder à une information (latences, ‘mot sur le bout </context>
</contexts>
<marker>2000</marker>
<rawString>Lexique anglais/français des sports olympiques: jeux d&apos;été, Insep Publications, Paris (2000).</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>W C MANN</author>
<author>S A THOMPSON</author>
</authors>
<title>Rhetorical Structure Theory: Toward a Functional Theory of Text Organization&apos;,</title>
<date>1988</date>
<journal>Text</journal>
<volume>8</volume>
<issue>3</issue>
<pages>243--281</pages>
<marker>MANN, THOMPSON, 1988</marker>
<rawString>MANN, W. C. &amp; THOMPSON, S. A. (1988). Rhetorical Structure Theory: Toward a Functional Theory of Text Organization&apos;, Text 8(3), 243--281.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="false">
<authors>
<author>A MARINI</author>
<author>F FABBRO</author>
</authors>
<title>Psycholinguistic models of speech production in Bilingualism and Multilingualism”.</title>
<date>2007</date>
<journal>Artificial Intelligence,</journal>
<booktitle>Artificial and Human Intelligence</booktitle>
<volume>27</volume>
<pages>47--67</pages>
<editor>In Ardila, A. and Ramos, E. (eds.)</editor>
<publisher>Nova Science Publishers Inc.</publisher>
<location>New York, NY,</location>
<marker>MARINI, FABBRO, 2007</marker>
<rawString>MARINI, A. and FABBRO, F. (2007) “Psycholinguistic models of speech production in Bilingualism and Multilingualism”. In Ardila, A. and Ramos, E. (eds.) “Speech and language disorders in Bilinguals”. Nova Science Publishers Inc. New York, NY, pp. 47-67s MCKEOWN, K. (1985).Discourse Strategies for Generating Natural-Language Text. Artificial Intelligence, 27, 1-41 NAGAO, M. (1984). A framework of a mechanical translation between japanese and english by analogy principle. In A. Elithorn &amp; R. Banerji (Eds.), Artificial and Human Intelligence (pp. 173–180). Amsterdam: Elsevier.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>J et S DECARRICO NATTINGER</author>
<author>J</author>
</authors>
<title>Lexical Phrases and Language Teaching ,</title>
<date>1992</date>
<publisher>University Press</publisher>
<location>Oxford, Oxford</location>
<marker>NATTINGER, J, 1992</marker>
<rawString>NATTINGER, J. et S. DECARRICO, J. (1992) Lexical Phrases and Language Teaching , Oxford, Oxford University Press NOVAK, J. &amp; D. GOWIN. 1984. Learning how to Learn.Cambridge. Cambridge University Press.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>R POWER</author>
<author>D SCOTT</author>
<author>R EVANS</author>
</authors>
<title>What you see is what you meant: direct knowledge editings with natural language feedback.</title>
<date>1998</date>
<booktitle>In H. Prade (Ed.), 13th European conference on artificial intelligence (ECAI’98)</booktitle>
<pages>677--681</pages>
<publisher>Chichester: Wiley.</publisher>
<marker>POWER, SCOTT, EVANS, 1998</marker>
<rawString>POWER, R., SCOTT, D., &amp; EVANS, R. (1998). What you see is what you meant: direct knowledge editings with natural language feedback. In H. Prade (Ed.), 13th European conference on artificial intelligence (ECAI’98) (pp. 677–681). Chichester: Wiley.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>E REITER</author>
<author>R DALE</author>
</authors>
<title>Building natural language generation systems. Cambridge:</title>
<date>2000</date>
<publisher>Cambridge University Press.</publisher>
<marker>REITER, DALE, 2000</marker>
<rawString>REITER, E., &amp; DALE, R. (2000). Building natural language generation systems. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>M et M YAZDANI SWARTZ</author>
</authors>
<title>Intelligent Tutoring Systems for Foreign Language Learning: The Bridge to International Communication.</title>
<date>1991</date>
<publisher>Springer Verlag,</publisher>
<location>Berlin.</location>
<marker>SWARTZ, 1991</marker>
<rawString>SWARTZ, M. et M. YAZDANI (Eds.). (1991). Intelligent Tutoring Systems for Foreign Language Learning: The Bridge to International Communication. Springer Verlag, Berlin.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>M WARSCHAUER</author>
<author>D HEALEY</author>
</authors>
<title>Computers and Language Learning: An overview.</title>
<date>1998</date>
<journal>Language Teaching,</journal>
<volume>31</volume>
<pages>57--71</pages>
<location>London: Edward Arnold.</location>
<note>http://www.lll.hawaii.edu/web/faculty/markw/overview.htm WILKINS D.</note>
<marker>WARSCHAUER, HEALEY, 1998</marker>
<rawString>WARSCHAUER, M. &amp; HEALEY, D. (1998). Computers and Language Learning: An overview. Language Teaching, 31. 57–71. http://www.lll.hawaii.edu/web/faculty/markw/overview.htm WILKINS D. (1972): Linguistics and Language Teaching. London: Edward Arnold.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>M ZOCK</author>
</authors>
<title>Swim or sink: the problem of communicating thought. In</title>
<date>1991</date>
<pages>235--247</pages>
<publisher>Springer.</publisher>
<location>New York:</location>
<marker>ZOCK, 1991</marker>
<rawString>ZOCK, M. (1991). Swim or sink: the problem of communicating thought. In M. Swartz &amp; M. Yazdani (Eds.), Intelligent tutoring systems for foreign language learning (pp. 235–247). New York: Springer.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>M ZOCK</author>
</authors>
<title>The Power of Words in Message Planning,</title>
<date>1996</date>
<booktitle>16th International Conference on Computational Linguistics, Copenhagen,</booktitle>
<pages>990--995</pages>
<marker>ZOCK, 1996</marker>
<rawString>ZOCK, M. (1996). The Power of Words in Message Planning, 16th International Conference on Computational Linguistics, Copenhagen, pp. 990-995 ZOCK, M., SABATIER, P. and L. JAKUBIEC. Message Composition Based on Concepts and Goals.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<date>2008</date>
<journal>International Journal of Speech Technology,</journal>
<pages>11--3</pages>
<marker>2008</marker>
<rawString>International Journal of Speech Technology, 11(3-4):181–193, 2008.</rawString>
</citation>
</citationList>
</algorithm>
</algorithms>