<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<algorithms version="110505">
<algorithm name="ParsCit" version="110505">
<citationList>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>S BIRD</author>
<author>E KLEIN</author>
<author>E LOPER</author>
</authors>
<date>2009</date>
<booktitle>Natural Language Processing with Python. O‟Reily.</booktitle>
<marker>BIRD, KLEIN, LOPER, 2009</marker>
<rawString>BIRD S., KLEIN E., LOPER E. (2009). Natural Language Processing with Python. O‟Reily.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>P CIMIANO</author>
<author>P HAASE</author>
<author>J HEIZMANN</author>
<author>M MANTEL</author>
</authors>
<title>ORAKEL: A portable natural language interface to knowledge Bases.</title>
<date>2007</date>
<tech>Technical report,</tech>
<institution>Institute AIFB, University of Karlsruhe,</institution>
<marker>CIMIANO, HAASE, HEIZMANN, MANTEL, 2007</marker>
<rawString>CIMIANO P., HAASE P., HEIZMANN J., MANTEL M. (2007). ORAKEL: A portable natural language interface to knowledge Bases. Technical report, Institute AIFB, University of Karlsruhe, Germany.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>A DUKE</author>
<author>T GLOVER</author>
<author>J DAVIES</author>
</authors>
<title>Squirrel: An advanced semantic search and browse facility. In:</title>
<date>2007</date>
<booktitle>th Proc. of the 4 European Semantic Web Conference.</booktitle>
<location>Innsbruck, Austria.</location>
<marker>DUKE, GLOVER, DAVIES, 2007</marker>
<rawString>DUKE A., GLOVER T., DAVIES J. (2007). Squirrel: An advanced semantic search and browse facility. In: th Proc. of the 4 European Semantic Web Conference. Innsbruck, Austria.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>V FOMITCHOV</author>
</authors>
<title>Formal systems for natural language man-machine interaction modeling.</title>
<date>1984</date>
<booktitle>Artificial Intelligence. Proc. of the IFAC Symposium,</booktitle>
<pages>4--6</pages>
<editor>In: Ponomaryov, V.M. (ed.)</editor>
<publisher>Pergamon Press,</publisher>
<location>Leningrad, USSR,</location>
<marker>FOMITCHOV, 1984</marker>
<rawString>FOMITCHOV V. (1984). Formal systems for natural language man-machine interaction modeling. In: Ponomaryov, V.M. (ed.) Artificial Intelligence. Proc. of the IFAC Symposium, Leningrad, USSR, 4-6 October 1983 (IFAC Proc. Series, 1984, No. 9). Oxford, UK; New York: Pergamon Press, 203-209.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>V A FOMICHOV</author>
</authors>
<title>Mathematical models of natural-language-processing systems as cybernetic models of a new kind.</title>
<date>1992</date>
<journal>Cybernetica (Belgium),</journal>
<volume>Vol. XXXV,</volume>
<pages>63--91</pages>
<marker>FOMICHOV, 1992</marker>
<rawString>FOMICHOV V.A. (1992). Mathematical models of natural-language-processing systems as cybernetic models of a new kind. Cybernetica (Belgium), Vol. XXXV, 63-91.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>V A FOMICHOV</author>
</authors>
<title>Towards a mathematical theory of natural-language communication.</title>
<date>1993</date>
<journal>Informatica. An Intern. J. of Computing and Informatics (Slovenia),</journal>
<volume>17</volume>
<pages>21--34</pages>
<marker>FOMICHOV, 1993</marker>
<rawString>FOMICHOV V.A. (1993a). Towards a mathematical theory of natural-language communication. Informatica. An Intern. J. of Computing and Informatics (Slovenia), Vol.17, 21-34.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>V A FOMICHOV</author>
</authors>
<title>K-calculuses and K-languages as powerful formal means to design intelligent systems processing medical texts.</title>
<date>1993</date>
<journal>Cybernetica (Belgium),</journal>
<volume>Vol. XXXVI,</volume>
<pages>161--182</pages>
<marker>FOMICHOV, 1993</marker>
<rawString>FOMICHOV V.A. (1993b). K-calculuses and K-languages as powerful formal means to design intelligent systems processing medical texts. Cybernetica (Belgium), Vol. XXXVI, 161-182.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>V A FOMICHOV</author>
</authors>
<title>Integral Formal Semantics and the design of legal full-text databases.</title>
<date>1994</date>
<journal>Cybernetica (Belgium),</journal>
<volume>Vol. XXXVII,</volume>
<pages>145--177</pages>
<marker>FOMICHOV, 1994</marker>
<rawString>FOMICHOV V.A. (1994). Integral Formal Semantics and the design of legal full-text databases. Cybernetica (Belgium), Vol. XXXVII, 145-177.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>V A FOMICHOV</author>
</authors>
<title>The Formalization of Designing Natural Language Processing Systems.</title>
<date>2005</date>
<publisher>MAX Press</publisher>
<location>Moscow:</location>
<note>(in Russian).</note>
<marker>FOMICHOV, 2005</marker>
<rawString>FOMICHOV V.A. (2005). The Formalization of Designing Natural Language Processing Systems. Moscow: MAX Press (in Russian).</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>V A FOMICHOV</author>
</authors>
<title>Mathematical Foundations of Representing the Content of Messages Sent by Computer Intelligent Agents.</title>
<date>2007</date>
<institution>State University – Higher School of Economics, Publishing</institution>
<location>Moscow:</location>
<note>(in Russian).</note>
<marker>FOMICHOV, 2007</marker>
<rawString>FOMICHOV V.A. (2007). Mathematical Foundations of Representing the Content of Messages Sent by Computer Intelligent Agents. Moscow: State University – Higher School of Economics, Publishing House &amp;quot;TEIS&amp;quot; (in Russian).</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>V A FOMICHOV</author>
</authors>
<title>(2009a) Theory of K-representations as a Source of an Advanced Language Platform for Semantic Web of a New Generation. Web Science Overlay J.</title>
<date>2009</date>
<booktitle>On-line Proceedings of the First International Conference on Web Science,</booktitle>
<location>Athens, Greece,</location>
<marker>FOMICHOV, 2009</marker>
<rawString>FOMICHOV V.A. (2009a) Theory of K-representations as a Source of an Advanced Language Platform for Semantic Web of a New Generation. Web Science Overlay J. On-line Proceedings of the First International Conference on Web Science, Athens, Greece, March 18-20, 2009; available at http://journal.webscience.org/221/1/websci09_submission_128.pdf.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="false">
<authors>
<author>V A FOMICHOV</author>
</authors>
<title>A Scheme and Formal Tools for Transforming the Existing Web into Semantic Web of a New Generation. In:</title>
<date>2009</date>
<booktitle>Pre-Conference Proceedings of the Focus Symposium on Knowledge Management Systems</booktitle>
<volume>3</volume>
<pages>39--50</pages>
<institution>Baden-Baden, Germany), Collaborative Agent Design Research Center, California Polytechnic State University,</institution>
<location>San Luis Obispo, CA, USA,</location>
<marker>FOMICHOV, 2009</marker>
<rawString>FOMICHOV V.A. (2009b). A Scheme and Formal Tools for Transforming the Existing Web into Semantic Web of a New Generation. In: Pre-Conference Proceedings of the Focus Symposium on Knowledge Management Systems (August 4, 2009, Focus Symposia Chair: Jens Pohl) in conjunction with InterSymp-2009, 21st International Conference on Systems Research, Informatics and Cybernetics, August 3 – 7, 2009, Baden-Baden, Germany), Collaborative Agent Design Research Center, California Polytechnic State University, San Luis Obispo, CA, USA, 39-50.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="false">
<authors>
<author>A Vladimir</author>
</authors>
<title>Fomichov FOMICHOV V.A. (2010a). Semantics-Oriented Natural Language Processing: Mathematical Models and Algorithms.</title>
<publisher>Springer.</publisher>
<location>New York, Dordrecht, Heidelberg, London :</location>
<marker>Vladimir, </marker>
<rawString>Vladimir A. Fomichov FOMICHOV V.A. (2010a). Semantics-Oriented Natural Language Processing: Mathematical Models and Algorithms. New York, Dordrecht, Heidelberg, London : Springer.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="false">
<authors>
<author>V A FOMICHOV</author>
</authors>
<title>Theory of K-representations as a Comprehensive Formal Framework for Developing a Multilingual Semantic Web.</title>
<journal>Informatica. An International Journal of Computing and Informatics (Slovenia),</journal>
<volume>34</volume>
<pages>387--396</pages>
<marker>FOMICHOV, </marker>
<rawString>FOMICHOV V.A. (2010b). Theory of K-representations as a Comprehensive Formal Framework for Developing a Multilingual Semantic Web. Informatica. An International Journal of Computing and Informatics (Slovenia), Vol. 34, No. 3, 387-396.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>A FRANK</author>
<author>H-U KRIEGER</author>
<author>F XU</author>
<author>H USZKOREIT</author>
<author>B CRYSMANN</author>
<author>B JRG</author>
<author>U SCHAEFER</author>
</authors>
<title>Question answering from structured knowledge sources.</title>
<date>2007</date>
<journal>J. of Applied Logic,</journal>
<volume>5</volume>
<issue>1</issue>
<marker>FRANK, KRIEGER, XU, USZKOREIT, CRYSMANN, JRG, SCHAEFER, 2007</marker>
<rawString>FRANK A., KRIEGER H.-U., XU F., USZKOREIT H., CRYSMANN B., JRG B., SCHAEFER U. (2007). Question answering from structured knowledge sources. J. of Applied Logic, 5 (1), 20-48.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>A-M POPESCU</author>
<author>O ETZIONI</author>
<author>H KAUTZ</author>
</authors>
<title>Towards a theory of natural language interfaces to th databases. In:</title>
<date>2003</date>
<booktitle>Proc. of the 8 International Conference on Intelligent User Interfaces,</booktitle>
<pages>149--157</pages>
<location>Miami, FL,</location>
<marker>POPESCU, ETZIONI, KAUTZ, 2003</marker>
<rawString>POPESCU A.-M., ETZIONI O., KAUTZ H. (2003). Towards a theory of natural language interfaces to th databases. In: Proc. of the 8 International Conference on Intelligent User Interfaces, Miami, FL, 149-157.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>V PRINCE</author>
<author>M ROCHE</author>
</authors>
<title>Information Retrieval in Biomedicine: Natural Language Processing for Knowledge Integration.</title>
<date>2009</date>
<journal>IGI Global.</journal>
<marker>PRINCE, ROCHE, 2009</marker>
<rawString>PRINCE V., ROCHE M., eds (2009). Information Retrieval in Biomedicine: Natural Language Processing for Knowledge Integration. IGI Global.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>P D TURNPENNY</author>
<author>S ELLARD</author>
</authors>
<title>Emery‟s Elements of Medical Genetics. Twelfth Edition.</title>
<date>2005</date>
<publisher>Elsevier Limited.</publisher>
<location>Edinburgh, London, New York, Oxford, Sydney, Toronto:</location>
<marker>TURNPENNY, ELLARD, 2005</marker>
<rawString>TURNPENNY P.D., ELLARD S. (2005). Emery‟s Elements of Medical Genetics. Twelfth Edition. Edinburgh, London, New York, Oxford, Sydney, Toronto: Elsevier Limited.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Y WILKS</author>
<author>C BREWSTER</author>
</authors>
<title>Natural Language Processing as a Foundation of the Semantic Web. Foundations and Trends</title>
<date>2006</date>
<journal>in Web Science,</journal>
<volume>1</volume>
<publisher>now Publishers Inc.</publisher>
<location>Hanover, MA; Delft:</location>
<marker>WILKS, BREWSTER, 2006</marker>
<rawString>WILKS Y., BREWSTER C. (2006). Natural Language Processing as a Foundation of the Semantic Web. Foundations and Trends in Web Science, Vol. 1, No. 3. Hanover, MA; Delft: now Publishers Inc.</rawString>
</citation>
</citationList>
</algorithm>
</algorithms>