<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<algorithms version="110505">
<algorithm name="ParsCit" version="110505">
<citationList>
<citation valid="true">
<title>Les Sables d’Olonne et l’équipe du Centre pour l’édition électronique ouverte (Cléo) pour leur collaboration et la mise à disposition des données du portail OpenEdition. Références</title>
<date>2007</date>
<booktitle>Proc. IJCAI,</booktitle>
<pages>2740--2747</pages>
<marker>2007</marker>
<rawString>TALN-RÉCITAL 2013, 17-21 Juin, Les Sables d’Olonne et l’équipe du Centre pour l’édition électronique ouverte (Cléo) pour leur collaboration et la mise à disposition des données du portail OpenEdition. Références DOWNEY, D., DUMAIS, S. et HORVITZ, E. (2007). Models of searching and browsing : Languages, studies, and applications. In Proc. IJCAI, pages 2740–2747.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Gayo AVELLO</author>
<author>D</author>
</authors>
<title>A Survey on Session Detection Methods in Query Logs and a Proposal for Future Evaluation.</title>
<date>2009</date>
<journal>Information Sciences,</journal>
<volume>179</volume>
<issue>12</issue>
<marker>AVELLO, D, 2009</marker>
<rawString>Gayo AVELLO, D. (2009). A Survey on Session Detection Methods in Query Logs and a Proposal for Future Evaluation. Information Sciences, 179(12):1822–1843.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>D et GÖKER HE</author>
<author>A</author>
</authors>
<title>Detecting Session Boundaries from Web User Logs.</title>
<date>2000</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the BCS-IRSG 22nd Annual Colloquium on Information Retrieval Research,</booktitle>
<pages>57--66</pages>
<marker>HE, A, 2000</marker>
<rawString>HE, D. et GÖKER, A. (2000). Detecting Session Boundaries from Web User Logs. In Proceedings of the BCS-IRSG 22nd Annual Colloquium on Information Retrieval Research, pages 57–66.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>D HE</author>
<author>A et HARPER GÖKER</author>
<author>D J</author>
</authors>
<title>Combining Evidence for Automatic Web Session Identification.</title>
<date>2002</date>
<booktitle>Information Processing and Management,</booktitle>
<pages>38--5</pages>
<marker>HE, GÖKER, J, 2002</marker>
<rawString>HE, D., GÖKER, A. et HARPER, D. J. (2002). Combining Evidence for Automatic Web Session Identification. Information Processing and Management, 38(5):727–742.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>P JACCARD</author>
</authors>
<title>Étude comparative de la distribution florale dans une portion des alpes et des jura.</title>
<date>1901</date>
<booktitle>Bulletin del la Société Vaudoise des Sciences Naturelles,</booktitle>
<pages>37--547</pages>
<marker>JACCARD, 1901</marker>
<rawString>JACCARD, P. (1901). Étude comparative de la distribution florale dans une portion des alpes et des jura. Bulletin del la Société Vaudoise des Sciences Naturelles, 37:547–579.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>B J JANSEN</author>
<author>A SPINK</author>
<author>C et KOSHMAN BLAKELY</author>
<author>S</author>
</authors>
<title>Defining a Session on Web Search Engines.</title>
<date>2007</date>
<journal>Journal of the American Society for Information Science and Technology,</journal>
<volume>58</volume>
<issue>6</issue>
<marker>JANSEN, SPINK, BLAKELY, S, 2007</marker>
<rawString>JANSEN, B. J., SPINK, A., BLAKELY, C. et KOSHMAN, S. (2007). Defining a Session on Web Search Engines. Journal of the American Society for Information Science and Technology, 58(6):862–871.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>R et KLINKNER JONES</author>
<author>K L</author>
</authors>
<title>Beyond the Session Timeout : Automatic Hierarchical Segmentation of Search Topics in Query Logs.</title>
<date>2008</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the 17th ACM Conference on Information and Knowledge Management,</booktitle>
<pages>699--708</pages>
<marker>JONES, L, 2008</marker>
<rawString>JONES, R. et KLINKNER, K. L. (2008). Beyond the Session Timeout : Automatic Hierarchical Segmentation of Search Topics in Query Logs. In Proceedings of the 17th ACM Conference on Information and Knowledge Management, pages 699–708.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>T et BIELIKOVÁ KRAMÁR</author>
<author>M</author>
</authors>
<title>Detecting Search Sessions Using Document Metadata and Implicit Feedback.</title>
<date>2012</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the WSCD 2012 Workshop on Web Search Click Data.</booktitle>
<marker>KRAMÁR, M, 2012</marker>
<rawString>KRAMÁR, T. et BIELIKOVÁ, M. (2012). Detecting Search Sessions Using Document Metadata and Implicit Feedback. In Proceedings of the WSCD 2012 Workshop on Web Search Click Data.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>S LEVA</author>
</authors>
<title>Les sessions de recherche comme contexte des requêtes.</title>
<date>2013</date>
<booktitle>In Actes de l’atelier Contextualisation de Messages Courts – 13e Conférence Francophone sur l’Extraction et la Gestion des Connaissances (EGC’13),</booktitle>
<pages>1--12</pages>
<marker>LEVA, 2013</marker>
<rawString>LEVA, S. (2013). Les sessions de recherche comme contexte des requêtes. In Actes de l’atelier Contextualisation de Messages Courts – 13e Conférence Francophone sur l’Extraction et la Gestion des Connaissances (EGC’13), pages 1–12.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>C LUCCHESE</author>
<author>S ORLANDO</author>
<author>R PEREGO</author>
<author>F et TOLOMEI SILVESTRI</author>
<author>G</author>
</authors>
<title>Identifying TaskBased Sessions in Search Engine Query Logs.</title>
<date>2011</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the 4th ACM International Conference on Web Search and Data Mining,</booktitle>
<pages>277--286</pages>
<marker>LUCCHESE, ORLANDO, PEREGO, SILVESTRI, G, 2011</marker>
<rawString>LUCCHESE, C., ORLANDO, S., PEREGO, R., SILVESTRI, F. et TOLOMEI, G. (2011). Identifying TaskBased Sessions in Search Engine Query Logs. In Proceedings of the 4th ACM International Conference on Web Search and Data Mining, pages 277–286.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>H C et ÇAVDUR OZMUTLU</author>
<author>F</author>
</authors>
<title>Application of Automatic Topic Identification on Excite Web Search Engine Data Logs.</title>
<date>2005</date>
<booktitle>Information Processing and Management,</booktitle>
<pages>41--5</pages>
<marker>OZMUTLU, F, 2005</marker>
<rawString>OZMUTLU, H. C. et ÇAVDUR, F. (2005). Application of Automatic Topic Identification on Excite Web Search Engine Data Logs. Information Processing and Management, 41(5):1243–1262.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>W M RAND</author>
</authors>
<title>Objective criteria for the evaluation of clustering methods.</title>
<date>1971</date>
<journal>Journal of the American Statistical Association,</journal>
<volume>66</volume>
<issue>336</issue>
<pages>846--850</pages>
<marker>RAND, 1971</marker>
<rawString>RAND, W. M. (1971). Objective criteria for the evaluation of clustering methods. Journal of the American Statistical Association, 66(336):pp. 846–850.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>C SILVERSTEIN</author>
<author>H MARAIS</author>
<author>M et MORICZ HENZINGER</author>
<author>M</author>
</authors>
<title>Analysis of a Very Large Web Search Engine Query Log.</title>
<date>1999</date>
<journal>SIGIR Forum,</journal>
<volume>33</volume>
<issue>1</issue>
<marker>SILVERSTEIN, MARAIS, HENZINGER, M, 1999</marker>
<rawString>SILVERSTEIN, C., MARAIS, H., HENZINGER, M. et MORICZ, M. (1999). Analysis of a Very Large Web Search Engine Query Log. SIGIR Forum, 33(1):6–12.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>A SPINK</author>
<author>M PARK</author>
<author>B J et PEDERSEN JANSEN</author>
<author>J</author>
</authors>
<title>Multitasking During Web Search Sessions.</title>
<date>2006</date>
<booktitle>Information Processing and Management, 42(1):264–275. 230 c ATALA</booktitle>
<marker>SPINK, PARK, JANSEN, J, 2006</marker>
<rawString>SPINK, A., PARK, M., JANSEN, B. J. et PEDERSEN, J. (2006). Multitasking During Web Search Sessions. Information Processing and Management, 42(1):264–275. 230 session="Posters TALN"c ATALA</rawString>
</citation>
</citationList>
</algorithm>
</algorithms>