<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<algorithms version="110505">
<algorithm name="ParsCit" version="110505">
<citationList>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>TALN-RECITAL</author>
</authors>
<title>17-21 Iuin, Les Sables d’Olonne</title>
<date>2004</date>
<institution>University of Edinburgh.</institution>
<location>Edinburg, UK.</location>
<marker>TALN-RECITAL, 2004</marker>
<rawString>TALN-RECITAL 2013, 17-21 Iuin, Les Sables d’Olonne CURRAN, ]. R. (2004). PhD Thesis: From distributional to semantic similarity. University of Edinburgh. Edinburg, UK.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>B DECADT</author>
<author>V HOSTE</author>
<author>W DAELEMANS</author>
<author>A VAN DEN BOSCH</author>
</authors>
<title>GAMBL, Genetic Algorithm Optimization of Memory-Based WSD.</title>
<date>2004</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the 3rd Int’l Workshop on the Evaluation ofSystems for the SemanticAnalysis of Text,</booktitle>
<pages>108--112</pages>
<location>Barcelona,</location>
<marker>DECADT, HOSTE, DAELEMANS, VAN DEN BOSCH, 2004</marker>
<rawString>DECADT, B., HOSTE, V., DAELEMANS, W. AND VAN DEN BOSCH, A. (2004). GAMBL, Genetic Algorithm Optimization of Memory-Based WSD. In Proceedings of the 3rd Int’l Workshop on the Evaluation ofSystems for the SemanticAnalysis of Text, pp. 108-112. Barcelona, Spain.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>M DENKOWSKI</author>
</authors>
<title>A Survey of Techniques for Unsupervised Word Sense Induction. In Language &amp; Statistics II Literature Review</title>
<date>2009</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the 12th Int’l Conference of the Italian Association forAI, pp.2</booktitle>
<volume>0</volume>
<pages>2</pages>
<marker>DENKOWSKI, 2009</marker>
<rawString>DENKOWSKI, M. (2009). A Survey of Techniques for Unsupervised Word Sense Induction. In Language &amp; Statistics II Literature Review DI MARCO, A. AND NAVIGLI, R. (2011). Clustering Web Search Results With Maximum Spanning Trees. In Proceedings of the 12th Int’l Conference of the Italian Association forAI, pp.2 0 1-2 1 2.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>D1 MARCO</author>
<author>A</author>
<author>R NAVIGLI</author>
</authors>
<title>Clustering and Diversifying Web Search Results with Graph-Based Word Sense Induction.</title>
<date>2013</date>
<booktitle>In Computational Linguistics 39(4),</booktitle>
<pages>201--212</pages>
<publisher>MIT.</publisher>
<marker>MARCO, A, NAVIGLI, 2013</marker>
<rawString>D1 MARCO, A. AND NAVIGLI, R. (2013). Clustering and Diversifying Web Search Results with Graph-Based Word Sense Induction. In Computational Linguistics 39(4), pp. 201-212. MIT.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>B DOROW</author>
<author>D WIDDOWS</author>
</authors>
<title>Discovering Corpus-Specific Word Senses.</title>
<date>2003</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the 10th Conference of the European Chapter of the Association for Computational Linguistics (EA CL</booktitle>
<pages>79--82</pages>
<location>Budapest, Hungary.</location>
<marker>DOROW, WIDDOWS, 2003</marker>
<rawString>DOROW, B. AND WIDDOWS, D. (2003). Discovering Corpus-Specific Word Senses. In Proceedings of the 10th Conference of the European Chapter of the Association for Computational Linguistics (EA CL 2003), pp. 79-82. Budapest, Hungary.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>D AND MOSES SERCI</author>
<author>E</author>
</authors>
<title>Using Curvature and Markov Clustering in Graphs for Lexical Acquisition and Word Sense Discrimination.</title>
<date>2005</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the MEANING-2005 Workshop.</booktitle>
<marker>SERCI, E, 2005</marker>
<rawString>DOROW, B., WIDDOWS, D., LING, K., ECKMANN, ]., SERCI, D.AND MOSES, E. (2005). Using Curvature and Markov Clustering in Graphs for Lexical Acquisition and Word Sense Discrimination. In Proceedings of the MEANING-2005 Workshop.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>P EDMONDS</author>
<author>S COTTON</author>
</authors>
<title>SENSEVAL-2: Overview.</title>
<date>2001</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the 2nd Int’l Workshop on Evaluating Word Sense Disambiguation Systems,</booktitle>
<pages>1--5</pages>
<marker>EDMONDS, COTTON, 2001</marker>
<rawString>EDMONDS, P. AND COTTON, S. (2001). SENSEVAL-2: Overview. In Proceedings of the 2nd Int’l Workshop on Evaluating Word Sense Disambiguation Systems, pp. 1-5 France.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>C FELLBAUM</author>
</authors>
<title>WordNet: An Electronic Database. MITPress.</title>
<date>1998</date>
<location>Cambridge, M.A, USA.</location>
<marker>FELLBAUM, 1998</marker>
<rawString>FELLBAUM, C. (ED.) (1998). WordNet: An Electronic Database. MITPress. Cambridge, M.A, USA.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>O FERRET</author>
</authors>
<title>Discovering Word Senses from a Network of Lexical Cooccurrences.</title>
<date>2004</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the 20th Int’l Conference on Computational Linguistics,</booktitle>
<volume>1</volume>
<pages>pp.</pages>
<marker>FERRET, 2004</marker>
<rawString>FERRET, O. (2004). Discovering Word Senses from a Network of Lexical Cooccurrences. In Proceedings of the 20th Int’l Conference on Computational Linguistics, pp. 1 32 6-1 3 32.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>R</author>
</authors>
<title>A synopsis of linguistic theory 1930-1955.</title>
<date>1957</date>
<journal>Selected Papers of ].R. Firth</journal>
<booktitle>In Studies in Linguistic Analysis (0Xford.&apos; Philological Society),</booktitle>
<volume>19</volume>
<pages>1--32</pages>
<editor>Palmer, F.R., (ed.)</editor>
<publisher>Longman.</publisher>
<location>London:</location>
<note>Reprinted in</note>
<marker>R, 1957</marker>
<rawString>FIRTH, ].R. (1957). A synopsis of linguistic theory 1930-1955. In Studies in Linguistic Analysis (0Xford.&apos; Philological Society), pp. 1-32. Reprinted in Palmer, F.R., (ed.) (1968). Selected Papers of ].R. Firth 19 52-19 59. London: Longman.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>S FORTUNATO</author>
</authors>
<title>Community Detection in Graphs.</title>
<date>2010</date>
<booktitle>In Physics Reports 486,</booktitle>
<pages>75--174</pages>
<marker>FORTUNATO, 2010</marker>
<rawString>FORTUNATO, S. (2010). Community Detection in Graphs. In Physics Reports 486, pp. 75-174.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>C GROZEA</author>
</authors>
<title>Finding Optimal Parameter Settings for High Performance Word Sense Disambiguation.</title>
<date>2004</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the 3rd Int’l Workshop on the Senseval-3,</booktitle>
<pages>12--5</pages>
<marker>GROZEA, 2004</marker>
<rawString>GROZEA, C. (2004). Finding Optimal Parameter Settings for High Performance Word Sense Disambiguation. In Proceedings of the 3rd Int’l Workshop on the Senseval-3, pp. 12 5-128.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Z HARRIS</author>
</authors>
<title>Distributional Structure.</title>
<date>1954</date>
<booktitle>In Papers in Structural and Transformational Linguistics,</booktitle>
<pages>775--79</pages>
<marker>HARRIS, 1954</marker>
<rawString>HARRIS, Z. (1954). Distributional Structure. In Papers in Structural and Transformational Linguistics, pp. 775-79 4.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>D HOPE</author>
<author>B KELLER</author>
</authors>
<title>MaxMax: A Graph-Based Soft Clustering Algorithm Applied to Word Sense Induction.</title>
<date>2013</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the Int’l Conference on Intelligent Text Processing and Computational Linguistics (CICLing-2013),</booktitle>
<pages>368--381</pages>
<location>Samos, Greece.</location>
<marker>HOPE, KELLER, 2013</marker>
<rawString>HOPE, D. AND KELLER, B. (2013). MaxMax: A Graph-Based Soft Clustering Algorithm Applied to Word Sense Induction. In Proceedings of the Int’l Conference on Intelligent Text Processing and Computational Linguistics (CICLing-2013), pp. 368-381. Samos, Greece.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>V HOSTE</author>
<author>I HENDRICKX</author>
<author>W DAELEMANS</author>
<author>A VAN DEN BOSCH</author>
</authors>
<title>Parameter Optimization for Machine-Learning of Word Sense Disambiguation.</title>
<date>2002</date>
<journal>In Natural Language Engineering</journal>
<volume>8</volume>
<pages>31--1</pages>
<publisher>Cambridge University Press.</publisher>
<marker>HOSTE, HENDRICKX, DAELEMANS, VAN DEN BOSCH, 2002</marker>
<rawString>HOSTE, V., HENDRICKX, I., DAELEMANS, W. AND VAN DEN BOSCH, A. (2002). Parameter Optimization for Machine-Learning of Word Sense Disambiguation. In Natural Language Engineering 8( 04 ), pp. 31 1-32 5. Cambridge University Press.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>E HOVY</author>
<author>M MARCUS</author>
<author>M PALMER</author>
<author>L RAMSHAW</author>
<author>R WEISCHEDEL</author>
</authors>
<title>OntoNotes: The 90% Solution.</title>
<date>2006</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the Human Language Technology Conference of the North American Chapter of the Association for Computational Linguistics,</booktitle>
<pages>5--7</pages>
<publisher>USA.</publisher>
<marker>HOVY, MARCUS, PALMER, RAMSHAW, WEISCHEDEL, 2006</marker>
<rawString>HOVY, E., MARCUS, M., PALMER, M., RAMSHAW, L. AND WEISCHEDEL, R. (2006). OntoNotes: The 90% Solution. In Proceedings of the Human Language Technology Conference of the North American Chapter of the Association for Computational Linguistics, pp. 5 7-60. USA.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>ATALA TALN-RECITAL</author>
</authors>
<title>Introduction to the special issue on word sense disambiguation: the state of the art.</title>
<date>2013</date>
<journal>In Computational Linguistics</journal>
<volume>24</volume>
<issue>1</issue>
<pages>17--21</pages>
<location>Cambridge, MA, USA.</location>
<contexts>
<context position="2847" citStr="TALN-RECITAL 2013" startWordPosition="406" endWordPosition="407"> Induction, under-resourced languages, lexical resources. M0&apos;I‘s-CLES: désambiguisation lexicale, induction de sens, langues peu dotées, ressources langagiéres. 1 Introduction Word Sense Disambiguation (WSD) is a core and open research problem in Computational Linguistics and Natural Language Processing (NLP), which was recognized at the beginning of the scientiﬁc interest in Machine Translation (MT) and Artiﬁcial Intelligence (AI). On a variety of word types and ambiguities research has progressed steadily to the point where WSD systems achieve relatively high levels of accuracy. 192 © ATALA TALN-RECITAL 2013, 17-21 Iuin, Les Sables d’Olonne The goal of a WSD is to computationally assign the correct sense of a word (i.e. meaning) in context (phrase, sentence, paragraph, text) from a predeﬁned sense inventory, when the word has multiple meanings. It is a pervasive characteristic of natural language. The problem is that words often have more than one meaning, sometimes fairly similar and sometimes completely different. For example, the word bank has several senses and may refer to the edge of a river, a building, or a ﬁnancial institution. The speciﬁc sense intended is determined by the textual cont</context>
<context position="6536" citStr="TALN-RECITAL 2013" startWordPosition="1005" endWordPosition="1006">paragraph, etc.). It is essentially a task of classification for word of a text: word senses are the possible classes, the context provides evidence (features), and each occurrence of a word is assigned to one or more of its possible classes based on the evidence. There are many methods to perform WSD. In this section, various types of approaches and algorithms for WSD will be brieﬂy presented. The reader can refer to (Ide and Véronis, 1998) for works before 1998 and (Agirre and Edmonds, 2006), (Navigli, 2009) or (McCarthy, 2009) for a complete and current state of the art of WSD. 193 © ATALA TALN-RECITAL 2013, 17-21 Iuin, Les Sables d’Olonne 2.1 Approaches WSD approaches can be categorized into supervised WSD and unsupervised WSD, and a further distinction can be made between knowledge-rich and knowledge-poor approaches (Navigli, 2009). Knowledge-rich methods involve the use of external knowledge sources whereas knowledge-poor methods do not Based on machine learning techniques, researchers distinguish between supervised methods and unsupervised methods. There are three mainstream approaches to WSD, namely: Supervised WSD, Minimally-supervised WSD, and Unsupervised WSD. Figure 1 presents various W</context>
<context position="9033" citStr="TALN-RECITAL 2013" startWordPosition="1358" endWordPosition="1359">re, reusing models from one language for another leads at best to a poor classification performance (Khapra et a1., 2009). 2.1.2 Minimally-supervisedWSD Minimally supervised methods use a sense inventory, a few sense-annotated example instances, and raw corpora. From the sense-annotated examples, the system induces the senses or categories of senses for the non-annotated data, and then it functions exactly as an unsupervised clustering approach. The most prominent Minimally supervised method (Y arowsky, 1995), however, to our knowledge, has not been evaluated on SemEval WSD tasks. 194 © ATALA TALN-RECITAL 2013, 17-21 Iuin, Les Sables d’Olonne 2.1.2.1 lﬁzowledge-based WSD Knowledge-based WSD algorithms are similar to Minimally-supervised WSD approaches. The objective of Knowledge-based methods is to exploit static knowledge resources, such as dictionaries, thesauri, glossaries, ontologies, collocation etc., to infer the senses of words in context. Degree (Navigli and Lapata, 2010; Ponzetto and Navigli, 2010) or Personalized PageRank (Agirre and Soroa, 2009) are among the latest knowledge-based systems in the literature that exploits WordNet (Fellbaum, 1998) or other resources like BabelNet (Navigli </context>
<context position="12267" citStr="TALN-RECITAL 2013" startWordPosition="1834" endWordPosition="1835">ated by a WSD algorithm, then P=R=F1. 3 Word Sense Induction Word sense induction (WSI) is the task of automatically identifying the senses of words in texts, without the need of handcrafted resources or manually annotated data. It is an unsupervised WSD technique use machine learning methods on raw corpora without relying on any external resources such as dictionaries or sense-tagged data. During the learning phase, algorithms induce words senses from raw text by clustering word occurrences following the Distributional Hypotliesis (Harris, 1954; Curran, 2004). This hypothesis was 195 © ATALA TALN-RECITAL 2013, 17-21 Iuin, Les Sables d’Olonne popularized with the phrase &amp;quot;a word is cliaracterized by the companyitkeeps&amp;quot; (Firth, 1957). Two words are considered semantically close if they co-occur with the same neighboring words. As a result, shifting the focus away from how to select the most suitable senses from an inventory towards how to automatically discover senses from a text By applying WSI it is possible to mitigate the Knowledge Acquisition Bottleneck (Wagner, 2008) problem. The single common thread to WSI methods is the reliance on clustering algorithms used on the words in the unannotated co</context>
<context position="15896" citStr="TALN-RECITAL 2013" startWordPosition="2390" endWordPosition="2391">Discrimination algorithm (Schiitze, 1998) based on large matrix computation methods. Another approach, presented by (Pinto et al., 2007), attempts to improve the usability of small, narrow-domain corpora through self-term expansion. (Brody and Lapata, 2009) shows that the task of word sense induction can also be framed in a Bayesian context by considering contexts of ambiguous words to be samples from a multinomial distribution. There are other extended-clustering approaches, that include the bi-gram clustering technique proposed by (Schiitze, 1998), the clustering technique using 196 © ATALA TALN-RECITAL 2013, 17-21 Iuin, Les Sables d’Olonne phrasal co-occurrences presented by (Dorow and Widdows, 2003), the technique for word clustering using a context window presented by (Ferret, 2004) and the method applying the Information Bottleneck algorithm for sense induction proposed by (Niu et al., 2007). These additional clustering techniques can be broadly categorized as either improving feature selection and enriching features or introducing more effective and efficient clustering algorithms. 3.1.3 Graph-basedApproaches The main hypothesis of co-occurrence graphs is assuming that the semantic of a word</context>
<context position="19286" citStr="TALN-RECITAL 2013" startWordPosition="2880" endWordPosition="2881">vel Algonthms for WSI Information Bottleneck c§lal§::ig:nMGOrg£lh TABLE 1 — Overview of Techniques for Word Sense Induction (Denkowski, 2009). Latent Semantic Analysis (LSA) (Landauer and Dumais, 1997; Landauer et al., 1998) is currently a very popular approach to WSI that operates on word spaces (Van de Cruys and Apidianaki, 2011). [AS aims at ﬁnding and extract latent dimensions of meaning using NMF (Non-negative Matrix Factorization ), PCA (Principal Component Analysis) or S VD (Singular Value Decomposition ). The extracted latent dimensions are then used to distinguish between 197 © ATALA TALN-RECITAL 2013, 17-21 Iuin, Les Sables d’Olonne different senses of a target word that are in turn used to disambiguate each given instance of that word. 3.1.4 Translation-orientedApproaches WSI approaches described above cover only monolingual data; in the context of Machine Translation (MT), recent work has been done to incorporate bilingual data into the sense induction task. Translation-oriented WSI approaches involve augmenting the source language context with target language equivalents. (Apidianaki, 2008) describes this process by using a bilingual corpus that has been word aligned by type and token </context>
<context position="22503" citStr="TALN-RECITAL 2013" startWordPosition="3383" endWordPosition="3384">overage and the homogeneity of a clustering output as opposed to the traditional clustering measure of F-Score (Zhao et al., 2005) that is most commonly used to assess the performance of WSI systems. 3.2.3 Evaluation as an Application Recently, (Navigli and Crisafulli, 2010; Di Marco and Navigli, 2013) proposed to evaluate WSI approaches as part of a speciﬁc application, where WSI techniques have been shown to consistently surpass symbolic state of the art systems (See section 4.3). The evaluation of WSI and WSD systems was performed in the context of Web searcli result clustering 198 © ATALA TALN-RECITAL 2013, 17-21 Iuin, Les Sables d’Olonne 3.3 SemEval WSI Evaluation Tasks This section brieﬂy describes the different SemEval workshops (from 2007 to 2013) with WSI evaluation tasks that focus on the evaluation of semantic analysis systems. 3.3.1 SemEval-2 007 Task 2 The goal of SemEval-2007 Task 2 (Agirre and Soroa, 2007) is to allow for the comparison across sense-induction and discrimination systems, and also to compare these systems to other supervised and knowledge-based systems. This task evaluates WSI systems on 33 nouns and 65 verbs (lexical sample), where the corpus consists of texts of the </context>
<context position="25582" citStr="TALN-RECITAL 2013" startWordPosition="3864" endWordPosition="3865">entioned difﬁculties, WSI is an attractive alternative to WSD, especially for under-resourced languages. The Figure 2 shows an overview of the state of freely available resources for a certain number of representative languages and the aim of the diagram is to give the reader an idea of the current situation. Making a highly precise diagram would be prohibitively complex and furthermore, the position of the various languages must be interpreted relatively to each other rather than in an absolute manner (except for English that we placed in the top righthand corner as a reference). 199 © ATALA TALN-RECITAL 2013, 17-21 Iuin, Les Sables d’Olonne Large - Size English Manually Sense~annotated Corpus Languages from Babe|Nel (French. Italian, German...) Dutch Same Chinese Japanese Annotated Data Hindi Marathi Most of the Bengali other No languages Assamese Knowledge-poor Knowledge Knowledge-rich FIGURE 2 — Computationally language richness — Data versus Knowledge (Schwab, 2013 [personal notes]). As described previously, two kinds of resources are difﬁcult/expensive to build: annotated corpora and lexical databases (static versus dynamic knowledge). While lexical databases can be used directly in many appl</context>
<context position="28487" citStr="TALN-RECITAL 2013" startWordPosition="4299" endWordPosition="4300">echniques for under-resourced languages are provided in this article, and also tries to provide a basic idea of the essentials of the ﬁeld. Here, the authors show a way to work on WSD by using WSI approaches in an unsupervised way, where very few resources (like corpora) are available. Basically, the performance of WSD systems depends heavily on which sense inventory is chosen, here WSI overcomes this issue by allowing unrestrained sets of senses. Besides, its evaluation is particularly hard because there is no easy way of comparing and ranking different representations of senses. 200 © ATALA TALN-RECITAL 2013, 17-21 Iuin, Les Sables d’Olonne Acknowledgements The work presented in this paper was conducted in the context of the VideoSense project, funded by the French National Research Agency (ANR) under its CONTINT 2009 program (grantANR-09-CORD-026). References AGIRRE, E., LOPEZ DE LACALLE, 0., AND SOROA, A. (2009). Knowledge-Based WSD on Speciﬁc Domains: Performing Better than Generic Supervised WSD. In Proceedings of the 21st lnt’l /oint Conference on Artiﬁcial lntelligence (l/CAI), pp. 1501- 1506. California. AGIRRE, E., MARTINEZ, D., LOPEZ DE LACALLE, 0., AND SOROA, A. (2 006a). Two Graph-Base</context>
</contexts>
<marker>TALN-RECITAL, 2013</marker>
<rawString>202 © ATALA TALN-RECITAL 2013, 17-21 Iuin, Les Sables d’Olonne IDE, N. AND VERONIS, ]. (1998). Introduction to the special issue on word sense disambiguation: the state of the art. In Computational Linguistics 24(1), pp. 02 -40. Cambridge, MA, USA.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>N IDE</author>
<author>T ERIAVEC</author>
<author>D TUFIS</author>
</authors>
<title>Sense Discrimination with Parallel Corpora.</title>
<date>2002</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings ofA CL-02 Workshop on Word Sense Disambiguation,</booktitle>
<pages>61--66</pages>
<publisher>USA.</publisher>
<marker>IDE, ERIAVEC, TUFIS, 2002</marker>
<rawString>IDE, N., ERIAVEC, T. AND TUFIS, D. (2002). Sense Discrimination with Parallel Corpora. In Proceedings ofA CL-02 Workshop on Word Sense Disambiguation, pp. 61-66. USA.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>S IABBARI</author>
<author>M HEPPLE</author>
<author>L GUTHRIE</author>
</authors>
<title>Evaluation Metrics for the Lexical Substitution Task.</title>
<date>2010</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the Human Language Technology Conference of the North American Chapter of the Association for Computational Linguistics,</booktitle>
<pages>289--292</pages>
<location>California, USA.</location>
<marker>IABBARI, HEPPLE, GUTHRIE, 2010</marker>
<rawString>IABBARI, S., HEPPLE, M. AND GUTHRIE, L. (2010). Evaluation Metrics for the Lexical Substitution Task. In Proceedings of the Human Language Technology Conference of the North American Chapter of the Association for Computational Linguistics, pp. 289-292. California, USA.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>P IN</author>
<author>Y WU</author>
<author>S YU</author>
</authors>
<title>SemEval-2007 Task 05: Multilingual Chinese-English Lexical Sample.</title>
<date>2007</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the 4th lnt’l Workshop on Semantic Evaluations (SemEval-2007),</booktitle>
<pages>pp.</pages>
<location>Prague, Czech Republic.</location>
<marker>IN, WU, YU, 2007</marker>
<rawString>]IN, P., WU, Y. AND YU, S. (2007). SemEval-2007 Task 05: Multilingual Chinese-English Lexical Sample. In Proceedings of the 4th lnt’l Workshop on Semantic Evaluations (SemEval-2007), pp. 19-23. Prague, Czech Republic.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>D IURGENS</author>
</authors>
<title>Word Sense Induction by Community Detection.</title>
<date>2011</date>
<journal>Computational Linguistics Human Language Technologies (A CL HL T</journal>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the 49th Annual Meeting of the Association for</booktitle>
<volume>201</volume>
<pages>pp.</pages>
<location>Portland, Oregon, USA.</location>
<marker>IURGENS, 2011</marker>
<rawString>IURGENS, D. (2011). Word Sense Induction by Community Detection. In Proceedings of the 49th Annual Meeting of the Association for Computational Linguistics Human Language Technologies (A CL HL T 201 1), pp. 2 4-2 8. Portland, Oregon, USA.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>M M KHAPRA</author>
<author>S SHAH</author>
<author>P KEDIA</author>
<author>P BHA&apos;I&apos;I‘ACHARYYA</author>
</authors>
<title>Projecting Parameters for Multilingual Word Sense Disambiguation.</title>
<date>2009</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the Conference on Empirical Methods in Natural Language Processing (EMNLP-09),</booktitle>
<pages>459--467</pages>
<marker>KHAPRA, SHAH, KEDIA, BHA&apos;I&apos;I‘ACHARYYA, 2009</marker>
<rawString>KHAPRA, M.M., SHAH, S., KEDIA, P., AND BHA&apos;I&apos;I‘ACHARYYA, P. (2009). Projecting Parameters for Multilingual Word Sense Disambiguation. In Proceedings of the Conference on Empirical Methods in Natural Language Processing (EMNLP-09), pp. 459 —467. Singapore.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>M M KHAPRA</author>
<author>A KULKARNI</author>
<author>S SOHONEY</author>
<author>P BHA&apos;I&apos;I‘ACHARYYA</author>
</authors>
<title>All Words Domain Adapted WSD: Finding a Middle Ground Between Supervision and Supervision.</title>
<date>2010</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the 48th Annual Meeting of the Association for Computational Linguistics,</booktitle>
<volume>1</volume>
<pages>pp.</pages>
<marker>KHAPRA, KULKARNI, SOHONEY, BHA&apos;I&apos;I‘ACHARYYA, 2010</marker>
<rawString>KHAPRA, M.M., KULKARNI, A., SOHONEY, S. AND BHA&apos;I&apos;I‘ACHARYYA, P. (2010). All Words Domain Adapted WSD: Finding a Middle Ground Between Supervision and Supervision. In Proceedings of the 48th Annual Meeting of the Association for Computational Linguistics, pp. 1 5 3 2 — 1 5 41.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>A KILGARRIFF</author>
</authors>
<title>SENSEVAL: An Exercise in Evaluating Word Sense Disambiguation Programs.</title>
<date>1998</date>
<booktitle>In Proceeding of the 1st lnt’l Conference on Language Resources and Evaluation (LREC1998),</booktitle>
<pages>581--588</pages>
<location>Granada,</location>
<marker>KILGARRIFF, 1998</marker>
<rawString>KILGARRIFF, A. (1998). SENSEVAL: An Exercise in Evaluating Word Sense Disambiguation Programs. In Proceeding of the 1st lnt’l Conference on Language Resources and Evaluation (LREC1998), pp. 581—588. Granada, Spain.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>I P KLAPAFFIS</author>
<author>S MANANDHAR</author>
</authors>
<title>007). UoY: A Hypergraph Model for Word Sense Induction and Disambiguation.</title>
<date></date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the 4th lnt’l Workshop on Semantic Evaluations (SemEval-2007),</booktitle>
<pages>414--417</pages>
<location>Prague, Czech Republic.</location>
<marker>KLAPAFFIS, MANANDHAR, </marker>
<rawString>KLAPAFFIS, I.P. AND MANANDHAR, S. (2 007). UoY: A Hypergraph Model for Word Sense Induction and Disambiguation. In Proceedings of the 4th lnt’l Workshop on Semantic Evaluations (SemEval-2007), pp. 414-417. Prague, Czech Republic.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>I P KLAPAFFIS</author>
<author>S MANANDHAR</author>
</authors>
<title>Evaluating Word Sense Induction and Disambiguation Methods.</title>
<date>2013</date>
<booktitle>In Language Resources and Evaluation,</booktitle>
<pages>1--2</pages>
<publisher>Springer.</publisher>
<marker>KLAPAFFIS, MANANDHAR, 2013</marker>
<rawString>KLAPAFFIS, I.P. AND MANANDHAR, S. (2013). Evaluating Word Sense Induction and Disambiguation Methods. In Language Resources and Evaluation, pp. 1-2 7. Springer.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<title>Domain-Speciﬁc Sense Distributions and Predominant Sense Acquisition.</title>
<date>2005</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the Human Language Technology Conference and the Conference on Empirical Methods in NLP,</booktitle>
<pages>419--426</pages>
<publisher>B.C., Canada.</publisher>
<marker>2005</marker>
<rawString>KOELING, R., MCCARTHY, D. AND CARROLL, ]. (2005). Domain-Speciﬁc Sense Distributions and Predominant Sense Acquisition. In Proceedings of the Human Language Technology Conference and the Conference on Empirical Methods in NLP, pp. 419-426. B.C., Canada.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>I KORKONTZELOS</author>
<author>S MANANDHAR</author>
</authors>
<title>UoY: Graphs of Unambiguous Vertices for Word Sense Induction and Disambiguation.</title>
<date>2010</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the 5th lnt’l Workshop on Semantic Evaluation (SemEval-2010),</booktitle>
<pages>355--358</pages>
<location>Uppsala,</location>
<marker>KORKONTZELOS, MANANDHAR, 2010</marker>
<rawString>KORKONTZELOS, I. AND MANANDHAR, S. (2010). UoY: Graphs of Unambiguous Vertices for Word Sense Induction and Disambiguation. In Proceedings of the 5th lnt’l Workshop on Semantic Evaluation (SemEval-2010), pp. 355-358, Uppsala, Sweden.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>T K LANDAUER</author>
<author>S T DUMAIS</author>
</authors>
<title>A Solution to Plato&apos;s Problem: The Latent Semantic Analysis Theory of Acquisition, Induction,</title>
<date>1997</date>
<booktitle>and Representation of Knowledge. ln Psychology Review(104),</booktitle>
<pages>211--240</pages>
<marker>LANDAUER, DUMAIS, 1997</marker>
<rawString>LANDAUER, T.K. AND DUMAIS, S.T. (1997). A Solution to Plato&apos;s Problem: The Latent Semantic Analysis Theory of Acquisition, Induction, and Representation of Knowledge. ln Psychology Review(104), pp. 211-240.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>T LANDAUER</author>
<author>P FOLTL</author>
<author>D LAHAM</author>
</authors>
<title>An Introduction to Latent Semantic Analysis.</title>
<date>1998</date>
<booktitle>In Discourse Processes,</booktitle>
<volume>2</volume>
<pages>pp.</pages>
<marker>LANDAUER, FOLTL, LAHAM, 1998</marker>
<rawString>LANDAUER, T., FOLTL, P. AND LAHAM, D. (1998). An Introduction to Latent Semantic Analysis. In Discourse Processes, pp. 2 5: 284-29 5.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>D LIN</author>
</authors>
<title>Automatic Retrieval and Clustering of Similar Words.</title>
<date>1998</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the 17th lnt’l Conference on Computational Linguistics,</booktitle>
<pages>768--774</pages>
<location>Quebec, Canada.</location>
<marker>LIN, 1998</marker>
<rawString>LIN, D. (1998). Automatic Retrieval and Clustering of Similar Words. In Proceedings of the 17th lnt’l Conference on Computational Linguistics, pp. 768-774. Quebec, Canada.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>ATALA TALN-RECITAL</author>
</authors>
<title>DIRT-Discovery of Inference Rules from Text</title>
<date>2013</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the 7th ACM SIGKDD Int&apos;l Conference on Knowledge Disco Very and Data Mining</booktitle>
<volume>3</volume>
<pages>17--21</pages>
<contexts>
<context position="2847" citStr="TALN-RECITAL 2013" startWordPosition="406" endWordPosition="407"> Induction, under-resourced languages, lexical resources. M0&apos;I‘s-CLES: désambiguisation lexicale, induction de sens, langues peu dotées, ressources langagiéres. 1 Introduction Word Sense Disambiguation (WSD) is a core and open research problem in Computational Linguistics and Natural Language Processing (NLP), which was recognized at the beginning of the scientiﬁc interest in Machine Translation (MT) and Artiﬁcial Intelligence (AI). On a variety of word types and ambiguities research has progressed steadily to the point where WSD systems achieve relatively high levels of accuracy. 192 © ATALA TALN-RECITAL 2013, 17-21 Iuin, Les Sables d’Olonne The goal of a WSD is to computationally assign the correct sense of a word (i.e. meaning) in context (phrase, sentence, paragraph, text) from a predeﬁned sense inventory, when the word has multiple meanings. It is a pervasive characteristic of natural language. The problem is that words often have more than one meaning, sometimes fairly similar and sometimes completely different. For example, the word bank has several senses and may refer to the edge of a river, a building, or a ﬁnancial institution. The speciﬁc sense intended is determined by the textual cont</context>
<context position="6536" citStr="TALN-RECITAL 2013" startWordPosition="1005" endWordPosition="1006">paragraph, etc.). It is essentially a task of classification for word of a text: word senses are the possible classes, the context provides evidence (features), and each occurrence of a word is assigned to one or more of its possible classes based on the evidence. There are many methods to perform WSD. In this section, various types of approaches and algorithms for WSD will be brieﬂy presented. The reader can refer to (Ide and Véronis, 1998) for works before 1998 and (Agirre and Edmonds, 2006), (Navigli, 2009) or (McCarthy, 2009) for a complete and current state of the art of WSD. 193 © ATALA TALN-RECITAL 2013, 17-21 Iuin, Les Sables d’Olonne 2.1 Approaches WSD approaches can be categorized into supervised WSD and unsupervised WSD, and a further distinction can be made between knowledge-rich and knowledge-poor approaches (Navigli, 2009). Knowledge-rich methods involve the use of external knowledge sources whereas knowledge-poor methods do not Based on machine learning techniques, researchers distinguish between supervised methods and unsupervised methods. There are three mainstream approaches to WSD, namely: Supervised WSD, Minimally-supervised WSD, and Unsupervised WSD. Figure 1 presents various W</context>
<context position="9033" citStr="TALN-RECITAL 2013" startWordPosition="1358" endWordPosition="1359">re, reusing models from one language for another leads at best to a poor classification performance (Khapra et a1., 2009). 2.1.2 Minimally-supervisedWSD Minimally supervised methods use a sense inventory, a few sense-annotated example instances, and raw corpora. From the sense-annotated examples, the system induces the senses or categories of senses for the non-annotated data, and then it functions exactly as an unsupervised clustering approach. The most prominent Minimally supervised method (Y arowsky, 1995), however, to our knowledge, has not been evaluated on SemEval WSD tasks. 194 © ATALA TALN-RECITAL 2013, 17-21 Iuin, Les Sables d’Olonne 2.1.2.1 lﬁzowledge-based WSD Knowledge-based WSD algorithms are similar to Minimally-supervised WSD approaches. The objective of Knowledge-based methods is to exploit static knowledge resources, such as dictionaries, thesauri, glossaries, ontologies, collocation etc., to infer the senses of words in context. Degree (Navigli and Lapata, 2010; Ponzetto and Navigli, 2010) or Personalized PageRank (Agirre and Soroa, 2009) are among the latest knowledge-based systems in the literature that exploits WordNet (Fellbaum, 1998) or other resources like BabelNet (Navigli </context>
<context position="12267" citStr="TALN-RECITAL 2013" startWordPosition="1834" endWordPosition="1835">ated by a WSD algorithm, then P=R=F1. 3 Word Sense Induction Word sense induction (WSI) is the task of automatically identifying the senses of words in texts, without the need of handcrafted resources or manually annotated data. It is an unsupervised WSD technique use machine learning methods on raw corpora without relying on any external resources such as dictionaries or sense-tagged data. During the learning phase, algorithms induce words senses from raw text by clustering word occurrences following the Distributional Hypotliesis (Harris, 1954; Curran, 2004). This hypothesis was 195 © ATALA TALN-RECITAL 2013, 17-21 Iuin, Les Sables d’Olonne popularized with the phrase &amp;quot;a word is cliaracterized by the companyitkeeps&amp;quot; (Firth, 1957). Two words are considered semantically close if they co-occur with the same neighboring words. As a result, shifting the focus away from how to select the most suitable senses from an inventory towards how to automatically discover senses from a text By applying WSI it is possible to mitigate the Knowledge Acquisition Bottleneck (Wagner, 2008) problem. The single common thread to WSI methods is the reliance on clustering algorithms used on the words in the unannotated co</context>
<context position="15896" citStr="TALN-RECITAL 2013" startWordPosition="2390" endWordPosition="2391">Discrimination algorithm (Schiitze, 1998) based on large matrix computation methods. Another approach, presented by (Pinto et al., 2007), attempts to improve the usability of small, narrow-domain corpora through self-term expansion. (Brody and Lapata, 2009) shows that the task of word sense induction can also be framed in a Bayesian context by considering contexts of ambiguous words to be samples from a multinomial distribution. There are other extended-clustering approaches, that include the bi-gram clustering technique proposed by (Schiitze, 1998), the clustering technique using 196 © ATALA TALN-RECITAL 2013, 17-21 Iuin, Les Sables d’Olonne phrasal co-occurrences presented by (Dorow and Widdows, 2003), the technique for word clustering using a context window presented by (Ferret, 2004) and the method applying the Information Bottleneck algorithm for sense induction proposed by (Niu et al., 2007). These additional clustering techniques can be broadly categorized as either improving feature selection and enriching features or introducing more effective and efficient clustering algorithms. 3.1.3 Graph-basedApproaches The main hypothesis of co-occurrence graphs is assuming that the semantic of a word</context>
<context position="19286" citStr="TALN-RECITAL 2013" startWordPosition="2880" endWordPosition="2881">vel Algonthms for WSI Information Bottleneck c§lal§::ig:nMGOrg£lh TABLE 1 — Overview of Techniques for Word Sense Induction (Denkowski, 2009). Latent Semantic Analysis (LSA) (Landauer and Dumais, 1997; Landauer et al., 1998) is currently a very popular approach to WSI that operates on word spaces (Van de Cruys and Apidianaki, 2011). [AS aims at ﬁnding and extract latent dimensions of meaning using NMF (Non-negative Matrix Factorization ), PCA (Principal Component Analysis) or S VD (Singular Value Decomposition ). The extracted latent dimensions are then used to distinguish between 197 © ATALA TALN-RECITAL 2013, 17-21 Iuin, Les Sables d’Olonne different senses of a target word that are in turn used to disambiguate each given instance of that word. 3.1.4 Translation-orientedApproaches WSI approaches described above cover only monolingual data; in the context of Machine Translation (MT), recent work has been done to incorporate bilingual data into the sense induction task. Translation-oriented WSI approaches involve augmenting the source language context with target language equivalents. (Apidianaki, 2008) describes this process by using a bilingual corpus that has been word aligned by type and token </context>
<context position="22503" citStr="TALN-RECITAL 2013" startWordPosition="3383" endWordPosition="3384">overage and the homogeneity of a clustering output as opposed to the traditional clustering measure of F-Score (Zhao et al., 2005) that is most commonly used to assess the performance of WSI systems. 3.2.3 Evaluation as an Application Recently, (Navigli and Crisafulli, 2010; Di Marco and Navigli, 2013) proposed to evaluate WSI approaches as part of a speciﬁc application, where WSI techniques have been shown to consistently surpass symbolic state of the art systems (See section 4.3). The evaluation of WSI and WSD systems was performed in the context of Web searcli result clustering 198 © ATALA TALN-RECITAL 2013, 17-21 Iuin, Les Sables d’Olonne 3.3 SemEval WSI Evaluation Tasks This section brieﬂy describes the different SemEval workshops (from 2007 to 2013) with WSI evaluation tasks that focus on the evaluation of semantic analysis systems. 3.3.1 SemEval-2 007 Task 2 The goal of SemEval-2007 Task 2 (Agirre and Soroa, 2007) is to allow for the comparison across sense-induction and discrimination systems, and also to compare these systems to other supervised and knowledge-based systems. This task evaluates WSI systems on 33 nouns and 65 verbs (lexical sample), where the corpus consists of texts of the </context>
<context position="25582" citStr="TALN-RECITAL 2013" startWordPosition="3864" endWordPosition="3865">entioned difﬁculties, WSI is an attractive alternative to WSD, especially for under-resourced languages. The Figure 2 shows an overview of the state of freely available resources for a certain number of representative languages and the aim of the diagram is to give the reader an idea of the current situation. Making a highly precise diagram would be prohibitively complex and furthermore, the position of the various languages must be interpreted relatively to each other rather than in an absolute manner (except for English that we placed in the top righthand corner as a reference). 199 © ATALA TALN-RECITAL 2013, 17-21 Iuin, Les Sables d’Olonne Large - Size English Manually Sense~annotated Corpus Languages from Babe|Nel (French. Italian, German...) Dutch Same Chinese Japanese Annotated Data Hindi Marathi Most of the Bengali other No languages Assamese Knowledge-poor Knowledge Knowledge-rich FIGURE 2 — Computationally language richness — Data versus Knowledge (Schwab, 2013 [personal notes]). As described previously, two kinds of resources are difﬁcult/expensive to build: annotated corpora and lexical databases (static versus dynamic knowledge). While lexical databases can be used directly in many appl</context>
<context position="28487" citStr="TALN-RECITAL 2013" startWordPosition="4299" endWordPosition="4300">echniques for under-resourced languages are provided in this article, and also tries to provide a basic idea of the essentials of the ﬁeld. Here, the authors show a way to work on WSD by using WSI approaches in an unsupervised way, where very few resources (like corpora) are available. Basically, the performance of WSD systems depends heavily on which sense inventory is chosen, here WSI overcomes this issue by allowing unrestrained sets of senses. Besides, its evaluation is particularly hard because there is no easy way of comparing and ranking different representations of senses. 200 © ATALA TALN-RECITAL 2013, 17-21 Iuin, Les Sables d’Olonne Acknowledgements The work presented in this paper was conducted in the context of the VideoSense project, funded by the French National Research Agency (ANR) under its CONTINT 2009 program (grantANR-09-CORD-026). References AGIRRE, E., LOPEZ DE LACALLE, 0., AND SOROA, A. (2009). Knowledge-Based WSD on Speciﬁc Domains: Performing Better than Generic Supervised WSD. In Proceedings of the 21st lnt’l /oint Conference on Artiﬁcial lntelligence (l/CAI), pp. 1501- 1506. California. AGIRRE, E., MARTINEZ, D., LOPEZ DE LACALLE, 0., AND SOROA, A. (2 006a). Two Graph-Base</context>
</contexts>
<marker>TALN-RECITAL, 2013</marker>
<rawString>203 © ATALA TALN-RECITAL 2013, 17-21 Iuin, Les Sables d’Olonne LIN, D. AND PAN&apos;I‘EL, P. (2001). DIRT-Discovery of Inference Rules from Text In Proceedings of the 7th ACM SIGKDD Int&apos;l Conference on Knowledge Disco Very and Data Mining pp. 3 2 3-328.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>S MANANDHAR</author>
<author>I P KLAPAI-‘I‘IS</author>
<author>D DLIGACH</author>
<author>S S PRADHAN</author>
</authors>
<date>2010</date>
<booktitle>SemEval-2010 Task 14: Word Sense Induction &amp; Disambiguation. In Proceedings of the 5th Int&apos;l Workshop on Semantic Evaluation (SemEval-2010),</booktitle>
<pages>63--68</pages>
<location>Uppsala,</location>
<marker>MANANDHAR, KLAPAI-‘I‘IS, DLIGACH, PRADHAN, 2010</marker>
<rawString>MANANDHAR, S., KLAPAI-‘I‘IS, I.P., DLIGACH, D. AND PRADHAN, S.S. (2010). SemEval-2010 Task 14: Word Sense Induction &amp; Disambiguation. In Proceedings of the 5th Int&apos;l Workshop on Semantic Evaluation (SemEval-2010), pp. 63-68. Uppsala, Sweden.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>S MANANDHAR</author>
<author>D YURET</author>
</authors>
<title>SemEval-2012: Semantic Evaluation Exercises.</title>
<date>2012</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the SemEval-2012: Semantic Evaluation Exercises.</booktitle>
<location>Montreal, Canada.</location>
<marker>MANANDHAR, YURET, 2012</marker>
<rawString>MANANDHAR, S. AND YURET, D. (2012). SemEval-2012: Semantic Evaluation Exercises. In Proceedings of the SemEval-2012: Semantic Evaluation Exercises. Montreal, Canada.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>D MCCARTHY</author>
<author>R NAVIGLI</author>
</authors>
<title>The English Lexical Substitution Task.</title>
<date>2009</date>
<journal>In Language Resources and Evaluation</journal>
<volume>43</volume>
<issue>2</issue>
<pages>139--159</pages>
<publisher>Springer.</publisher>
<marker>MCCARTHY, NAVIGLI, 2009</marker>
<rawString>MCCARTHY, D. AND NAVIGLI, R. (2009). The English Lexical Substitution Task. In Language Resources and Evaluation 43(2), pp. 139-159. Springer.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>R MIHALCEA</author>
<author>P EDMONDS</author>
</authors>
<title>Senseval-3: The Third Int&apos;l Workshop on the Evaluation of Systems for the Semantic Analysis of Text.</title>
<date>2004</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of Senseval-3: The 3rd Int&apos;l Workshop on the Evaluation of Systems for the Semantic Analysis of Text.</booktitle>
<marker>MIHALCEA, EDMONDS, 2004</marker>
<rawString>MIHALCEA, R. AND EDMONDS, P. (2004). Senseval-3: The Third Int&apos;l Workshop on the Evaluation of Systems for the Semantic Analysis of Text. In Proceedings of Senseval-3: The 3rd Int&apos;l Workshop on the Evaluation of Systems for the Semantic Analysis of Text.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>R MIHALCEA</author>
<author>E FARUQUE</author>
</authors>
<title>Senselearner: Minimally Supervised Word Sense Disambiguation for All Words in Open Text.</title>
<date>2004</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings ofA CL/SICLEX,</booktitle>
<pages>15--5</pages>
<marker>MIHALCEA, FARUQUE, 2004</marker>
<rawString>MIHALCEA, R. AND FARUQUE, E. (2004). Senselearner: Minimally Supervised Word Sense Disambiguation for All Words in Open Text. In Proceedings ofA CL/SICLEX, pp. 15 5-1 58.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>R NAVIGLI</author>
</authors>
<title>Word Sense Disambiguation: A Survey. In</title>
<date>2009</date>
<journal>ACM ComputingSurveys (CSUR)</journal>
<volume>41</volume>
<issue>2</issue>
<pages>1--69</pages>
<publisher>ACM.</publisher>
<marker>NAVIGLI, 2009</marker>
<rawString>NAVIGLI, R. (2009). Word Sense Disambiguation: A Survey. In ACM ComputingSurveys (CSUR) 41(2), pp. 1-69. ACM.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>R NAVIGLI</author>
<author>G CRISAFULLI</author>
</authors>
<title>Inducing Word Senses to Improve Web Search Result Clustering.</title>
<date>2010</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the Conference on Empirical Methods in Natural Language Processing (EMNLP-10),</booktitle>
<pages>116--126</pages>
<location>Boston, USA.</location>
<marker>NAVIGLI, CRISAFULLI, 2010</marker>
<rawString>NAVIGLI, R. AND CRISAFULLI, G. (2010). Inducing Word Senses to Improve Web Search Result Clustering. In Proceedings of the Conference on Empirical Methods in Natural Language Processing (EMNLP-10), pp. 116-126. Boston, USA.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>R NAVIGLI</author>
<author>D IURGENS</author>
<author>D VANNELLA</author>
</authors>
<title>SemEval-2013 Task 12: Multilingual Word Sense Disambiguation.</title>
<date>2013</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the 7th Int&apos;l Workshop on Semantic Evaluation, the 2nd ]oint Conference on Lexical and Computational Semantics,</booktitle>
<volume>1</volume>
<pages>pp.</pages>
<location>Atlanta, GA, USA.</location>
<marker>NAVIGLI, IURGENS, VANNELLA, 2013</marker>
<rawString>NAVIGLI R., IURGENS, D. AND VANNELLA, D. (2013). SemEval-2013 Task 12: Multilingual Word Sense Disambiguation. In Proceedings of the 7th Int&apos;l Workshop on Semantic Evaluation, the 2nd ]oint Conference on Lexical and Computational Semantics, pp. 1 16-1 2 6. Atlanta, GA, USA.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>R NAVIGLI</author>
<author>M LAPATA</author>
</authors>
<title>An Experimental Study on Graph Connectivity for Unsupervised Word Sense Disambiguation. In</title>
<date>2010</date>
<journal>IEEE Transactions on Pattern Analysis and Machine Intelligence</journal>
<volume>32</volume>
<issue>4</issue>
<pages>678--692</pages>
<publisher>IEEE.</publisher>
<marker>NAVIGLI, LAPATA, 2010</marker>
<rawString>NAVIGLI, R. AND LAPATA, M. (2010). An Experimental Study on Graph Connectivity for Unsupervised Word Sense Disambiguation. In IEEE Transactions on Pattern Analysis and Machine Intelligence 32(4), pp. 678-692. IEEE.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>R NAVIGLI</author>
<author>K C LITKOWSKI</author>
<author>HARGRAVES</author>
</authors>
<title>SemEval-2007 Task 07: Coarse-Grained English All-Words Task.</title>
<date>2007</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of 4th Int&apos;l Workshop on SemEval-2007,</booktitle>
<pages>30--35</pages>
<marker>NAVIGLI, LITKOWSKI, HARGRAVES, 2007</marker>
<rawString>NAVIGLI, R., LITKOWSKI, K.C. AND HARGRAVES, 0. (2007). SemEval-2007 Task 07: Coarse-Grained English All-Words Task. In Proceedings of 4th Int&apos;l Workshop on SemEval-2007, pp. 30-35.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>R NAVIGLI</author>
<author>S P PONZE&apos;I&apos;I‘0</author>
</authors>
<title>BabelNet: Building a Very Large Multilingual Semantic Network.</title>
<date>2010</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the 48th Annual Meeting of the Association for Computational Linguistics (ACL</booktitle>
<pages>216--225</pages>
<location>Uppsala,</location>
<marker>NAVIGLI, PONZE&apos;I&apos;I‘0, 2010</marker>
<rawString>NAVIGLI, R. AND PONZE&apos;I&apos;I‘0, S.P. (2010). BabelNet: Building a Very Large Multilingual Semantic Network. In Proceedings of the 48th Annual Meeting of the Association for Computational Linguistics (ACL 2010), pp. 216-225. Uppsala, Sweden.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>R NAVIGLI</author>
<author>D VANNELLA</author>
</authors>
<title>SemEval-2013 Task 11: Word Sense Induction &amp; Disambiguation within an End-User Application.</title>
<date>2013</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the 7th Int&apos;l Workshop on Semantic Evaluations (SemEval-2013).</booktitle>
<location>Atlanta, GA, USA.</location>
<marker>NAVIGLI, VANNELLA, 2013</marker>
<rawString>NAVIGLI, R. AND VANNELLA, D. (2013). SemEval-2013 Task 11: Word Sense Induction &amp; Disambiguation within an End-User Application. In Proceedings of the 7th Int&apos;l Workshop on Semantic Evaluations (SemEval-2013). Atlanta, GA, USA.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>D I</author>
<author>C TAN</author>
</authors>
<title>I2R: Three Systems for Word Sense Discrimination Chinese Word Sense Disambiguation and English Word Sense Disambiguation.</title>
<date>2007</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the 4th Int&apos;l Workshop on Semantic Evaluations,</booktitle>
<pages>177--182</pages>
<location>Prague, Czech Republic.</location>
<marker>I, TAN, 2007</marker>
<rawString>NIU, Z., ]I, D. AND TAN, C. (2007). I2R: Three Systems for Word Sense Discrimination Chinese Word Sense Disambiguation and English Word Sense Disambiguation. In Proceedings of the 4th Int&apos;l Workshop on Semantic Evaluations, pp. 177-182. Prague, Czech Republic.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>P PANTEL</author>
<author>D LIN</author>
</authors>
<title>Discovering Word Senses from Text.</title>
<date>2002</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the 8th Int&apos;l Conference on Knowledge Discoveiy and Data Mining,</booktitle>
<volume>6</volume>
<pages>pp.</pages>
<marker>PANTEL, LIN, 2002</marker>
<rawString>PANTEL, P. AND LIN, D. (2002). Discovering Word Senses from Text. In Proceedings of the 8th Int&apos;l Conference on Knowledge Discoveiy and Data Mining, pp. 6 1 3-619. Canada.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>D PINTO</author>
<author>P Rosso</author>
<author>H IIMENEZ-SALAZAR</author>
</authors>
<title>UPV-SI: Word Sense Induction Using SelfTerm Expansion.</title>
<date>2007</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of 4th Int&apos;l Workshop on Semantic Evaluations,</booktitle>
<pages>430--433</pages>
<marker>PINTO, Rosso, IIMENEZ-SALAZAR, 2007</marker>
<rawString>PINTO, D., Rosso, P. AND IIMENEZ-SALAZAR, H. (2007). UPV-SI: Word Sense Induction Using SelfTerm Expansion. In Proceedings of 4th Int&apos;l Workshop on Semantic Evaluations, pp. 430-433.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>ATALA TALN-RECITAL</author>
</authors>
<title>17-21 Iuin, Les Sables d’Olonne PONZE&apos;I&apos;I‘0,</title>
<date>2010</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the 48th Annual Meeting of the Association for Computational Linguistics (A CL 2010),</booktitle>
<volume>1</volume>
<pages>pp.</pages>
<location>Uppsala,</location>
<marker>TALN-RECITAL, 2010</marker>
<rawString>204 © ATALA TALN-RECITAL 2013, 17-21 Iuin, Les Sables d’Olonne PONZE&apos;I&apos;I‘0, S.P. AND NAVIGLI, R. (2010). Knowledge-Rich Word Sense Disambiguation Rivaling Supervised System. In Proceedings of the 48th Annual Meeting of the Association for Computational Linguistics (A CL 2010), pp. 1 52 2 -1 5 3 1. Uppsala, Sweden.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>W M RAND</author>
</authors>
<title>Objective Criteria for the Evaluation of Clustering Methods.</title>
<date>1971</date>
<journal>In ]ournal of the American Statistical Association</journal>
<volume>66</volume>
<issue>336</issue>
<pages>846--850</pages>
<publisher>Taylor &amp; Francis.</publisher>
<marker>RAND, 1971</marker>
<rawString>RAND, W. M. (1971). Objective Criteria for the Evaluation of Clustering Methods. In ]ournal of the American Statistical Association 66(336), pp. 846-850. Taylor &amp; Francis.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<title>V-Measure: A Conditional Entropy-Based External Cluster Evaluation Measure.</title>
<date>2007</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the Conference on Empirical Methods in Natural Language Processing and Computational Natural Language Learning,</booktitle>
<volume>41</volume>
<pages>pp.</pages>
<contexts>
<context position="29475" citStr="(2007)" startWordPosition="4451" endWordPosition="4451">ic Supervised WSD. In Proceedings of the 21st lnt’l /oint Conference on Artiﬁcial lntelligence (l/CAI), pp. 1501- 1506. California. AGIRRE, E., MARTINEZ, D., LOPEZ DE LACALLE, 0., AND SOROA, A. (2 006a). Two Graph-Based Algorithms for State of the Art WSD. In Proceedings of the Conference on EMNLP, pp. 585-593. AGIRRE, E., MARTINEZ, D., LOPEZ DE LACALLE, 0. AND SOROA, A. (2006b). Evaluating and Optimizing the Parameters of an Unsupervised Graph-Based WSD Algorithm. In Proceedings of TeXtGraphs: the 2nd Workshop on Graph Based Methods for NLP, pp. 89-96. New York, USA. AGIRRE, E. AND SOROA, A. (2007). SemEval-2007 Task 2: Evaluating Word Sense Induction and Discrimination Systems. In Proceedings of the 4th lnt’l Workshop on .S&apos;emEval-2007, pp. 7-12. AGIRRE, E. AND SOROA, A. (2009). Personalizing PageRank for Word Sense Disambiguation. In Proceedings of the 12th Conference of the EA CL 2009, pp. 33-41. Athens, Greece. AGIRRE, E., LOPEZ DE LACALLE, 0., FELLBAUM, C., HSIEH, S.K., TESCONI, M., MONACHINI, M., VOssEN, P. AND SEGERS, R. (2010). SemEval-2010 Task 17: All-Words Word Sense Disambiguation on a Speciﬁc Domain. In Proceedings of the 5th lnt’l Workshop on Semantic Evaluation, pp. 75-80</context>
</contexts>
<marker>2007</marker>
<rawString>ROSENBERG, A. AND HIRSCHBERG, ]. (2007). V-Measure: A Conditional Entropy-Based External Cluster Evaluation Measure. In Proceedings of the Conference on Empirical Methods in Natural Language Processing and Computational Natural Language Learning, pp. 41 0 -42 0.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>M SABOU</author>
<author>K BONTCHEVA</author>
<author>A SCHARL</author>
</authors>
<title>Crowdsourcing Research Opportunities: Lessons from Natural Language Processing.</title>
<date>2012</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the 12th lnt’l Conference on Knowledge Managementand Knowledge Technologies,</booktitle>
<volume>1</volume>
<pages>pp.</pages>
<marker>SABOU, BONTCHEVA, SCHARL, 2012</marker>
<rawString>SABOU, M., BONTCHEVA, K. AND SCHARL, A. (2012). Crowdsourcing Research Opportunities: Lessons from Natural Language Processing. In Proceedings of the 12th lnt’l Conference on Knowledge Managementand Knowledge Technologies, pp. 1 7: 1-1 7:8.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>H SCHU&apos;I&apos;LE</author>
</authors>
<title>Automatic Word Sense Discrimination.</title>
<date>1998</date>
<journal>ln Computational Linguistics</journal>
<volume>24</volume>
<issue>1</issue>
<pages>97--124</pages>
<publisher>MIT Press.</publisher>
<marker>SCHU&apos;I&apos;LE, 1998</marker>
<rawString>SCHU&apos;I&apos;LE, H. (1998). Automatic Word Sense Discrimination. ln Computational Linguistics 24(1), pp. 97-124. MIT Press.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>M STEINBACH</author>
<author>G KARYPIS</author>
<author>V KUMAR</author>
</authors>
<title>A Comparison of Document Clustering Techniques.</title>
<date>2000</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the 6th ACM SIGKDD lnt’l Conference on Knowledge Discovery andData Mining</booktitle>
<pages>52--5</pages>
<location>Boston, USA.</location>
<marker>STEINBACH, KARYPIS, KUMAR, 2000</marker>
<rawString>STEINBACH, M., KARYPIS, G., AND KUMAR, V. (2000). A Comparison of Document Clustering Techniques. In Proceedings of the 6th ACM SIGKDD lnt’l Conference on Knowledge Discovery andData Mining pp. 52 5-526. Boston, USA.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>T VAN DE CRUYS</author>
<author>M APIDIANAKI</author>
</authors>
<title>Latent Semantic Word Sense Induction and Disambiguation.</title>
<date>2011</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the 49th Annual Meeting of the Association for Computational Linguistics: Human Language Technologies,</booktitle>
<pages>1476--1485</pages>
<location>Oregon, USA.</location>
<marker>VAN DE CRUYS, APIDIANAKI, 2011</marker>
<rawString>VAN DE CRUYS, T. AND APIDIANAKI, M. (2011). Latent Semantic Word Sense Induction and Disambiguation. In Proceedings of the 49th Annual Meeting of the Association for Computational Linguistics: Human Language Technologies, pp. 1476- 1485. Oregon, USA.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>T VAN DE CRUYS</author>
</authors>
<title>PhD Thesis: Mining for Meaning - the Extraction of Lexico-Semantic Knowledge from</title>
<date>2010</date>
<pages>12--18</pages>
<publisher>The</publisher>
<institution>Text University of Groningen,</institution>
<marker>VAN DE CRUYS, 2010</marker>
<rawString>VAN DE CRUYS, T. (2010). PhD Thesis: Mining for Meaning - the Extraction of Lexico-Semantic Knowledge from Text University of Groningen, pp. 12-18. The Netherlands.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<title>Hyperlex: Lexical Cartography for Information Retrieval.</title>
<date>2004</date>
<journal>In Computer Speech and Language</journal>
<volume>18</volume>
<issue>3</issue>
<pages>223--252</pages>
<marker>2004</marker>
<rawString>VERONIS, ]. (2004). Hyperlex: Lexical Cartography for Information Retrieval. In Computer Speech and Language 18(3), pp. 223-252.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>L VON AHN</author>
</authors>
<title>Games With A Purpose.</title>
<date>2006</date>
<journal>In Computer</journal>
<volume>6</volume>
<issue>39</issue>
<pages>92--94</pages>
<publisher>IEEE Computer Society Press.</publisher>
<marker>VON AHN, 2006</marker>
<rawString>VON AHN, L. (2006). Games With A Purpose. In Computer 6(39), pp. 92-94. IEEE Computer Society Press.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>C WAGNER</author>
</authors>
<title>Breaking the knowledge acquisition bottleneck through conversational knowledge management.</title>
<date>2006</date>
<booktitle>In Information Resources Management /ournal (IRM/)</booktitle>
<volume>19</volume>
<issue>1</issue>
<pages>70--83</pages>
<publisher>IGI Global.</publisher>
<marker>WAGNER, 2006</marker>
<rawString>WAGNER, C. (2006). Breaking the knowledge acquisition bottleneck through conversational knowledge management. In Information Resources Management /ournal (IRM/) 19(1), pp. 70-83. IGI Global.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>A WANG</author>
<author>C D V HOANG</author>
<author>M Y KAN</author>
</authors>
<title>Perspectives on Crowdsourcing Annotations for Natural Language Processing.</title>
<date>2004</date>
<booktitle>In Language Resources and Evaluation,</booktitle>
<pages>1--2</pages>
<publisher>Springer.</publisher>
<marker>WANG, HOANG, KAN, 2004</marker>
<rawString>WANG, A., HOANG, C.D.V. AND KAN, M.Y. (2004). Perspectives on Crowdsourcing Annotations for Natural Language Processing. In Language Resources and Evaluation, pp. 1-2 3. Springer.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>D WIDDOWS</author>
<author>B DOROW</author>
</authors>
<title>A Graph Model for Unsupervised Lexical Acquisition.</title>
<date>2002</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the 19th lnt’l Conference on Computational Linguistics,</booktitle>
<pages>1--7</pages>
<marker>WIDDOWS, DOROW, 2002</marker>
<rawString>WIDDOWS, D. AND DOROW, B. (2002). A Graph Model for Unsupervised Lexical Acquisition. In Proceedings of the 19th lnt’l Conference on Computational Linguistics, pp. 1-7.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>D YAROWSKY</author>
</authors>
<title>Unsupervised Word Sense Disambiguation Rivaling Supervised Methods.</title>
<date>1995</date>
<marker>YAROWSKY, 1995</marker>
<rawString>YAROWSKY, D. (1995). Unsupervised Word Sense Disambiguation Rivaling Supervised Methods.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<date>1995</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the 33rd Annual Meeting of the Association for Computational Linguistics (ACL</booktitle>
<pages>189--196</pages>
<location>Cambridge, Massachusetts, USA.</location>
<marker>1995</marker>
<rawString>In Proceedings of the 33rd Annual Meeting of the Association for Computational Linguistics (ACL 1995), pp. 189-196. Cambridge, Massachusetts, USA.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Y ZHAO</author>
<author>G KARYPIS</author>
<author>U FAYYAD</author>
</authors>
<title>Hierarchical Clustering Algorithms for Document Datasets.</title>
<date>2005</date>
<journal>ln Data Miningand Knowledge Discoveiy,</journal>
<volume>10</volume>
<issue>2</issue>
<pages>141--168</pages>
<publisher>The</publisher>
<marker>ZHAO, KARYPIS, FAYYAD, 2005</marker>
<rawString>ZHAO, Y., KARYPIS, G., AND FAYYAD, U. (2005). Hierarchical Clustering Algorithms for Document Datasets. ln Data Miningand Knowledge Discoveiy, 10(2), pp. 141-168. The Netherlands.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Z ZHONG</author>
<author>H T NG</author>
</authors>
<title>It Makes Sense: A Wide-Coverage Word Sense Disambiguation System for Free Text</title>
<date>2010</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the 48th Annual Meeting of the Association for Computational Linguistics (A CL</booktitle>
<pages>78--83</pages>
<location>Uppsala,</location>
<marker>ZHONG, NG, 2010</marker>
<rawString>ZHONG, Z. AND NG, H.T. (2010). It Makes Sense: A Wide-Coverage Word Sense Disambiguation System for Free Text In Proceedings of the 48th Annual Meeting of the Association for Computational Linguistics (A CL 2010), pp. 78-83. Uppsala, Sweden.</rawString>
</citation>
</citationList>
</algorithm>
</algorithms>