<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<algorithms version="110505">
<algorithm name="ParsCit" version="110505">
<citationList>
<citation valid="false">
<authors>
<author>ACE</author>
</authors>
<title>The Automatic Content Extraction</title>
<date>2007</date>
<journal>CHEN W., ZHANG Y., &amp; ISAHARA</journal>
<booktitle>In : The 3th International Symposium on chinese spoken language processing, CHEN Keh-Jiann</booktitle>
<pages>15--21</pages>
<publisher>Academic Press,</publisher>
<location>San Diego.</location>
<contexts>
<context position="2387" citStr="ACE 2007" startWordPosition="325" endWordPosition="326">g, Information extraction, Syntactic parsing. 1 Introduction La reconnaissance d&apos;entités nommées (EN) joue un role crucial dans l&apos;extraction de connaissances, les systémes de question/réponse, la traduction et les résumés automatiques, ainsi que dans l&apos;indexation inter-lingue. Cette tache a pour objectif de déterminer les frontiéres d&apos;une entité nommée, et de lui attribuer un type. La déﬁnition d&apos;une « entité nommée » varie selon les systémes et l&apos;utilisation qui en est faite. La campagne d&apos;évaluation Automatic Content Extraction (ACE) en 2007 a étendu la déﬁnition traditionnelle des entités (ACE 2007) en ajoutant aux types habituels 231 © ATALA TALN-RECITAL 2013, 17-21 Iuin, Les Sables d’Olonne (personne, organisme, lieu, expressions numériques) les types véhicule et arme. Dans le programme Quaero (Rosset et al., 2011), la déﬁnition des entités nommées a également été étendue en prenant en compte de nouveaux types (tels que les civilisations et les fonctions), et des expressions ne contenant pas de nom propre. La déﬁnition des entités nommées que nous allons employer ici s&apos;approche de celles d&apos;ACE et de Quaero. Nous traitons donc les entités nommées de type : personne, organisme, lieu, exp</context>
</contexts>
<marker>ACE, 2007</marker>
<rawString>ACE 2007. The Automatic Content Extraction 2007 Evaluation Plan, Evaluation of the Detection and Recognition ofACE Entities, Value, Temporal Expressions, Relations, and Events CAO Wenjie, Zone Chengqing. Chinese person name identiﬁcation based on rules and statistics. In : The 3th International Symposium on chinese spoken language processing, CHEN Keh-Jiann and CHERT Chao-jan. Knowledge Extraction for Identiﬁcation of Chinese 242 © ATALA TALN-RECITAL 2013, 17-21 Iuin, Les Sables d’Olonne Organization Names. In: Second Chinese Language Processing Workshop, Association for Computational Linguistics, 2000, pages 15-21 CHEN W., ZHANG Y., &amp; ISAHARA H.. Chinese Named Entity Recognition with Conditional Random Fields. In: Proceedings of the Fifth SIGHAN Workshop on Chinese Language Processing, Association for Computational Linguistics, 2006, pages 118-121 DE LA ROBERTIE Pierre. Le nom propre en chinois. Essai de morphosyntaxe. In: CORELA — Numéros thématiques le traitement lexicographique des noms propres. Publié en ligne le 02 décembre 2005 EILENBERG Samuel. 1974 Automata, Languages, and Machines. Volume A. Academic Press, San Diego.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>F LIU</author>
<author>J ZHAO</author>
<author>B Lv</author>
<author>X B0</author>
<author>H YU</author>
</authors>
<title>Product Named Entity Recognition Based on Hierarchical Hidden Morkov Model. In</title>
<date>2005</date>
<journal>MAKHOUL J., KUBALA</journal>
<booktitle>Proceedings of the Forth SIGHAN Workshop on Chinese Language Processing,</booktitle>
<marker>LIU, ZHAO, Lv, B0, YU, 2005</marker>
<rawString>LIU, F., ZHAO, J., Lv, B., B0, X., &amp; YU, H. Product Named Entity Recognition Based on Hierarchical Hidden Morkov Model. In : Proceedings of the Forth SIGHAN Workshop on Chinese Language Processing, 2005 MAKHOUL J., KUBALA F., SCHWARTZ, R. et WEISCHEDEL R. (1999). Performance measures for information extraction. In Darpa broadcast news workshop.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="false">
<authors>
<author>MAo Xinnian</author>
<author>DoNG Yuan</author>
<author>HE Saike</author>
<author>WANG Haila</author>
<author>BAo Sencheng</author>
</authors>
<title>Chinese Word Segmentation and Named Entity Recognition Based on Conditional Random Fields.</title>
<date>2008</date>
<journal>[en chinois] SUN Zhell, WANG Hllilin,</journal>
<booktitle>In Sixth SIGHAN Workshop of Chinese Language Processing,</booktitle>
<volume>4</volume>
<pages>61--67</pages>
<marker>Xinnian, Yuan, Saike, Haila, Sencheng, 2008</marker>
<rawString>MAo Xinnian, DoNG Yuan, HE Saike, WANG Haila, BAo Sencheng. Chinese Word Segmentation and Named Entity Recognition Based on Conditional Random Fields. In Sixth SIGHAN Workshop of Chinese Language Processing, 2008 MCDONALD David D. Internal and External Evidence in the Identiﬁcation and Semantic Categorization of Proper Names. In Corpus Processing for Lexical Acquisition, 1993, pages 61-67 ROSSET Sophie, Grouin Cyril, Zweigenbaum Pierre. Entités nommées structurées : guide d &apos;annotation Quaero. Notes et Documents LIMSI N° : 2011-04, Septembre, 2011 Sproat, Richard. and Shih, Chilin. A statistic method for ﬁnding word boundaries in Chinese text. In: Computer Processing of Chinese &amp; Oriental Languages, 1990, Vol 4, Pages 336-351 sun &apos;I‘ieli, Lm Yanji, =FI 3E6_3‘ﬁH7l§El’\]lHir3&apos;i&apos;.5H&apos;.ll7§—&apos;5 IEISIE [The State of the art and difﬁculties in Automatic Chinese word segmentation]. In 1E,§\}§7K [Information Technology], 2009, Vol. 7 [en chinois] SUN Zhell, WANG Hllilin, 3‘? 4?: $ TZISWIR 5&apos;] HT 9?‘. 33 E [Overview on the advance of the research on named entity recognition]. In Ejﬂft. =F5&apos;l%?EH7K [New technology of library and information service], 2010, No.7, pages 42-47 [en chinois] Propre Names And Translation Service, Xinhua News Agency. Names of the world&apos;s peoples — A comprehensive dictionary of names in roman-chinese. Published by Chian Translation &amp; Publishing Corporation, 1993 WANG, L.-J.; L1, W.-C. &amp; CHANG, C.-H.. Recognizing Unregistered Names for Mandarin Word Identiﬁcation. In : Proceedings of 14th COLING, 1992, pages 1239-1243 WANG Longyue, L1 Shuoo, WoNG Derek F., CHAo Lidia, A Joint Chinese Named Entity Recognition and Disambiguation System. In The second CIPS-SIGHAN joint Conference on Chinese Language Processing, 2012</rawString>
</citation>
</citationList>
</algorithm>
</algorithms>