<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<algorithms version="110505">
<algorithm name="ParsCit" version="110505">
<citationList>
<citation valid="false">
<authors>
<author>Véronique MALAISÉ</author>
<author>Luit GAZENDAM</author>
<author>Hennie BRUGMAN</author>
</authors>
<title>Acknowledgements This research was partly supported by the NWO funded CATCH program, including the CHOICE project. We want to thank our colleagues, both at the University and at Sound and Vision for their daily help, support and our fruitful collaboration.</title>
<date>2006</date>
<journal>Références GAZENDAM L., MALAISÉ V., SCHREIBER G. &amp; BRUGMAN</journal>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of First International workshop on Semantic Web Annotations for Multimedia (SWAMM</booktitle>
<marker>MALAISÉ, GAZENDAM, BRUGMAN, 2006</marker>
<rawString>Véronique MALAISÉ, Luit GAZENDAM, Hennie BRUGMAN Acknowledgements This research was partly supported by the NWO funded CATCH program, including the CHOICE project. We want to thank our colleagues, both at the University and at Sound and Vision for their daily help, support and our fruitful collaboration. Références GAZENDAM L., MALAISÉ V., SCHREIBER G. &amp; BRUGMAN H. (2006). Deriving semantic annotations of an audiovisual program from contextual texts. In Proceedings of First International workshop on Semantic Web Annotations for Multimedia (SWAMM 2006).</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>N IDE</author>
<author>J VÉRONIS</author>
</authors>
<title>Introduction to the special issue on word sense disambiguation : The state of the art.</title>
<date>1998</date>
<journal>Computational Linguistics,</journal>
<volume>24</volume>
<issue>1</issue>
<pages>1--40</pages>
<marker>IDE, VÉRONIS, 1998</marker>
<rawString>IDE N. &amp; VÉRONIS J. (1998). Introduction to the special issue on word sense disambiguation : The state of the art. Computational Linguistics, 24(1), 1–40.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>ISO</author>
</authors>
<title>Documentation - guidelines for the establishment and development of monolingual thesauri. International Organization for Standardization,</title>
<date>1986</date>
<journal>ISO</journal>
<pages>2788--1986</pages>
<contexts>
<context position="2902" citStr="ISO, 1986" startWordPosition="416" endWordPosition="417">s these results along with perspectives for this experiment. Mots-clés : désambiguisation sémantique, algorithme de classement, annotation automatique. Keywords: word sense disambiguation, ranking algorithm, automatic annotation. 197 Véronique MALAISÉ, Luit GAZENDAM, Hennie BRUGMAN 1 Introduction Thesauri are controlled vocabularies, often used for indexing and retrieving documents from collections. The standard thesauri contain two types of elements, preferred and non preferred terms, related with a link called use/use for. This link is considered as (para-)synonymy in the ISO-2788 standard (ISO, 1986) and can thus be useful for (semi-) automatic indexing applications : it enables a program to index a document with a preferred term (which is the type of thesaurus based controlled annotation we are interested in) either if the document contains an occurrence of the preferred term or if it contains occurrences of the corresponding non preferred term. In reality, this use/use for relationship is often more complex, and can generate ambiguity problems when used “as is” in an automatic application. We present in this paper the solution that we have developed in our project for selecting the rele</context>
<context position="8778" citStr="ISO, 1986" startWordPosition="1354" endWordPosition="1355"> broader term, narrower term, related term. Terms from all facets of the GTAA may have related terms and use for relationships, but only Keywords and Genres can also have broader term/narrower term relations, organizing them into a set of hierarchies. Additionally, Keyword terms are thematically classified in 88 subcategories of 16 top Categories (Nature, Society,...). Although the data model that is used for the thesaurus allows links between terms across facets, no instances of these links currently exist. This experiment concerns only automatic indexing with terms from the Keyword facet. 2(ISO, 1986), section 3-Definitions. 3In general this relationship is encoded USE, but this acronym is the one used in the GTAA. 4(ISO, 1986), section 3-Definitions. 199 Véronique MALAISÉ, Luit GAZENDAM, Hennie BRUGMAN 3.3 Different semantics and non uniqueness of the Use relationship In the GTAA, there are 1377 US relationships, i.e. 1377 times a non preferred term is associated with a preferred term. Some of these non preferred terms are associated with multiple different preferred terms and some of the preferred term are associated with multiple non preferred terms. In the first case, the non preferred</context>
</contexts>
<marker>ISO, 1986</marker>
<rawString>ISO (1986). Documentation - guidelines for the establishment and development of monolingual thesauri. International Organization for Standardization, ISO 2788-1986 edition.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>D MAYNARD</author>
<author>V TABLAN</author>
<author>H CUNNINGHAM</author>
</authors>
<title>Ne recognition without training data on a language you don’t speak.</title>
<date>2003</date>
<booktitle>ACL Workshop on Multilingual and Mixed-language Named Entity Recognition : Combining Statistical and Symbolic Models.</booktitle>
<marker>MAYNARD, TABLAN, CUNNINGHAM, 2003</marker>
<rawString>MAYNARD D., TABLAN V. &amp; CUNNINGHAM H. (2003). Ne recognition without training data on a language you don’t speak. ACL Workshop on Multilingual and Mixed-language Named Entity Recognition : Combining Statistical and Symbolic Models.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>A MILES</author>
<author>D BRICKLEY</author>
</authors>
<title>Skos core guide. 2nd W3C Public Working Draft.</title>
<date>2005</date>
<marker>MILES, BRICKLEY, 2005</marker>
<rawString>MILES A. &amp; BRICKLEY D. (2005). Skos core guide. 2nd W3C Public Working Draft.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>M STEVENSON</author>
<author>Y WILKS</author>
</authors>
<title>The interaction of knowledge sources in word sense disambiguation.</title>
<date>2001</date>
<journal>Computational Linguistics,</journal>
<volume>27</volume>
<issue>3</issue>
<pages>321--349</pages>
<marker>STEVENSON, WILKS, 2001</marker>
<rawString>STEVENSON M. &amp; WILKS Y. (2001). The interaction of knowledge sources in word sense disambiguation. Computational Linguistics, 27(3), 321–349.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>M VAN ASSEM</author>
<author>V MALAISÉ</author>
<author>A MILES</author>
<author>G SCHREIBER</author>
</authors>
<title>A method to convert thesauri to skos.</title>
<date>2006</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the Third European Semantic Web Conference (ESWC’06).</booktitle>
<marker>VAN ASSEM, MALAISÉ, MILES, SCHREIBER, 2006</marker>
<rawString>VAN ASSEM M., MALAISÉ V., MILES A. &amp; SCHREIBER G. (2006). A method to convert thesauri to skos. In Proceedings of the Third European Semantic Web Conference (ESWC’06).</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>J VERONIS</author>
<author>N M IDE</author>
</authors>
<title>Word sense disambiguation with very large neural networks extracted from machine readable dictionaries.</title>
<date>1990</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the 13th conference on Computational linguistics,</booktitle>
<pages>389--394</pages>
<location>Morristown, NJ, USA</location>
<marker>VERONIS, IDE, 1990</marker>
<rawString>VERONIS J. &amp; IDE N. M. (1990). Word sense disambiguation with very large neural networks extracted from machine readable dictionaries. In Proceedings of the 13th conference on Computational linguistics, p. 389–394, Morristown, NJ, USA : Association for Computational Linguistics.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>D YAROWSKY</author>
</authors>
<title>Word-sense disambiguation using statistical models of roget’s categories trained on large corpora.</title>
<date>1992</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of 14th International Conference on Computational Linguistics (COLING-92).</booktitle>
<marker>YAROWSKY, 1992</marker>
<rawString>YAROWSKY D. (1992). Word-sense disambiguation using statistical models of roget’s categories trained on large corpora. In Proceedings of 14th International Conference on Computational Linguistics (COLING-92).</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>D YAROWSKY</author>
</authors>
<title>Unsupervised word sense disambiguation rivaling supervised methods.</title>
<date>1995</date>
<booktitle>In Meeting of the Association for Computational Linguistics (ACL’ 95).</booktitle>
<marker>YAROWSKY, 1995</marker>
<rawString>YAROWSKY D. (1995). Unsupervised word sense disambiguation rivaling supervised methods. In Meeting of the Association for Computational Linguistics (ACL’ 95).</rawString>
</citation>
</citationList>
</algorithm>
</algorithms>