<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<algorithms version="110505">
<algorithm name="ParsCit" version="110505">
<citationList>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>BEN HAMADOU A</author>
</authors>
<title>Vérification et correction automatique par analyse affixale des textes écrits en langue naturelle : le cas de l’arabe non voyellé. Thèse d’état en informatique, Faculté des Sciences de Tunis.</title>
<date>1993</date>
<marker>A, 1993</marker>
<rawString>BEN HAMADOU A. (1993). Vérification et correction automatique par analyse affixale des textes écrits en langue naturelle : le cas de l’arabe non voyellé. Thèse d’état en informatique, Faculté des Sciences de Tunis.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>BEN OTHMANE Z C</author>
</authors>
<title>De la synthèse lexicographique à la détection et la correction des graphie fautives arabes. Thèse de doctorat, Université de</title>
<date>1998</date>
<location>Paris XI, Orsay.</location>
<marker>C, 1998</marker>
<rawString>BEN OTHMANE Z. C. (1998). De la synthèse lexicographique à la détection et la correction des graphie fautives arabes. Thèse de doctorat, Université de Paris XI, Orsay.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>BEN OTHMANE Z C</author>
<author>BEN AHMED M</author>
</authors>
<title>Le contexte au service des graphies fautives arabes.</title>
<date>2003</date>
<tech>TALN’03, Batz-sur-Mer.</tech>
<marker>C, M, 2003</marker>
<rawString>BEN OTHMANE Z. C., BEN AHMED M. (2003). Le contexte au service des graphies fautives arabes. TALN’03, Batz-sur-Mer.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>BEN OTHMANE Z C</author>
<author>BEN FRAJ F</author>
<author>BEN AHMED M</author>
</authors>
<title>Un système multi-agent pour le traitement des erreurs cachées en langue arabe.</title>
<date>2005</date>
<booktitle>Actes de la 12ème Conférence sur le Traitement Automatique des langues naturelles TALN&apos;05, Dourdan,</booktitle>
<volume>1</volume>
<pages>143--153</pages>
<marker>C, F, M, 2005</marker>
<rawString>BEN OTHMANE Z. C., BEN FRAJ F., BEN AHMED M. (2005). Un système multi-agent pour le traitement des erreurs cachées en langue arabe. Actes de la 12ème Conférence sur le Traitement Automatique des langues naturelles TALN&apos;05, Dourdan, vol. 1, p. 143-153.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>J BIGERT</author>
<author>O KNUTSSON</author>
</authors>
<title>Robust Error Detection : A Hybrid Approach Combining Unsupervised Error Detection and Linguistic Knowledge.</title>
<date>2002</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of Robust Methods in Analysis of Natural Language Data (ROMAND’02),</booktitle>
<location>Frascati, Italie.</location>
<marker>BIGERT, KNUTSSON, 2002</marker>
<rawString>BIGERT J., KNUTSSON O. (2002). Robust Error Detection : A Hybrid Approach Combining Unsupervised Error Detection and Linguistic Knowledge. In Proceedings of Robust Methods in Analysis of Natural Language Data (ROMAND’02), Frascati, Italie.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>A GOLDING</author>
</authors>
<title>A Bayesian hybrid method for context-sensitive spelling correction.</title>
<date>1995</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the third Workshop On Very Large Corpora,</booktitle>
<pages>39--53</pages>
<location>Cambridge, Massachuses, USA,</location>
<marker>GOLDING, 1995</marker>
<rawString>GOLDING A. (1995). A Bayesian hybrid method for context-sensitive spelling correction. In Proceedings of the third Workshop On Very Large Corpora, Cambridge, Massachuses, USA, (1995), 39-53.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>A GOLDING</author>
<author>Y SCHABES</author>
</authors>
<title>Combining trigram based and feature based methods for context sensitive spelling correction.</title>
<date>1996</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the 34th Annual Meeting of the Association for Computational Linguistics,</booktitle>
<pages>71--78</pages>
<location>Santa Cruz,</location>
<marker>GOLDING, SCHABES, 1996</marker>
<rawString>GOLDING A., SCHABES Y. (1996). Combining trigram based and feature based methods for context sensitive spelling correction. In Proceedings of the 34th Annual Meeting of the Association for Computational Linguistics, Santa Cruz, 71-78.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>A GOLDING</author>
<author>D ROTH</author>
</authors>
<title>A winnow-based approach to context-sensitive spelling correction.</title>
<date>1999</date>
<booktitle>Machine Learning,</booktitle>
<volume>34</volume>
<issue>1</issue>
<pages>107--130</pages>
<marker>GOLDING, ROTH, 1999</marker>
<rawString>GOLDING A., ROTH D. (1999). A winnow-based approach to context-sensitive spelling correction. Machine Learning, 34(1-3), 107-130.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>T K LANDAUER</author>
<author>P W Foltz</author>
<author>D Laham</author>
</authors>
<title>An introduction to Latent Semantic Analysis.</title>
<date>1998</date>
<booktitle>Discourse Processes,</booktitle>
<volume>25</volume>
<pages>259--284</pages>
<marker>LANDAUER, Foltz, Laham, 1998</marker>
<rawString>LANDAUER T.K., Foltz P.W., Laham D. (1998). An introduction to Latent Semantic Analysis. Discourse Processes, Vol. 25, 259-284.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>I MLAYEH</author>
</authors>
<title>Extraction de collocations à partir de corpus textuels en langue arabe.</title>
<date>2004</date>
<booktitle>Mémoire de mastère, Ecole nationale des sciences informatiques, Université de la Manouba.</booktitle>
<marker>MLAYEH, 2004</marker>
<rawString>MLAYEH I. (2004). Extraction de collocations à partir de corpus textuels en langue arabe. Mémoire de mastère, Ecole nationale des sciences informatiques, Université de la Manouba.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>S VERBERNE</author>
</authors>
<title>Context sensitive spell checking based on word trigram probabilities. Master thesis Taal, Spraak &amp; Informatica,</title>
<date>2002</date>
<institution>University of Nijmegen.</institution>
<marker>VERBERNE, 2002</marker>
<rawString>VERBERNE S. (2002). Context sensitive spell checking based on word trigram probabilities. Master thesis Taal, Spraak &amp; Informatica, University of Nijmegen.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>W XIAOLONG</author>
<author>L JIANHUA</author>
</authors>
<title>Combine trigram and automatic weight distribution in Chinese spelling error correction.</title>
<date>2001</date>
<journal>Journal of computer Science and Technology, Volume</journal>
<volume>17</volume>
<location>Province,</location>
<marker>XIAOLONG, JIANHUA, 2001</marker>
<rawString>XIAOLONG W., JIANHUA L. (2001). Combine trigram and automatic weight distribution in Chinese spelling error correction. Journal of computer Science and Technology, Volume 17 Issue 6, Province, China.</rawString>
</citation>
</citationList>
</algorithm>
</algorithms>