<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<algorithms version="110505">
<algorithm name="ParsCit" version="110505">
<citationList>
<citation valid="false">
<title>Remerciements Recherche financée par ARCUS (Région Rhône-Alpes, Ministère des Affaires Etrangères français). Merci à tous les contributeurs</title>
<date>2007</date>
<journal>Références BEKIOS J., BOGUSLAVSKY I., CARDEÑOSA J., GALLARDO C.</journal>
<booktitle>Automatic Construction of an Interlingual Dictionary for Multilingual Lexicography. Proceedings, International Conf. on Machine Learning: Models, Technologies &amp; Applications (MLMTA&apos;07),</booktitle>
<pages>215--220</pages>
<location>(Grenoble, Bombay, Pondichéry).</location>
<marker>2007</marker>
<rawString>Remerciements Recherche financée par ARCUS (Région Rhône-Alpes, Ministère des Affaires Etrangères français). Merci à tous les contributeurs (Grenoble, Bombay, Pondichéry). Références BEKIOS J., BOGUSLAVSKY I., CARDEÑOSA J., GALLARDO C. (2007). Automatic Construction of an Interlingual Dictionary for Multilingual Lexicography. Proceedings, International Conf. on Machine Learning: Models, Technologies &amp; Applications (MLMTA&apos;07), 215-220.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>C BOITET</author>
<author>P BHATTACHARYYA</author>
<author>E BLANC</author>
<author>S MEENA</author>
<author>S BOUDHH</author>
<author>G FAFIOTTE</author>
<author>A FALAISE</author>
<author>V VACHANI</author>
</authors>
<title>Building Hindi-French-English-UNL resources for SurviTra-CIFLI, linguistic survival system under construction.</title>
<date>2007</date>
<tech>SNLP ’07, Thaïlande.</tech>
<marker>BOITET, BHATTACHARYYA, BLANC, MEENA, BOUDHH, FAFIOTTE, FALAISE, VACHANI, 2007</marker>
<rawString>BOITET C., BHATTACHARYYA P., BLANC E., MEENA S., BOUDHH S., FAFIOTTE G., FALAISE A., VACHANI V. (2007). Building Hindi-French-English-UNL resources for SurviTra-CIFLI, linguistic survival system under construction. SNLP ’07, Thaïlande.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>S SINGH</author>
<author>M DALAL</author>
<author>V VACHANI</author>
<author>P BHATTACHARYYA</author>
<author>O DAMANI</author>
</authors>
<date>2007</date>
<booktitle>Hindi Generation from Interlingua. Actes de Machine Translation Summit. Copenhague,</booktitle>
<pages>421--428</pages>
<marker>SINGH, DALAL, VACHANI, BHATTACHARYYA, DAMANI, 2007</marker>
<rawString>SINGH S., DALAL M., VACHANI V., BHATTACHARYYA P., DAMANI O. (2007). Hindi Generation from Interlingua. Actes de Machine Translation Summit. Copenhague, 421-428.</rawString>
</citation>
</citationList>
</algorithm>
</algorithms>