<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<algorithms version="110505">
<algorithm name="ParsCit" version="110505">
<citationList>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>R Bertrand</author>
<author>G Ferré</author>
<author>P Blache</author>
<author>R Espesser</author>
<author>S Rauzy</author>
</authors>
<title>Backchannels revisited from a multimodal perspective»,</title>
<date>2007</date>
<booktitle>Proceedings of Auditory-visual Speech Processing</booktitle>
<location>Hilvarenbeek, The Netherlands.</location>
<marker>Bertrand, Ferré, Blache, Espesser, Rauzy, 2007</marker>
<rawString>Bertrand R., Ferré G., Blache P., Espesser R. &amp; Rauzy S. (2007) «Backchannels revisited from a multimodal perspective», Proceedings of Auditory-visual Speech Processing Hilvarenbeek, The Netherlands.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="false">
<authors>
<author>P Blache</author>
<author>R Espesser</author>
<author>G Ferré</author>
<author>C Meunier</author>
<author>B Priego-Valverde</author>
<author>S Rauzy</author>
</authors>
<title>Le Cid - Corpus of Interactional Data - Annotation et Exploitation Multimodale de Parole Conversationnelle,</title>
<date>2009</date>
<journal>TRANEL,</journal>
<booktitle>in revue TAL 49:3</booktitle>
<volume>47</volume>
<location>Hermès.</location>
<marker>Blache, Espesser, Ferré, Meunier, Priego-Valverde, Rauzy, 2009</marker>
<rawString>Bertrand R. , P. Blache, R. Espesser, G. Ferré, C. Meunier, B. Priego-Valverde, S. Rauzy (2009) Le Cid - Corpus of Interactional Data - Annotation et Exploitation Multimodale de Parole Conversationnelle, in revue TAL 49:3 Bertrand R., Portes C. &amp; Sabio F. (2007) «Distribution syntaxique, discursive et interactionnelle des contours intonatifs du français dans un corpus de conversation», TRANEL, 47, 2007 Bird S., Day D., Garofolo J., Henderson J., Laprun C. &amp; Liberman M. (2000) «ATLAS : A Flexible and Extensible Architecture for Linguistic Annotation», Proceedings of the Second International Conference on Language Resources and Evaluation Blache P. (2001) Les Grammaires de Propriétés : Des contraintes pour le traitement automatique des langues naturelles, Hermès.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Blache P A Di Cristo</author>
</authors>
<date>2002</date>
<booktitle>Variabilité et dépendances des composants linguistiques », in Actes de TALN’02.</booktitle>
<marker>Di Cristo, 2002</marker>
<rawString>Blache P. A. Di Cristo (2002), « Variabilité et dépendances des composants linguistiques », in Actes de TALN’02.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="false">
<authors>
<author>P Blache</author>
<author>S Rauzy</author>
</authors>
<title>Influence de la qualité de l&apos;étiquetage sur le chunking : une corrélation dépendant de la taille des chunks», Actes de TALN08 Carletta</title>
<date>2008</date>
<journal>Announcing the AMI Meeting Corpus. The ELRA Newsletter</journal>
<booktitle>The AMI Meetings Corpus», Proceedings of the Measuring Behavior</booktitle>
<volume>11</volume>
<issue>1</issue>
<location>Carletta, J.</location>
<note>de la Clergerie</note>
<marker>Blache, Rauzy, 2008</marker>
<rawString>Blache P. &amp; Rauzy S. (2008) «Influence de la qualité de l&apos;étiquetage sur le chunking : une corrélation dépendant de la taille des chunks», Actes de TALN08 Carletta J. et al. (2005) «The AMI Meetings Corpus», Proceedings of the Measuring Behavior 2005 symposium on Annotating and measuring Meeting Behavior, Carletta, J. (2006) Announcing the AMI Meeting Corpus. The ELRA Newsletter 11(1) de la Clergerie E., Ayache C., de Chalandar G., Francopoulo G., Gardent C. &amp; Paroubek P. (2008) «Large Scale Production of Syntactic Annotations for French», Proceedings of the International Workshop on Automated Syntactic Annotations for Interoperable Language Ressources.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>E et B Post Delais-Roussarie</author>
</authors>
<title>Unités prosodiques et grammaire de l&apos;intonation : vers une nouvelle approche », in actes des XXVIIème Journées d&apos;Études sur la Parole Doetjes</title>
<date>2008</date>
<booktitle>The Prosody of Left Detached Constituent in French”, in proceedings of Speech Prosody</booktitle>
<marker>Delais-Roussarie, 2008</marker>
<rawString>Delais-Roussarie, E et B. Post (2008) « Unités prosodiques et grammaire de l&apos;intonation : vers une nouvelle approche », in actes des XXVIIème Journées d&apos;Études sur la Parole Doetjes J., E. Delais-Roussarie &amp; P. Sleeman (2002) “The Prosody of Left Detached Constituent in French”, in proceedings of Speech Prosody 2002.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>V Gendner</author>
<author>G Illouz</author>
<author>M Jardino</author>
<author>L Monceaux</author>
<author>P Paroubek</author>
<author>I Robba</author>
<author>A Vilnat</author>
</authors>
<title>PEAS, the first instantiation of a comparative framework for evaluating parsers of French»,</title>
<date>2003</date>
<journal>Research Notes of EACL</journal>
<publisher>Cambridge University Press,</publisher>
<marker>Gendner, Illouz, Jardino, Monceaux, Paroubek, Robba, Vilnat, 2003</marker>
<rawString>Gendner V., Illouz G., Jardino M., Monceaux L., Paroubek P., Robba I. &amp; Vilnat A. (2003) «PEAS, the first instantiation of a comparative framework for evaluating parsers of French», Research Notes of EACL 2003 Hirst D. &amp; Di Cristo A., Intonation Systems, Cambridge University Press, 1998.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="false">
<authors>
<author>S-A Jun</author>
<author>C Fougeron</author>
</authors>
<title>Realizations of accentual phrase in French intonation»,</title>
<date>2002</date>
<journal>Probus</journal>
<booktitle>Data Annotations and Measures in EASY the Evaluation Campaign for Parsers in French», Proceedings of the 5th International Conference on Language Resources and Evaluation</booktitle>
<volume>14</volume>
<marker>Jun, Fougeron, 2002</marker>
<rawString>Jun S.-A. &amp; Fougeron C. (2002) «Realizations of accentual phrase in French intonation», Probus 14 Kipp M. (2006) Anvil 4.0. Annotation of Video and Spoken Language. (http://www.dfki.de/~kipp/anvil) McNeill D. (2005) Gesture and Thought. University of Chicago Press MUMIN : A Nordic Network for MUltiModal Interfaces (http://www.cst.dk/mumin/) NITE : Natural Interactivity Tools Engineering (http://nite.nis.sdu.dk/) Paroubek P., Robba I., Vilnat A. &amp; Ayache C. (2006) «Data Annotations and Measures in EASY the Evaluation Campaign for Parsers in French», Proceedings of the 5th International Conference on Language Resources and Evaluation Portes C., Bertrand R. &amp; Espesser R. (2007) «Contribution to a grammar of intonation in French.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Form</author>
</authors>
<title>function of three rising patterns», Nouveaux Cahiers de Linguistique Française,</title>
<date></date>
<marker>Form, </marker>
<rawString>Form and function of three rising patterns», Nouveaux Cahiers de Linguistique Française, 28 Rauzy S. &amp; Blache P. (2007) «Un lexique syntaxique des verbes du français : VfrLPL», Rapport de recherche RAU-3055, Laboratoire Parole et Langage.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>E Selkirk</author>
</authors>
<title>Phonology and Syntax: the Relation between Sound and Structure,</title>
<date>1984</date>
<publisher>MIT Press.</publisher>
<marker>Selkirk, 1984</marker>
<rawString>Selkirk E. (1984) Phonology and Syntax: the Relation between Sound and Structure, MIT Press.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>VERBMOBIL Alexandersson J</author>
<author>B Buschbeck-Wolf</author>
<author>T Fujinami</author>
<author>M Kipp</author>
<author>S Koch</author>
<author>E Maier</author>
<author>N Reithinger</author>
<author>B Schmitz</author>
<author>M Siegel</author>
</authors>
<date>1998</date>
<booktitle>Dialogue Acts in VERBMOBIL-2 - Second Edition. Rapport interne,</booktitle>
<publisher>DFKI GmbH.</publisher>
<marker>J, Buschbeck-Wolf, Fujinami, Kipp, Koch, Maier, Reithinger, Schmitz, Siegel, 1998</marker>
<rawString>VERBMOBIL : Alexandersson J., Buschbeck-Wolf B., Fujinami T., Kipp M., Koch S., Maier E., Reithinger N., Schmitz B. &amp; Siegel M. Dialogue Acts in VERBMOBIL-2 - Second Edition. Rapport interne, 1998, DFKI GmbH.</rawString>
</citation>
</citationList>
</algorithm>
</algorithms>