<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<algorithms version="110505">
<algorithm name="ParsCit" version="110505">
<citationList>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>les CapDigital</author>
</authors>
<title>partenaires du projet :Vecsys, LIMSI, Sinéqua et Témis. Références CAILLIAU F., POUDAT C.,</title>
<date>2008</date>
<location>JADT</location>
<marker>CapDigital, 2008</marker>
<rawString>CapDigital, les partenaires du projet :Vecsys, LIMSI, Sinéqua et Témis. Références CAILLIAU F., POUDAT C., (2008) Caractérisation lexicale des contributions clients agents dans un corpus de conversations téléphoniques retranscrites, JADT 2008.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>F Y Y CHOI</author>
</authors>
<title>Advances in domain independent linear text segmentation.</title>
<date>2000</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the 1st Meeting of the North American Chapter of the Association for Computational Linguistics,</booktitle>
<location>USA.</location>
<marker>CHOI, 2000</marker>
<rawString>CHOI F. Y. Y. (2000). Advances in domain independent linear text segmentation. In Proceedings of the 1st Meeting of the North American Chapter of the Association for Computational Linguistics, USA.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>S FERNANDEZ</author>
<author>E SANJUAN</author>
<author>J-M TORRES-MORENO</author>
</authors>
<title>Enertex: un système basé sur l&apos;énergie textuelle. Actes de Traitement Automatique de la Langue Naturelle,</title>
<date>2008</date>
<location>TALN</location>
<marker>FERNANDEZ, SANJUAN, TORRES-MORENO, 2008</marker>
<rawString>FERNANDEZ S., SANJUAN E., TORRES-MORENO J-M. (2008). Enertex: un système basé sur l&apos;énergie textuelle. Actes de Traitement Automatique de la Langue Naturelle, TALN 2008.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>M GARNIER-RIZET</author>
<author>G ADDA</author>
<author>F CAILLIAU</author>
<author>J L GAUVAIN</author>
<author>S GUILLEMIN-LANNE</author>
<author>L LAMEL</author>
<author>S VANNI</author>
<author>C WAAST-RICHARD</author>
</authors>
<title>CallSurf - Automatic transcription, indexing and structuration of call center conversational speech for knowledge extraction and query by content,</title>
<date>2008</date>
<location>LREC</location>
<marker>GARNIER-RIZET, ADDA, CAILLIAU, GAUVAIN, GUILLEMIN-LANNE, LAMEL, VANNI, WAAST-RICHARD, 2008</marker>
<rawString>GARNIER-RIZET M., ADDA G., CAILLIAU F., GAUVAIN J. L., GUILLEMIN-LANNE S., LAMEL L., VANNI S., WAAST-RICHARD C. (2008). CallSurf - Automatic transcription, indexing and structuration of call center conversational speech for knowledge extraction and query by content, LREC 2008.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>M A HEARST</author>
</authors>
<title>Text-tiling : segmenting text into multi-paragraph subtopic passages. Computational Linguistics,</title>
<date>1997</date>
<pages>59--66</pages>
<marker>HEARST, 1997</marker>
<rawString>HEARST M. A. (1997). Text-tiling : segmenting text into multi-paragraph subtopic passages. Computational Linguistics, p. 59–66.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>A LABADIÉ</author>
<author>V PRINCE</author>
</authors>
<title>Comparaison de méthodes lexicales et syntaxico-sémantiques dans la segmentation thématique de texte non supervisée. Actes de Traitement Automatique de la Langue Naturelle,</title>
<date>2008</date>
<location>TALN</location>
<marker>LABADIÉ, PRINCE, 2008</marker>
<rawString>LABADIÉ A., PRINCE V. (2008). Comparaison de méthodes lexicales et syntaxico-sémantiques dans la segmentation thématique de texte non supervisée. Actes de Traitement Automatique de la Langue Naturelle, TALN 2008.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>S LAMPRIER</author>
<author>T AMGHAR</author>
<author>B LEVRAT</author>
<author>F SAUBION</author>
</authors>
<title>SegGen: A Genetic Algorithm for Linear Text Segmentation. Actes de IJCAI.</title>
<date>2007</date>
<marker>LAMPRIER, AMGHAR, LEVRAT, SAUBION, 2007</marker>
<rawString>LAMPRIER S., AMGHAR T., LEVRAT B., SAUBION F. (2007) SegGen: A Genetic Algorithm for Linear Text Segmentation. Actes de IJCAI.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>L PEVZNER</author>
<author>M A HEARST</author>
</authors>
<title>A critique and improvement of an evaluation metric for text segmentation. Computational Linguistics,</title>
<date>2002</date>
<pages>p.</pages>
<marker>PEVZNER, HEARST, 2002</marker>
<rawString>PEVZNER L. &amp; HEARST M. A. (2002). A critique and improvement of an evaluation metric for text segmentation. Computational Linguistics, p. 19–36.</rawString>
</citation>
</citationList>
</algorithm>
</algorithms>