<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<algorithms version="110505">
<algorithm name="ParsCit" version="110505">
<citationList>
<citation valid="true">
<title>l’utilisation de représentations de bas niveau et de techniques efficaces de résolution de contraintes. Laura Kallmeyer, Wolfgang Maier et Yannick Parmentier Références</title>
<date>2001</date>
<journal>BARTHÉLEMY F., BOULLIER P., DESCHAMP P. &amp; DE LA CLERGERIE É.</journal>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the 39th Annual Meeting on Association for Computational Linguistics,</booktitle>
<pages>42--49</pages>
<contexts>
<context position="3050" citStr="(2001)" startWordPosition="423" endWordPosition="423">comme par exemple la permutation d’arguments dans le « brouillage » (scrambling) des langues dites à ordre des mots libres (Becker et al., 1992), ou encore les constructions non Laura Kallmeyer, Wolfgang Maier et Yannick Parmentier semi-linéaires telles que l’empilement de cas en géorgien ancien (Michaelis &amp; Kracht, 1996), et les nombres chinois (Radzinski, 1991), phénomènes que les RCGs peuvent traiter (Boullier, 1999). Aussi, des algorithmes d’analyse pour RCG ont été présentés par (i) Boullier (2000), qui définit un algorithme d’analyse descendante directionnelle, et (ii) Barthélemy et al. (2001), qui ajoutent un oracle à l’algorithme de Boullier afin de limiter l’espace de recherche. La classe des RCGs simples a reçu une plus grande attention, comme en témoignent les travaux sur l’analyse à base d’automates de De La Clergerie (2002), ceux sur l’analyse déductive de LCFRS de Burden et Ljunglöf (2005), ou encore l’approche de Kanazawa (2008) pour l’analyse de MCFG au moyen de Datalog. Dans cet article, nous ne prétendons pas motiver l’utilisation des RCGs (pour cela, se référer aux articles sus-cités), mais cherchons plutôt à combler un manque dans la littérature sur les algorithmes d’</context>
</contexts>
<marker>2001</marker>
<rawString>l’utilisation de représentations de bas niveau et de techniques efficaces de résolution de contraintes. Laura Kallmeyer, Wolfgang Maier et Yannick Parmentier Références BARTHÉLEMY F., BOULLIER P., DESCHAMP P. &amp; DE LA CLERGERIE É. (2001). Guided parsing of Range Concatenation Languages. In Proceedings of the 39th Annual Meeting on Association for Computational Linguistics, p. 42–49.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>T BECKER</author>
<author>O RAMBOW</author>
<author>M NIV</author>
</authors>
<title>The Derivationel Generative Power of Formal Systems or Scrambling is Beyond LCFRS.</title>
<date>1992</date>
<tech>Technical Report IRCS-92-38,</tech>
<institution>Institute for Research in Cognitive Science, University of Pennsylvania.</institution>
<marker>BECKER, RAMBOW, NIV, 1992</marker>
<rawString>BECKER T., RAMBOW O. &amp; NIV M. (1992). The Derivationel Generative Power of Formal Systems or Scrambling is Beyond LCFRS. Technical Report IRCS-92-38, Institute for Research in Cognitive Science, University of Pennsylvania.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>E BERTSCH</author>
<author>M-J NEDERHOF</author>
</authors>
<title>On the complexity of some extensions of RCG parsing.</title>
<date>2001</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the Seventh International Workshop on Parsing Technologies,</booktitle>
<pages>66--77</pages>
<location>Beijing, China.</location>
<marker>BERTSCH, NEDERHOF, 2001</marker>
<rawString>BERTSCH E. &amp; NEDERHOF M.-J. (2001). On the complexity of some extensions of RCG parsing. In Proceedings of the Seventh International Workshop on Parsing Technologies, p. 66–77, Beijing, China.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>P BOULLIER</author>
</authors>
<title>Proposal for a Natural Language Processing Syntactic Backbone.</title>
<date>1998</date>
<booktitle>Rapport de Recherche RR-3342, Institut National de Recherche en Informatique et en Automatique,</booktitle>
<location>Le Chesnay, France.</location>
<marker>BOULLIER, 1998</marker>
<rawString>BOULLIER P. (1998). Proposal for a Natural Language Processing Syntactic Backbone. Rapport de Recherche RR-3342, Institut National de Recherche en Informatique et en Automatique, Le Chesnay, France.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>P BOULLIER</author>
</authors>
<title>Chinese numbers, mix, scrambling, and range concatenation grammars.</title>
<date>1999</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the 9th Conference of the European Chapter of the Association for Computational Linguistics (EACL’99),</booktitle>
<pages>53--60</pages>
<location>Bergen, Norway.</location>
<marker>BOULLIER, 1999</marker>
<rawString>BOULLIER P. (1999). Chinese numbers, mix, scrambling, and range concatenation grammars. In Proceedings of the 9th Conference of the European Chapter of the Association for Computational Linguistics (EACL’99), p. 53–60, Bergen, Norway.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>P BOULLIER</author>
</authors>
<title>Range concatenation grammars.</title>
<date>2000</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the Sixth International Workshop on Parsing Technologies (IWPT</booktitle>
<pages>53--64</pages>
<location>Trento, Italy.</location>
<marker>BOULLIER, 2000</marker>
<rawString>BOULLIER P. (2000). Range concatenation grammars. In Proceedings of the Sixth International Workshop on Parsing Technologies (IWPT 2000), p. 53–64, Trento, Italy.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>H BURDEN</author>
<author>P LJUNGLÖF</author>
</authors>
<title>Parsing linear context-free rewriting systems.</title>
<date>2005</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the Ninth International Workshop on Parsing Technology,</booktitle>
<pages>11--17</pages>
<location>Vancouver, British Columbia.</location>
<marker>BURDEN, LJUNGLÖF, 2005</marker>
<rawString>BURDEN H. &amp; LJUNGLÖF P. (2005). Parsing linear context-free rewriting systems. In Proceedings of the Ninth International Workshop on Parsing Technology, p. 11–17, Vancouver, British Columbia.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>M KANAZAWA</author>
</authors>
<title>A prefix-correct earley recognizer for multiple context-free grammars.</title>
<date>2008</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the Ninth International Workshop on Tree Adjoining Grammars and Related Formalisms (TAG+9),</booktitle>
<pages>49--56</pages>
<location>Tübingen, Germany.</location>
<marker>KANAZAWA, 2008</marker>
<rawString>KANAZAWA M. (2008). A prefix-correct earley recognizer for multiple context-free grammars. In Proceedings of the Ninth International Workshop on Tree Adjoining Grammars and Related Formalisms (TAG+9), p. 49–56, Tübingen, Germany.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>W MAIER</author>
<author>A SØGAARD</author>
</authors>
<title>Treebanks and mild context-sensitivity.</title>
<date>2008</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the 13th Conference on Formal Grammar</booktitle>
<location>Hamburg, Germany.</location>
<marker>MAIER, SØGAARD, 2008</marker>
<rawString>MAIER W. &amp; SØGAARD A. (2008). Treebanks and mild context-sensitivity. In Proceedings of the 13th Conference on Formal Grammar 2008, Hamburg, Germany.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>J MICHAELIS</author>
<author>M KRACHT</author>
</authors>
<title>Semilinearity as a Syntactic Invariant.</title>
<date>1996</date>
<booktitle>In Logical Aspects of Computational Linguistics,</booktitle>
<location>Nancy.</location>
<marker>MICHAELIS, KRACHT, 1996</marker>
<rawString>MICHAELIS J. &amp; KRACHT M. (1996). Semilinearity as a Syntactic Invariant. In Logical Aspects of Computational Linguistics, Nancy.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>D RADZINSKI</author>
</authors>
<title>Chinese number-names, tree adjoining languages, and mild contextsensitivity.</title>
<date>1991</date>
<journal>Computational Linguistics,</journal>
<volume>17</volume>
<pages>277--299</pages>
<marker>RADZINSKI, 1991</marker>
<rawString>RADZINSKI D. (1991). Chinese number-names, tree adjoining languages, and mild contextsensitivity. Computational Linguistics, 17, 277–299.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>B SAGOT</author>
</authors>
<title>Linguistic facts as predicates over ranges of the sentence.</title>
<date>2005</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of LACL 05, number 3492 in Lecture Notes in Computer Science,</booktitle>
<pages>271--286</pages>
<location>Bordeaux, France.</location>
<marker>SAGOT, 2005</marker>
<rawString>SAGOT B. (2005). Linguistic facts as predicates over ranges of the sentence. In Proceedings of LACL 05, number 3492 in Lecture Notes in Computer Science, p. 271–286, Bordeaux, France.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>H SEKI</author>
<author>T MATSUMURA</author>
<author>M FUJII</author>
<author>T KASAMI</author>
</authors>
<title>On multiple context-free grammars.</title>
<date>1991</date>
<journal>Theoretical Computer Science,</journal>
<volume>88</volume>
<pages>191--229</pages>
<marker>SEKI, MATSUMURA, FUJII, KASAMI, 1991</marker>
<rawString>SEKI H., MATSUMURA T., FUJII M. &amp; KASAMI T. (1991). On multiple context-free grammars. Theoretical Computer Science, 88, 191–229.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>S M SHIEBER</author>
<author>Y SCHABES</author>
<author>F C N PEREIRA</author>
</authors>
<title>Principles and implementation of deductive parsing.</title>
<date>1995</date>
<journal>Journal of Logic Programming,</journal>
<volume>24</volume>
<issue>1</issue>
<pages>3--36</pages>
<marker>SHIEBER, SCHABES, PEREIRA, 1995</marker>
<rawString>SHIEBER S. M., SCHABES Y. &amp; PEREIRA F. C. N. (1995). Principles and implementation of deductive parsing. Journal of Logic Programming, 24(1&amp; 2), 3–36.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>A SØGAARD</author>
</authors>
<title>Range concatenation grammars for translation.</title>
<date>2008</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the 22nd International Conference on Computational Linguistics,</booktitle>
<location>Manchester, England.</location>
<marker>SØGAARD, 2008</marker>
<rawString>SØGAARD A. (2008). Range concatenation grammars for translation. In Proceedings of the 22nd International Conference on Computational Linguistics, Manchester, England.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>VILLEMONTE DE LA CLERGERIE E</author>
</authors>
<title>Parsing mildly context-sensitive languages with thread automata.</title>
<date>2002</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the 19th International Conference on Computational Linguistics, p. 1–7,</booktitle>
<location>Taipei, Taiwan.</location>
<marker>E, 2002</marker>
<rawString>VILLEMONTE DE LA CLERGERIE E. (2002). Parsing mildly context-sensitive languages with thread automata. In Proceedings of the 19th International Conference on Computational Linguistics, p. 1–7, Taipei, Taiwan.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>D J WEIR</author>
</authors>
<title>Characterizing mildly context-sensitive grammar formalisms.</title>
<date>1988</date>
<tech>PhD thesis,</tech>
<institution>University of Pennsylvania,</institution>
<location>Philadelphia, PA.</location>
<marker>WEIR, 1988</marker>
<rawString>WEIR D. J. (1988). Characterizing mildly context-sensitive grammar formalisms. PhD thesis, University of Pennsylvania, Philadelphia, PA.</rawString>
</citation>
</citationList>
</algorithm>
</algorithms>