<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<algorithms version="110505">
<algorithm name="ParsCit" version="110505">
<citationList>
<citation valid="false">
<title>Pour cette démonstration, nous aurions besoin à minima d’une table. Pour un meilleur rendu, nous apprécierons un vidéoprojecteur et son écran (ou bien un grand écran de PC), éventuellement une connexion Internet (cablée ou par wifi) et un support à poster.</title>
<date>2003</date>
<booktitle>Références DAILLE B.</booktitle>
<pages>9--16</pages>
<editor>In F. Bond, A. Korhonen, D. MacCarthy and A. Villacicencio (eds.),</editor>
<marker>2003</marker>
<rawString>Pour cette démonstration, nous aurions besoin à minima d’une table. Pour un meilleur rendu, nous apprécierons un vidéoprojecteur et son écran (ou bien un grand écran de PC), éventuellement une connexion Internet (cablée ou par wifi) et un support à poster. Références DAILLE B. (2003). Conceptual structuring through term variations. In F. Bond, A. Korhonen, D. MacCarthy and A. Villacicencio (eds.), Proceedings ACL 2003 Workshop on Multiword Expressions : Analysis, Acquisition and Treatment, p. 9–16.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>D FERRUCCI</author>
<author>A LALLY</author>
</authors>
<title>Uima : an architectural approach to unstructured information processing in the corporate research environment.</title>
<date>2004</date>
<journal>Natural Language Engineering,</journal>
<volume>10</volume>
<issue>3</issue>
<pages>327--348</pages>
<marker>FERRUCCI, LALLY, 2004</marker>
<rawString>FERRUCCI D. &amp; LALLY A. (2004). Uima : an architectural approach to unstructured information processing in the corporate research environment. Natural Language Engineering, 10(3-4), 327–348.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>N FOUROUR</author>
</authors>
<title>Nemesis, un système de reconnaissance incrémentielle des entités nommées pour le français.</title>
<date>2002</date>
<booktitle>In Actes de TALN,</booktitle>
<pages>265--274</pages>
<location>Nancy.</location>
<marker>FOUROUR, 2002</marker>
<rawString>FOUROUR N. (2002). Nemesis, un système de reconnaissance incrémentielle des entités nommées pour le français. In Actes de TALN, p. 265–274, Nancy.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="false">
<authors>
<author>U HAHN</author>
<author>E BUYKO</author>
<author>K TOMANEK</author>
<author>S PIAO</author>
<author>J MCNAUGHT</author>
<author>Y TSURUOKA</author>
<author>S ANANIADOU</author>
</authors>
<title>An annotation type system for a data-driven nlp pipeline.</title>
<date>2007</date>
<journal>Association for Computational Linguistics. HERNANDEZ N., POULARD F., AFANTENOS S., VERNIER M. &amp; ROCHETEAU J. Not</journal>
<booktitle>In LAW at ACL,</booktitle>
<pages>33--40</pages>
<location>Prague, Czech Republic,</location>
<marker>HAHN, BUYKO, TOMANEK, PIAO, MCNAUGHT, TSURUOKA, ANANIADOU, 2007</marker>
<rawString>HAHN U., BUYKO E., TOMANEK K., PIAO S., MCNAUGHT J., TSURUOKA Y. &amp; ANANIADOU S. (2007). An annotation type system for a data-driven nlp pipeline. In LAW at ACL, p. 33–40 : Prague, Czech Republic, June 28-29, 2007. Stroudsburg, PA : Association for Computational Linguistics. HERNANDEZ N., POULARD F., AFANTENOS S., VERNIER M. &amp; ROCHETEAU J. Not yet another annotation framework but engineering-sensitive rules to design (uima) type systems. In A paraître.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>J L LEIDNER</author>
</authors>
<title>Current issues in software engineering for natural language processing.</title>
<date>2003</date>
<booktitle>In SEALTS at HLT/NAACL,</booktitle>
<pages>45--50</pages>
<location>Edmonton, Alberta, Canada.</location>
<marker>LEIDNER, 2003</marker>
<rawString>LEIDNER J. L. (2003). Current issues in software engineering for natural language processing. In SEALTS at HLT/NAACL, p. 45–50, Edmonton, Alberta, Canada.</rawString>
</citation>
</citationList>
</algorithm>
</algorithms>