<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<algorithms version="110505">
<algorithm name="ParsCit" version="110505">
<citationList>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>L VONAHN</author>
<author>L DABBISH</author>
</authors>
<title>Labelling Images with a Computer Game,</title>
<date>2004</date>
<booktitle>ACM Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems (CHI),</booktitle>
<pages>319--326</pages>
<marker>VONAHN, DABBISH, 2004</marker>
<rawString>VONAHN L., DABBISH L. (2004) Labelling Images with a Computer Game, ACM Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems (CHI), pp. 319-326.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="false">
<authors>
<author>J BOYD-GRABER</author>
<author>C FELLBAUM</author>
<author>D OSHERSON</author>
<author>R SCHAPIRE</author>
</authors>
<title>Adding dense, weighted connections to WordNet, Proceedings of the third Global WordNet Meeting, Jeju Island,</title>
<date>2006</date>
<journal>Journal of verbal learning and verbal behaviour,</journal>
<booktitle>Latent Semantic Indexing (LSI) and TREC-2, The Second Text REtrieval Conference, National Institute of Standards and Technology Special Publication,</booktitle>
<volume>8</volume>
<issue>2</issue>
<pages>240--248</pages>
<institution>Cepadues Ed.</institution>
<marker>BOYD-GRABER, FELLBAUM, OSHERSON, SCHAPIRE, 2006</marker>
<rawString>BOYD-GRABER J., FELLBAUM C., OSHERSON D., SCHAPIRE R. (2006) Adding dense, weighted connections to WordNet, Proceedings of the third Global WordNet Meeting, Jeju Island, Korea COLLINS A., QUILLIAN M.R. (1969) Retrieval time from semantic memory, Journal of verbal learning and verbal behaviour, 8 (2), pp. 240-248 DUMAIS S.T. (1994) Latent Semantic Indexing (LSI) and TREC-2, The Second Text REtrieval Conference, National Institute of Standards and Technology Special Publication, vol 500, n°215, pp. 105-116 FAIRON C., HO N.D. (2004) Quantité d’information échangée : une nouvelle mesure de la similarité des mots, Journées internationales d’Analyse statistiques des Données Textuelles (JADT’04), Louvain-la-Neuve (Belgique) GAUME B. (2004) Balades aléatoires dans les Petits Mondes Lexicaux, I3 Information Interaction Intelligence, vol. 4, n°2, Cepadues Ed.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="false">
<authors>
<author>M LAFOURCADE</author>
<author>A JOUBERT</author>
</authors>
<title>Détermination des sens d’usage dans un réseau lexical construit grâce à un jeu en ligne, Conférence sur le Traitement Automatique des Langues Naturelles (TALN’08),</title>
<date>2008</date>
<journal>Psychological Review,</journal>
<volume>104</volume>
<pages>211--240</pages>
<location>Avignon,</location>
<marker>LAFOURCADE, JOUBERT, 2008</marker>
<rawString>LAFOURCADE M., JOUBERT A. (2008) Détermination des sens d’usage dans un réseau lexical construit grâce à un jeu en ligne, Conférence sur le Traitement Automatique des Langues Naturelles (TALN’08), Avignon, pp.189-199 LANDAUER T.K., DUMAIS S.T. (1997) A solution to Plato’s problem : the Latent Semantic Analysis theory of acquisition, induction and representation of knowledge, Psychological Review, 104, pp. 211-240 LAPATA M., KELLER F. (2005) Web-based Models for Natural Language Processing, ACM Transactions on Speech and Language Processing, vol.2, n°1, pp. 1-30.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="false">
<authors>
<author>H LIEBERMAN</author>
<author>D A SMITH</author>
<author>A TEETERS</author>
</authors>
<title>Common Consensus: a web-based game for collecting commonsense goals,</title>
<date>2007</date>
<journal>Editions Duculot AUPELF-UREF</journal>
<booktitle>International Conference on Intelligent User Interfaces (IUI’07),</booktitle>
<volume>3</volume>
<issue>4</issue>
<pages>235--244</pages>
<publisher>MIT Press,</publisher>
<location>Hawaii, USA</location>
<marker>LIEBERMAN, SMITH, TEETERS, 2007</marker>
<rawString>LIEBERMAN H., SMITH D.A., TEETERS A. (2007) Common Consensus: a web-based game for collecting commonsense goals, International Conference on Intelligent User Interfaces (IUI’07), Hawaii, USA MANNING C.D., SCHÜTZE H. (1999) Foundations of Statistical Natural Language Processing, MIT Press, Cambridge MEL’CUK I.A., CLAS A., POLGUERE A. (1995) Introduction à la lexicologie explicative et combinatoire, Editions Duculot AUPELF-UREF MILLER G.A., BECKWITH R., FELLBAUM C., GROSS D., MILLER K.J. (1990) Introduction to WordNet: an on-line lexical database, International Journal of Lexicography 3 (4), pp. 235-244.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>S PLOUX</author>
<author>B VICTORRI</author>
</authors>
<title>Construction d’espaces sémantiques à l’aide de dictionnaires de synonymes, Traitement Automatique des</title>
<date>1998</date>
<journal>Langues,</journal>
<booktitle>Structural properties of Lexical Systems: Monolingual and Multilingual Perspectives, Proceedings of the Workshop on Multilingual Language Resources and Interoperability (COLING/ACL 2006),</booktitle>
<volume>39</volume>
<pages>161--182</pages>
<location>Sydney,</location>
<marker>PLOUX, VICTORRI, 1998</marker>
<rawString>PLOUX S., VICTORRI B. (1998) Construction d’espaces sémantiques à l’aide de dictionnaires de synonymes, Traitement Automatique des Langues, 39, n°1, pp. 161-182 POLGUÈRE A. (2006) Structural properties of Lexical Systems: Monolingual and Multilingual Perspectives, Proceedings of the Workshop on Multilingual Language Resources and Interoperability (COLING/ACL 2006), Sydney, pp. 50-59.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>ROBERTSON S et SPARK JONES K</author>
</authors>
<title>Relevance weighting of search terms,</title>
<date>1976</date>
<journal>Journal of the American Society for Information Science,</journal>
<volume>27</volume>
<pages>129--146</pages>
<marker>K, 1976</marker>
<rawString>ROBERTSON S. et SPARK JONES K. (1976) Relevance weighting of search terms, Journal of the American Society for Information Science, n° 27, pp. 129-146.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>ROGET</author>
</authors>
<title>Thesaurus of English Words and Phrases,</title>
<date>1968</date>
<location>Longman, London</location>
<marker>ROGET, 1968</marker>
<rawString>ROGET (1852) Thesaurus of English Words and Phrases, Longman, London SALTON G. (1968) Automatic Information Organization and Retrieval, Mac Graw Hill, NY.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="false">
<authors>
<author>A TVERSKY</author>
</authors>
<title>Features of similarity,</title>
<date>1977</date>
<journal>Psychological Review,</journal>
<booktitle>Corpus linguistics’ 2001 Conference,</booktitle>
<tech>ZAMPA</tech>
<volume>84</volume>
<pages>327--352</pages>
<location>Lancaster, U.K.</location>
<marker>TVERSKY, 1977</marker>
<rawString>TVERSKY A. (1977) Features of similarity, Psychological Review, 84, pp.327-352 VÉRONIS J. (2001) Sense tagging: does it make sense?, Corpus linguistics’ 2001 Conference, Lancaster, U.K. ZAMPA V. et LAFOURCADE M. (2009) Evaluations comparées de deux méthodes d’acquisitions lexicale et ontologique : JeuxDeMots vs Latent Semantic Analysis, XVIèmes rencontres de Rochebrune : ontologie et dynamique des systèmes complexes, perspectives interdisciplinaires.</rawString>
</citation>
</citationList>
</algorithm>
</algorithms>