<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<algorithms version="110505">
<algorithm name="ParsCit" version="110505">
<citationList>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>E Charniak</author>
<author>C Hendrickson</author>
<author>C Jacobson</author>
<author>M Perkowitz</author>
</authors>
<title>Equations for partof-speech tagging,</title>
<date>1993</date>
<booktitle>Proceedings of the 11th National Conference on AI,</booktitle>
<pages>784--789</pages>
<marker>Charniak, Hendrickson, Jacobson, Perkowitz, 1993</marker>
<rawString>E. Charniak, C. Hendrickson, C. Jacobson and M. Perkowitz (1993), Equations for partof-speech tagging, Proceedings of the 11th National Conference on AI, 784-789.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>M Collins</author>
<author>S Miller</author>
</authors>
<title>Semantic Tagging using a Probalistic Context Free Grammar,</title>
<date>1998</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the Sixth Workshop on Very Large Corpora.</booktitle>
<marker>Collins, Miller, 1998</marker>
<rawString>M. Collins and S. Miller (1998), Semantic Tagging using a Probalistic Context Free Grammar, In Proceedings of the Sixth Workshop on Very Large Corpora.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>M J Collins</author>
</authors>
<title>Three generative, lexicalised models for statistical parsing,</title>
<date>1997</date>
<booktitle>Proceedings of the 35th Annual Meeting of the Association for Computational Linguistics,</booktitle>
<pages>16--23</pages>
<marker>Collins, 1997</marker>
<rawString>M.J. Collins (1997), Three generative, lexicalised models for statistical parsing, Proceedings of the 35th Annual Meeting of the Association for Computational Linguistics, 16-23.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>S Miller</author>
<author>D Stallard</author>
<author>R Bobrow</author>
<author>R Schwartz</author>
</authors>
<title>A Fully Statistical Approach to Natural Language Interfaces,</title>
<date>1996</date>
<booktitle>Proceedings of the 34th Annual Meeting of the ACL,</booktitle>
<pages>55--61</pages>
<publisher>Morgan Kaufmann Publishers,</publisher>
<location>San Francisco, Arivind</location>
<marker>Miller, Stallard, Bobrow, Schwartz, 1996</marker>
<rawString>S. Miller, D. Stallard, R. Bobrow and R. Schwartz (1996), A Fully Statistical Approach to Natural Language Interfaces, Proceedings of the 34th Annual Meeting of the ACL, Morgan Kaufmann Publishers, San Francisco, Arivind J oshi and Martha Palmer, 55-61.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>L R Rabiner</author>
</authors>
<title>A tutorial on hidden Markov models and selected applications in speech recognition,</title>
<date>1989</date>
<booktitle>Proceedings of the IEEE,</booktitle>
<volume>77</volume>
<pages>257--286</pages>
<marker>Rabiner, 1989</marker>
<rawString>L.R. Rabiner (1989), A tutorial on hidden Markov models and selected applications in speech recognition, Proceedings of the IEEE, Vol. 77, No. 2, 257-286.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>C A Thompson</author>
<author>R J</author>
</authors>
<title>Learning to Parse Natural Language Database Queries into Logical Form,</title>
<date>1997</date>
<booktitle>Proceedings of the ML-97 Workshop on Automata Induction, Grammatical Inference, and Language Acquisition.</booktitle>
<marker>Thompson, J, 1997</marker>
<rawString>C. A. Thompson, R. J . Mooney and L. R.Tang (1997), Learning to Parse Natural Language Database Queries into Logical Form, Proceedings of the ML-97 Workshop on Automata Induction, Grammatical Inference, and Language Acquisition.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>C D Manning</author>
<author>B Carpenter</author>
</authors>
<title>Three generative, lexicalised models for statistical parsing,</title>
<date>1997</date>
<booktitle>Proceedings of the 5th Int. Workshop on Parsing Technologies,</booktitle>
<pages>147--158</pages>
<contexts>
<context position="1187" citStr="Manning and Carpenter, 1997" startWordPosition="166" endWordPosition="169"> similarities are then used to compute the degree of certainty of a particular parse. The treatment of word order and the disambiguation of meanings can therefore be learned. Mots-clefs — Keywords Analyseur sémantique, Corpus, Langue naturelle Semantic parser, Corpus, Natural language 1 Introduction In order to achieve better results in acquisition, coverage, robustness and portability, corpusbased methods have been recently applied with success in areas like speech recognition (Rabiber, 1989), part-of-speech tagging (Charniak, Hendrickson, Jacobson and Perkowitz, 1993) and syntactic parsing (Manning and Carpenter, 1997). In Semantic Parsing, the process of mapping a natural language input to some structured meaning representation, Collins and Miller (Collins, 1998) describe a statistical model for extraction of events; Miller, Stallard, Bobrow and Schwartz describe an approach entirely based on a trained statistical model (Miller, Stallard, Robrow and Schwartz, 1996) and Thompson, Mooney and Tang (Thompson, Mooney and Tang, 1997) propose a novel and very interesting approach based on a bottom-up parser and a machine learning algorithm. I propose an approach in which a bottom-up parser is combined with a stat</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Manning, Carpenter, 1997</marker>
<rawString>C.D. Manning and B. Carpenter (1997), Three generative, lexicalised models for statistical parsing, Proceedings of the 5th Int. Workshop on Parsing Technologies, 147-158.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>M P Marcus</author>
</authors>
<title>A Theory of Syntactic Recognition for Natural Language,</title>
<date>1980</date>
<publisher>MIT Press.</publisher>
<contexts>
<context position="2017" citStr="Marcus, 1980" startWordPosition="297" endWordPosition="298">ard, Bobrow and Schwartz describe an approach entirely based on a trained statistical model (Miller, Stallard, Robrow and Schwartz, 1996) and Thompson, Mooney and Tang (Thompson, Mooney and Tang, 1997) propose a novel and very interesting approach based on a bottom-up parser and a machine learning algorithm. I propose an approach in which a bottom-up parser is combined with a statistical model. Figure 1 shows the overall architecture of the system. 2 Overview of the Parsing Process This section presents the various elements of the system. The parser used is a variant of a Shift-Reduce parser (Marcus, 1980). It actually comprises three different manageable actions that the parser uses to get to the ﬁnal parse, which is a semantic interpretation (in ﬁrst-order logic) of a natural language utterance. This left to right parsing makes the process relatively intuitive for humans. J.V11\/1l\/1 \J \/ll\/L \/ LIA Training File Semantic Lexicon Overly General Parser Statistical File Specialized Parser Output: Meaning Figure 1: The Parser Architecture Input: Phrase The Input String The input string is a list of words to give an interpretation for. When no action is applicable and the input string is empty</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Marcus, 1980</marker>
<rawString>M.P. Marcus (1980), A Theory of Syntactic Recognition for Natural Language, MIT Press.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Ulf Hermjakob</author>
<author>J Raymond</author>
</authors>
<title>Learning Parse and Translation Decisions from Examples with Rich Context,</title>
<date>1997</date>
<booktitle>Proceedings of the 35th Annual Meeting of the Association for Computational Linguistics,</booktitle>
<pages>482--489</pages>
<marker>Hermjakob, Raymond, 1997</marker>
<rawString>Ulf Hermjakob and Raymond J . Mooney (1997), Learning Parse and Translation Decisions from Examples with Rich Context, Proceedings of the 35th Annual Meeting of the Association for Computational Linguistics, 482-489.</rawString>
</citation>
</citationList>
</algorithm>
</algorithms>