<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<conference>
    <edition>
        <acronyme>TALaRE'2015</acronyme>
        <titre>Traitement Automatique des Langues Régionales de France et d'Europe</titre>
        <ville>Caen</ville>
        <pays>France</pays>
        <dateDebut>2015-06-22</dateDebut>
        <dateFin>2015-06-22</dateFin>
        <presidents>
            <president>
                <prenom>Marianne</prenom>
                <nom>Vergez-Couret</nom>
            </president>
            <president>
                <prenom>Delphine</prenom>
                <nom>Bernhard</nom>
            </president>
            <president>
                <prenom>Anne-Laure</prenom>
                <nom>Ligozat</nom>
            </president>
            <president>
                <prenom>Jean-Michel</prenom>
                <nom>Eloy</nom>
            </president>
            <president>
                <prenom>Christophe</prenom>
                <nom>Rey</nom>
            </president>
        </presidents>
        <typeArticles>
            <type id="long">Articles</type>
        </typeArticles>
        <siteWeb>http://lilpa.unistra.fr/colloques/talare2015/</siteWeb>
    </edition>
	<articles>
	<article id="talare-2015-long-001">
		<auteurs>
			<auteur>
				<prenom>Marie-Hélène</prenom>
				<nom>Lay</nom>
				<email>marie-helene.lay@univ-poitiers.fr</email>
				<affiliationId>1</affiliationId>
				<affiliationId>2</affiliationId>
			</auteur>
			<auteur>
				<prenom>Jean-Christophe</prenom>
				<nom>Dourdet</nom>
				<email>jean-christophe.dourdet01@univ-poitiers.fr</email>
				<affiliationId>1</affiliationId>
				<affiliationId>2</affiliationId>
			</auteur>												
		</auteurs>
		<affiliations>
			<affiliation affiliationId="1">Université de Poitiers, 1, Rue Raymond Cantel Bât A3, TSA 11102, 86073 POITIERS CEDEX 9</affiliation>
			<affiliation affiliationId="2">Laboratoire FoReLL, EA 3816</affiliation>			
		</affiliations>
		<titre>Création de ressources lexicales pour une langue d'oïl : le parlanjhe</titre>
		<type>long</type>
		<pages></pages>
		<resume>Le présent article porte sur la constitution de ressources lexicales pour le poitevin-saintongeais, langue régionale (très) faiblement dotée. Depuis 2006, le projet TelPoS (Textes Electroniques en poitevin-saintongeais) a permis la constitution d'une base de données de textes (essentiellement littéraires) caractérisés par une forte variation, tant diatopique que diachronique (le premier texte date du 16e siècle). Le parlanjhe est une langue d'oïl, donc morphologiquement proche du français : nous avons choisi d'adapter des ressources dont nous disposions pour le français, en intégrant à notre outil d'annotation un moteur d'expansion de requêtes basé sur des règles morpho-graphématiques, VariaLog. L'une des caractéristiques essentielles de ce projet est de se dérouler dans un environnement disposant de très peu de compétences informatiques, les stratégies les plus répandues en TAL se trouvant de ce fait exclues. Nous utilisons donc AnaLog, un outil d'annotation manuelle développé précisément pour répondre à cette situation.</resume>
		<mots_cles>AnaLog, VariaLog, linguistique de corpus, annotation manuelle, annotation morpho-sytaxique, création de ressources lexicales, poitevin-saintongeais, parlanjhe</mots_cles>
		<title>Building lexical resources for Parlanjhe, a language of the Oïl area.</title>
		<abstract>The topic of this paper is the constitution of lexical resources for poitevin-saintongeais, a regional language of western France, one of the “under-resourced languages”. Since 2006, the TELPOS Project (Electronic Texts in poitevinsaintongeais) has helped constitute a database of texts, mainly literary texts, characterized by a wide variation, both diatopic and diachronic (the first text dates back to the XVIth century). The “parlanjhe” is a language of the oïl area, and therefore morphologically close to French. We chose to adapt the lexical resources at our disposal for French by adding to our annotation tool an engine called VariaLog, to expand queries on the basis of morpho-graphemic rules. One of the crucial characteristics of this project is that it is evolving in an environment with very little computer knowhow. The most widespread strategies prevailing in computer linguistics are therefore out of reach. This is why we use AnaLog, a manual annotation tool developed precisely to answer the needs of such situations.</abstract>
		<keywords>AnaLog, VariaLog, corpus linguistic, manual annotation, POS tagging, building of lexical resources, poitevin-saintongeais, parlanjhe.</keywords>
	</article>
	<article id="talare-2015-long-002">
		<auteurs>
			<auteur>
				<prenom>Delphine</prenom>
				<nom>Bernhard</nom>
				<email>dbernhard@unistra.fr</email>
				<affiliationId>1</affiliationId>
			</auteur>
			<auteur>
				<prenom>Lucie</prenom>
				<nom>Steiblé</nom>
				<email>steiblelucie@gmail.com</email>
				<affiliationId>1</affiliationId>
			</auteur>												
		</auteurs>
		<affiliations>
			<affiliation affiliationId="1">LiLPa, Université de Strasbourg, 14 rue Descartes, F-67084 Strasbourg Cedex</affiliation>
		</affiliations>
		<titre>Quand l’oral se fait entendre à l’écrit : alignement de lexiques en l’absence de normalisation graphique</titre>
		<type>long</type>
		<pages></pages>
		<resume>Les dialectes parlés en Alsace, que l’on regroupe communément sous l’appellation « alsacien », se caractérisent par un manque de ressources numériques, qu’il s’agisse de corpus ou de lexiques. Par ailleurs, les dialectes d’Alsace sont avant tout des langues parlées dans la vie quotidienne, et leur graphie n’est pas encore complètement codifiée : une unité lexicale peut donc avoir plusieurs graphies. Ceci est un défi majeur pour la construction de ressources lexicales, car les variantes orthographiques d’une entrée lexicale doivent être identifiées. Cet article décrit une méthode pour la construction de lexiques bilingues français-alsacien qui vise à résoudre ce problème. Elle consiste à aligner des lexiques bilingues existants, en utilisant l’algorithme phonétique Double Metaphone afin de détecter les variantes. En outre, les mots alsaciens sont automatiquement reliés aux entrées de BabelNet, un réseau sémantique multilingue (Navigli &amp; Ponzetto, 2012). La méthode d’alignement des lexiques atteint de bons niveaux de précision, ce qui permet la construction automatique de ressources, avec une intervention humaine limitée à quelques corrections. La principale originalité de ce travail est qu’il ne vise pas la normalisation, qui consisterait à transformer les variantes orthographiques en une norme donnée. Par ailleurs, au lieu d’une simple liste de mots bilingues, les liens vers BabelNet fournissent une couche sémantique supplémentaire reliant les entrées à des sens lexicaux. Enfin, nous utilisons les alignements obtenus pour faire une comparaison entre observations réalisées sur la langue orale et les graphies relevées dans les lexiques.</resume>
		<mots_cles>alignement de lexiques, variantes orthographiques, alsacien, BabelNet</mots_cles>
		<title>From Spoken to Written : Lexicon Alignment in the Absence of an Orthographic System</title>
		<abstract>The dialects spoken in Alsace, which are commonly grouped under the name “Alsatian”, are characterized by a lack of digital resources, whether corpora or lexicons. Moreover, the Alsatian dialects are primarily spoken in everyday life, and their spelling is not yet completely codified : a given lexical unit can have multiple spellings. This is a major challenge for building lexical resources because alternative spellings of a lexical entry must be identified. This article describes a method for building French-Alsatian bilingual lexicons that aims to solve this problem. It consists in aligning existing bilingual lexicons, using the phonetic algorithm Double Metaphone to detect variants. In addition, the Alsatian words are automatically linked to entries in Babelnet, a multilingual semantic network (Navigli &amp; Ponzetto, 2012). The lexicon alignment method achieves good levels of precision, which allows the automatic construction of resources with limited human intervention. The main originality of this work is that it does not target normalization, which would transform the spelling variants to a given standard. Moreover, instead of a simple list of bilingual words, links to Babelnet provide an additional semantic layer which connects the lexical items to senses. Finally, we use the alignments obtained to perform a comparison between phenomena observed in the spoken language and the written forms found in the lexicons.</abstract>
		<keywords>lexicon alignment, spelling variants, Alsatian, BabelNet</keywords>
	</article>
	<article id="talare-2015-long-003">
		<auteurs>
			<auteur>
				<prenom>Jean-Michel</prenom>
				<nom>Eloy</nom>
				<email>jean-michel.eloy@u-picardie.fr</email>
				<affiliationId>1</affiliationId>
			</auteur>
			<auteur>
				<prenom>Fanny</prenom>
				<nom>Martin</nom>
				<email>fanny.martin@u-picardie.fr</email>
				<affiliationId>1</affiliationId>
			</auteur>
			<auteur>
				<prenom>Christophe</prenom>
				<nom>Rey</nom>
				<email>christophe.rey@u-picardie.fr</email>
				<affiliationId>1</affiliationId>
			</auteur>												
		</auteurs>
		<affiliations>
			<affiliation affiliationId="1">LESCLAP (CERCLL-EA 4283), Université de Picardie Jules Verne, Amiens</affiliation>						
		</affiliations>
		<titre>PICARTEXT : Une ressource informatisée pour la langue picarde</titre>
		<type>long</type>
		<pages></pages>
		<resume>Picartext est une base de données textuelles, construite depuis près de 10 ans à l'Université de Picardie à Amiens. Elle présente des caractéristiques de premier intérêt pour la recherche sur les traitements automatiques. La langue picarde, d'une vitalité non négligeable, dispose d'une littérature assez abondante et de très nombreux dictionnaires et glossaires. Mais elle ne possède pas de standard, ni linguistique, ni graphique. La langue est donc très variante. La base de données, de nature littéraire, d'environ 5 millions d'occurrences, est accessible en ligne au moyen d'un outil d'interrogation paramétrable : non seulement il permet la restriction du corpus de travail (lieux, dates, genres), mais il permet une recherche tenant compte d'équivalences phonétiques et d'équivalences dialectales. Il est ouvert à des évolutions en termes de balisage, en particulier dans le cadre d'un projet ANR portant sur trois langues régionales simultanément (picard, alsacien, occitan).</resume>
		<mots_cles>picard, non standardisation, variation dialectale, variation graphique, numérisation, balisage, équivalences</mots_cles>
		<title>PICARTEXT : a computerized resource for picard</title>
		<abstract>Picartext is a textual database, built up since about 10 years in Picardy University in Amiens. Some of its characteristics make it very interesting for research on natural languages processing. Picard language, of a not insignificant vitality, has a rather plentiful literature, and very numerous dictionaries and glossaries. But it does not possess standard, either linguistics, or graphic. The language is thus very variant. The database, of literary nature, counts about 5 million token, is reachable on-line, with a customizable tool of interrogation : not only it allows the limitation of the working corpus (places, dates, genres), but he allows a search taking into account phonetic equivalences and dialectal equivalences. It is opened to evolutions in terms of tagging, in particular within the framework of an ANR project concerning three regional languages simultaneously (picard, alsatian, occitan).</abstract>
		<keywords>picard language, non standardisation, dialectal variation, graphical variation, digitisation, tagging, equivalences</keywords>
		</article>	
		<article id="talare-2015-long-004">
			<auteurs>
				<auteur>
					<prenom>Annie</prenom>
					<nom>Foret</nom>
					<email>Annie.Foret@irisa.fr</email>
					<affiliationId>1</affiliationId>
				</auteur>
				<auteur>
					<prenom>Valérie</prenom>
					<nom>Bellynck</nom>
					<email>Valerie.Bellynck@imag.fr</email>
					<affiliationId>2</affiliationId>
				</auteur>
				<auteur>
					<prenom>Christian</prenom>
					<nom>Boitet</nom>
					<email>Christian.Boitet@imag.fr</email>
					<affiliationId>2</affiliationId>
				</auteur>												
			</auteurs>
			<affiliations>
				<affiliation affiliationId="1">IRISA &amp; Université Rennes 1, Campus de Beaulieu, F-35042 Rennes cedex</affiliation>
			<affiliation affiliationId="2">LIG-GETALP, UdG &amp; CNRS, Campus, 41 rue des Mathématiques, GRENOBLE cedex 9</affiliation>					
			</affiliations>
			<titre>Akenou-Breizh, un projet de plate-forme valorisant des ressources et outils informatiques et linguistiques pour le breton</titre>
			<type>long</type>
			<pages></pages>
			<resume>Nous présentons un nouveau projet, Akenou-Breizh, qui vise (1) à mettre en place une plate-forme permettant d’étudier les influences d’une langue d’héritage, comme le breton, sur une langue d’usage, comme le français, et (2) à mettre à disposition de tous les intéressés des outils s’intégrant au “Web sémantique et multilingue”, et proposant des accès proactifs aux connaissances sur le breton ainsi qu’une visualisation directe des correspondances sous-phrastiques dans des présentations bilingues alignées. Nous nous proposons non seulement d’utiliser les nombreuses ressources disponibles librement, en particulier celles de l’OPLB 1 et du projet APERTIUM, mais aussi d’en créer de nouvelles, comme des corpus bilingues alignés de bonne qualité, en utilisant le “Web collaboratif”, et de construire sur le site dédié lingwarium.org des modules linguistiques améliorant ou étendant ceux qui existent, par exemple un analyseur-générateur morphologique. Nous décrivons aussi une expérience réalisée à partir d’un lexique réduit pour le breton, qui montre comment on peut enrichir un dictionnaire classique, en le reliant à un treillis de thèmes et à un système de gestion de contexte (ici CAMELIS), de façon à ce qu’on puisse l’interroger (par facettes sémantiques) et comparer différentes ressources.</resume>
			<mots_cles>breton, langue d’héritage, langue d’usage, outils et ressources, études contrastives</mots_cles>
			<title>Akenou-Breizh, a platform project to develop computational and linguistic resources and tools for breton</title>
			<abstract>We present a new project, Akenou-Breizh, that aims to (1) put in place a platform allowing to study the influences of an heritage language, such as Breton, on a usage language, such as French, and (2) to make available, to all interested persons, tools well integrated in the “semantic and multilingual web” and proposing proactive access to various kinds of knowledge concerning Breton, as well as direct visualisation of infrasentential correspondences in aligned bilingual presentations. We plan not only to use the numerous freely available resources, in particular those of OPLB and of the APERTIUM project, but also to create new ones, such as good quality bilingual aligned corpora, thereby using the “collaborative web”, and to build on the dedicated lingwarium.org web site linguistic modules improving on or extending those that exist, for example a morphological analyzer-generator.We also describe an experiment set up starting from a reduced lexicon for Breton, that shows how it is possible to enrich a classical dictionary, by linking it to a lattice of topics and to a context management system (here CAMELIS), in such a way one can query it (along semantic facets) and compare different resources.</abstract>
			<keywords>Breton, heritage language, usage language, tools and resources, contrastive studies</keywords>
		</article>	
		<article id="talare-2015-long-005">
			<auteurs>
				<auteur>
					<prenom>Benoît</prenom>
					<nom>Dazéas</nom>
					<email>b.dazeas@locongres.org</email>
					<affiliationId>1</affiliationId>
				</auteur>												
			</auteurs>
			<affiliations>
				<affiliation affiliationId="1">Lo Congrès permanent de la lenga occitana, Château d'Este, BP 326, 64141 Billère cedex</affiliation>
			</affiliations>
			<titre>Feuille de route pour le développement numérique occitan</titre>
			<type>long</type>
			<pages></pages>
			<resume>Le Livre blanc de META-NET, un réseau d’experts européens en technologies de la langue, alerte sur le risque « d’extinction numérique » de plusieurs langues européennes et de l’urgence pour elles de se doter rapidement de technologies de support. Cette étude propose également une grille de classification et d’évaluation des ressources et préconise des principes d’action tels que la création massive de données, la mutualisation ou encore le transfert technologique. Dans ce cadre Lo Congres permanent de lenga occitana a piloté la rédaction d’une feuille de route pour le développement numérique de l’occitan. Le rapport final fait état des ressources existantes et propose une planification de réalisation (2015-2019) des ressources de bases et des outils finaux. La mise en place de cet ambitieux programme nécessitera la coordination des acteurs de transmission de l’occitan – politiques linguistiques, recherche scientifique et communauté du logiciel libre – ainsi que la mobilisation des différents crédits et fonds européens.</resume>
			<mots_cles>Langues régionales et minoritaires, occitan, feuille de route, ressources langagières, technologies de la langue, politiques linguistiques.</mots_cles>
			<title>Roadmap for the Occitan digital development</title>
			<abstract>The META-NET White Paper Series, issued by the European network of experts in language technology, alerts to the risk of digital extiction for several European languages and the emergency to get equipped with supporting technologies. The study also presents a classification scale and assessment of the ressources and recommends taking actions, like massive data import, resource pooling, or technological tranfert. According to this, Lo Congres permanent de la lenga occitana steered the drawing up of a roadmap for the Occitan digital development. The final report lists the existing resources and schedules the release of each basic resource and final tools (2015-2019). The implementation of this ambitious workprogram will require a teamwork of all partners involved in the transmission of Occitan – language policies, scientific research and open-source application community – as well as gathering various credits and European Funds.</abstract>
			<keywords>Regional and minority languages, Occitan, language ressources, language technologies, language policies</keywords>
		</article>
		<article id="talare-2015-long-006">
			<auteurs>
				<auteur>
					<prenom>Dominique</prenom>
					<nom>Château-Annaud</nom>
					<email>dc@macarel.net</email>
					<email>d.chateau@laposte.net</email>
					<affiliationId>1</affiliationId>
				</auteur>											
			</auteurs>
			<affiliations>
				<affiliation affiliationId="1">Association Òsca-Font dubèrta, 1 charrèira/rue St Rames, 63000 Clarmont d’Auvèrnhe/Clermont-Ferrand</affiliation>
			</affiliations>
			<titre>Communication sur les travaux de Òsca-Font dubèrta</titre>
			<type>long</type>
			<pages></pages>
			<resume>Cette communication présente l’intégration de deux développements informatiques récents conçus comme des outils linguistiques et lexicographiques séparés. Cette intégration se concrétise en un outil original, une plate-forme d’édition numérique dont la notion sera précisée. Les deux projets sont implantés dans un site web et exploitent les données provenant de bases de données SQL. L’interface utilisateur est constitué de formulaires d’édition et de recherche, de tableaux en HTML et de rapports en différents formats. À l’origine les données proviennent de dictionnaires dialectaux, de listes de verbes, de modèles de conjugaison et d’autres informations annexes. L’ensemble est uniquement disponible dans un format faiblement structuré (traitement de texte WYSIWYG) impropre à un traitement numérique efficace, ce qui nécessite une conversion en base de données. Celle-ci a suscité beaucoup d’efforts et soulevé des contraintes méthodologiques et humaines. Pour le conjugueur automatique les algorithmes sont codés comme une hiérarchie de classes d’objets facile à adapter pour d’autres dialectes 1 et extensible à d’autres formats de sortie. Pour conclure nous évoquerons l’extension des capacités de la plate-forme vers les bases de données textuelles NoSQL et vers une architecture REST.</resume>
			<mots_cles>plate-forme d’édition numérique, base de données NoSQL, outil lexicographique, conjugueur automatique, conception orientée-objet, lexique, dictionnaire</mots_cles>
			<title>Paper on the work of OSCA-Font dubèrta</title>
			<abstract>This paper presents the integration of two recent IT developments designed to be two separated linguistic and lexicographical tools in an original one, a digital publishing platform, which concept will be described. Both projects are web applications, typically LAMP (Linux, Apache, MySql, PHP). The first one is designed to build a transdialectal lexical base. Data comes from dialectal dictionaries, verb lists, conjugation patterns and other related information to be converted in database. Despite the weakly structured format (WYSIWYG word processing) not usable for serious digital processing, the conversion populated a big lexical base. The conversion task drew a lot of efforts and raised methodological and human constraints. The second one is an automatic conjugator made from an easy to adapt object-oriented hierarchy for the lengadocian occitan dialect. One more dialect, gascon is available and wait to be tested. Provencal dialect is on study. Output formats extensions can be implemented by a loosely coupled coding. As a conclusion we will discuss the extension of the publishing platform capabilities geared to textual NoSql databases and REST architecture</abstract>
			<keywords>digital publishing platform, NoSQL database, lexicographical tool, automatic conjugator, object-oriented design, glossary, dictionary.</keywords>
		</article>
		<article id="talare-2015-long-007">
			<auteurs>
				<auteur>
					<prenom>Marianne</prenom>
					<nom>Vergez-Couret</nom>
					<email>marianne.vergez@univ-tlse2.fr</email>
					<affiliationId>1</affiliationId>
				</auteur>
				<auteur>
					<prenom>Assaf</prenom>
					<nom>Urieli</nom>
					<email>assaf.urieli@univ-tlse2.fr</email>
					<affiliationId>1</affiliationId>
					<affiliationId>2</affiliationId>
				</auteur>												
			</auteurs>
			<affiliations>
				<affiliation affiliationId="1">CLLE-ERSS, CNRS, Université de Toulouse 2, 5 allées Antonio Machado, 31058 TOULOUSE cedex 9</affiliation>
				<affiliation affiliationId="2">Joliciel Informatique SARL, 2 avenue du Cardié, 09000 FOIX</affiliation>		
			</affiliations>
			<titre>Analyse morphosyntaxique de l'occitan languedocien : l'amitié entre un petit languedocien et un gros catalan</titre>
			<type>long</type>
			<pages></pages>
			<resume>Dans cette étude, nous nous intéressons à la question de l'analyse morphosyntaxique de l'occitan. Nous utilisons Talismane, un logiciel par apprentissage supervisé, nécessitant des données annotées pour l'entraînement et optionnellement un lexique. Nous montrons dans cet article, qu'en l'absence de données annotées suffisantes pour l'occitan, il est possible d'obtenir de bons résultats (92%) en utilisant les données d'une langue étymologiquement proche, le catalan. Nous avons utilisé le corpus Ancora (500 000 formes) et un lexique occitan languedocien (250 000 entrées). Utiliser un corpus catalan de taille importante permet une amélioration de +3% par rapport au résultat obtenu avec le seul corpus d'entraînement occitan disponible à ce jour de 2800 formes.</resume>
			<mots_cles>traitement automatique des langues peu dotées, occitan, analyse morphosyntaxique</mots_cles>
			<title>Pos-tagging the Lengadocian dialect of Occitan: a little Lengadocian befriends a big Catalan</title>
			<abstract>In this study, we examine the question of Occitan POS-tagging. We use Talismane, a supervised machine learning NLP tool, requiring annotated data for training and optionally a lexicon. We show that, with insufficient data for Occitan, it is possible to obtain good results (92%) by using data from an etymologically close language, in this case Catalan. We used the Catalan Ancora corpus (500,000 tokens) and an Occitan Languedocien lexicon (250,000 entries). Using the larger Catalan corpus improved results by +3% with respect to the result obtained using the only Occitan training corpus available to date (2,800 tokens).</abstract>
			<keywords>natural language processing for lesser resourced languages, Occitan, POS-tagging</keywords>
		</article>
	</articles>
</conference>
