<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<algorithms version="110505">
<algorithm name="ParsCit" version="110505">
<citationList>
<citation valid="false">
<title>Remerciements Nous remercions Antoine Sylvain pour sa participation à la constitution du corpus de textes issus de Wikipédia et Vikidia. Ces travaux ont reçu le soutien financier du projet DOXA du pôle de compétitivité CAP-DIGITAL.</title>
<date>2010</date>
<journal>Références BELDER, J. D. et MOENS, M.-F.</journal>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the Workshop on Accessible Search Systems, in conjunction with SIGIR</booktitle>
<contexts>
<context position="5003" citStr="(2010)" startWordPosition="738" endWordPosition="738">upprimer et de rendre les informations primordiales plus visibles et d’autre part quelles sont les constructions syntaxiques qui peuvent poser problème pour les simplifier. Parmi les premiers efforts en ce sens, citons (Carroll et al., 1999) et (Inui et al., 2003), qui ont proposé des outils pour produire des textes plus abordables pour les personnes atteintes d’un handicap langagier tel que l’aphasie ou la surdité. Cependant, l’aide à la lecture ne s’adresse pas qu’aux lecteurs présentant des handicaps, mais aussi à ceux qui apprennent une langue (première ou seconde). Ainsi, Belder et Moens (2010) se sont intéressés à la simplification pour des enfants de langue maternelle anglaise, tandis que Siddharthan (2006), Petersen et Ostendorf (2007) et Medero et Ostendorf (2011) ont étudié la simplification pour les apprenants d’une langue seconde. La plupart de ces travaux concernent la langue anglaise, à l’exception de (Inui et al., 2003) qui traitent également le japonais. Parallèlement, la simplification automatique a également été utilisée comme un pré-traitement visant à augmenter l’efficacité d’opérations postérieures effectuées sur des textes. Les premiers, Chandrasekar et al. (1996) o</context>
</contexts>
<marker>2010</marker>
<rawString>Remerciements Nous remercions Antoine Sylvain pour sa participation à la constitution du corpus de textes issus de Wikipédia et Vikidia. Ces travaux ont reçu le soutien financier du projet DOXA du pôle de compétitivité CAP-DIGITAL. Références BELDER, J. D. et MOENS, M.-F. (2010). Text Simplification for Children. In Proceedings of the Workshop on Accessible Search Systems, in conjunction with SIGIR 2010.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>M CANDITO</author>
<author>J NIVRE</author>
<author>P et ANGUIANO DENIS</author>
<author>E</author>
</authors>
<title>Benchmarking of statistical dependency parsers for French.</title>
<date>2010</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the 23rd International Conference on Computational Linguistics : Posters,</booktitle>
<pages>108--116</pages>
<publisher>Association</publisher>
<institution>for Computational Linguistics.</institution>
<marker>CANDITO, NIVRE, DENIS, E, 2010</marker>
<rawString>CANDITO, M., NIVRE, J., DENIS, P. et ANGUIANO, E. (2010). Benchmarking of statistical dependency parsers for French. In Proceedings of the 23rd International Conference on Computational Linguistics : Posters, pages 108–116. Association for Computational Linguistics.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>J CARROLL</author>
<author>G MINNEN</author>
<author>D PEARCE</author>
<author>Y CANNING</author>
<author>S et TAIT DEVLIN</author>
<author>J</author>
</authors>
<title>Simplifying Text for Language-Impaired Readers.</title>
<date>1999</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the Ninth Conference of the European Chapter of the Association for Computational Linguistics,</booktitle>
<pages>269--270</pages>
<marker>CARROLL, MINNEN, PEARCE, CANNING, DEVLIN, J, 1999</marker>
<rawString>CARROLL, J., MINNEN, G., PEARCE, D., CANNING, Y., DEVLIN, S. et TAIT, J. (1999). Simplifying Text for Language-Impaired Readers. In Proceedings of the Ninth Conference of the European Chapter of the Association for Computational Linguistics, pages 269–270.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>N CATACH</author>
</authors>
<title>Les listes orthographiques de base du français.</title>
<date>1985</date>
<location>Nathan, Paris.</location>
<marker>CATACH, 1985</marker>
<rawString>CATACH, N. (1985). Les listes orthographiques de base du français. Nathan, Paris.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>J et DALE CHALL</author>
<author>E</author>
</authors>
<title>Readability Revisited : The New Dale-Chall Readability Formula. Brookline Books,</title>
<date>1995</date>
<location>Cambridge.</location>
<marker>CHALL, E, 1995</marker>
<rawString>CHALL, J. et DALE, E. (1995). Readability Revisited : The New Dale-Chall Readability Formula. Brookline Books, Cambridge.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>R CHANDRASEKAR</author>
<author>C et SRINIVAS DORAN</author>
<author>B</author>
</authors>
<title>Motivations and methods for text simplification.</title>
<date>1996</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the 16th conference on Computational linguistics,</booktitle>
<pages>1041--1044</pages>
<marker>CHANDRASEKAR, DORAN, B, 1996</marker>
<rawString>CHANDRASEKAR, R., DORAN, C. et SRINIVAS, B. (1996). Motivations and methods for text simplification. In Proceedings of the 16th conference on Computational linguistics, pages 1041–1044.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>P DENIS</author>
<author>B SAGOT</author>
</authors>
<title>Coupling an annotated corpus and a morphosyntactic lexicon for state-of-the-art pos tagging with less human effort.</title>
<date>2009</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of PACLIC.</booktitle>
<marker>DENIS, SAGOT, 2009</marker>
<rawString>DENIS, P., SAGOT, B. et al. (2009). Coupling an annotated corpus and a morphosyntactic lexicon for state-of-the-art pos tagging with less human effort. In Proceedings of PACLIC.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>D et FAVRE GILLICK</author>
<author>B</author>
</authors>
<title>A scalable global model for summarization.</title>
<date>2009</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the Workshop on Integer Linear Programming for Natural Language Processing, ILP ’09,</booktitle>
<pages>10--18</pages>
<location>Stroudsburg, PA, USA.</location>
<marker>GILLICK, B, 2009</marker>
<rawString>GILLICK, D. et FAVRE, B. (2009). A scalable global model for summarization. In Proceedings of the Workshop on Integer Linear Programming for Natural Language Processing, ILP ’09, pages 10–18, Stroudsburg, PA, USA.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>M et SMITH HEILMAN</author>
<author>N A</author>
</authors>
<title>Extracting Simplified Statements for Factual Question Generation.</title>
<date>2010</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the 3rd Workshop on Question Generation.</booktitle>
<marker>HEILMAN, A, 2010</marker>
<rawString>HEILMAN, M. et SMITH, N. A. (2010). Extracting Simplified Statements for Factual Question Generation. In Proceedings of the 3rd Workshop on Question Generation.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>K INUI</author>
<author>A FUJITA</author>
<author>T TAKAHASHI</author>
<author>R et IWAKURA IIDA</author>
<author>T</author>
</authors>
<title>Text simplification for reading assistance : a project note.</title>
<date>2003</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the second international workshop on Paraphrasing,</booktitle>
<pages>9--16</pages>
<marker>INUI, FUJITA, TAKAHASHI, IIDA, T, 2003</marker>
<rawString>INUI, K., FUJITA, A., TAKAHASHI, T., IIDA, R. et IWAKURA, T. (2003). Text simplification for reading assistance : a project note. In Proceedings of the second international workshop on Paraphrasing, pages 9–16.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>S JONNALAGADDA</author>
<author>L TARI</author>
<author>J HAKENBERG</author>
<author>C et GONZALEZ BARAL</author>
<author>G</author>
</authors>
<title>Towards Effective Sentence Simplification for Automatic Processing of Biomedical Text.</title>
<date>2009</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of NAACLHLT</booktitle>
<marker>JONNALAGADDA, TARI, HAKENBERG, BARAL, G, 2009</marker>
<rawString>JONNALAGADDA, S., TARI, L., HAKENBERG, J., BARAL, C. et GONZALEZ, G. (2009). Towards Effective Sentence Simplification for Automatic Processing of Biomedical Text. In Proceedings of NAACLHLT 2009.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>R et ANDREW LEVY</author>
<author>G</author>
</authors>
<title>Tregex and tsurgeon : tools for querying and manipulating tree data structures.</title>
<date>2006</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the fifth international conference on Language Resources and Evaluation,</booktitle>
<pages>2231--2234</pages>
<marker>LEVY, G, 2006</marker>
<rawString>LEVY, R. et ANDREW, G. (2006). Tregex and tsurgeon : tools for querying and manipulating tree data structures. In Proceedings of the fifth international conference on Language Resources and Evaluation, pages 2231–2234.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>J et WILBUR LIN</author>
<author>W J</author>
</authors>
<title>Syntactic sentence compression in the biomedical domain : facilitating access to related articles.</title>
<date>2007</date>
<journal>Information Retrieval,</journal>
<volume>10</volume>
<issue>4</issue>
<marker>LIN, J, 2007</marker>
<rawString>LIN, J. et WILBUR, W. J. (2007). Syntactic sentence compression in the biomedical domain : facilitating access to related articles. Information Retrieval, 10(4):393–414.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>J et OSTENDORF MEDERO</author>
<author>M</author>
</authors>
<title>Identifying Targets for Syntactic Simplification.</title>
<date>2011</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the SLaTE</booktitle>
<pages>workshop.</pages>
<marker>MEDERO, M, 2011</marker>
<rawString>MEDERO, J. et OSTENDORF, M. (2011). Identifying Targets for Syntactic Simplification. In Proceedings of the SLaTE 2011 workshop.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>R et SHIEBER NELKEN</author>
<author>S</author>
</authors>
<title>Towards robust context-sensitive sentence alignment for monolingual corpora.</title>
<date>2006</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the 11th Conference of the European Chapter of the Association for Computational Linguistics,</booktitle>
<pages>161--168</pages>
<marker>NELKEN, S, 2006</marker>
<rawString>NELKEN, R. et SHIEBER, S. (2006). Towards robust context-sensitive sentence alignment for monolingual corpora. In Proceedings of the 11th Conference of the European Chapter of the Association for Computational Linguistics, pages 161–168.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>V PATEL</author>
<author>T et AROCHA BRANCH</author>
<author>J</author>
</authors>
<title>Errors in interpreting quantities as procedures : The case of pharmaceutical labels.</title>
<date>2002</date>
<booktitle>International journal of medical informatics,</booktitle>
<pages>65--3</pages>
<marker>PATEL, BRANCH, J, 2002</marker>
<rawString>PATEL, V., BRANCH, T. et AROCHA, J. (2002). Errors in interpreting quantities as procedures : The case of pharmaceutical labels. International journal of medical informatics, 65(3):193–211.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>S E et OSTENDORF PETERSEN</author>
<author>M</author>
</authors>
<title>Text Simplification for Language Learners : A Corpus Analysis.</title>
<date>2007</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of Speech and Language Technology in Education (SLaTE2007),</booktitle>
<pages>69--72</pages>
<marker>PETERSEN, M, 2007</marker>
<rawString>PETERSEN, S. E. et OSTENDORF, M. (2007). Text Simplification for Language Learners : A Corpus Analysis. In Proceedings of Speech and Language Technology in Education (SLaTE2007), pages 69–72.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>J RICHARD</author>
<author>J BARCENILLA</author>
<author>B BRIE</author>
<author>E CHARMET</author>
<author>E et REYNARD CLEMENT</author>
<author>P</author>
</authors>
<title>Le traitement de documents administratifs par des populations de bas niveau de formation.</title>
<date>1993</date>
<journal>Le Travail Humain,</journal>
<volume>56</volume>
<issue>4</issue>
<marker>RICHARD, BARCENILLA, BRIE, CHARMET, CLEMENT, P, 1993</marker>
<rawString>RICHARD, J., BARCENILLA, J., BRIE, B., CHARMET, E., CLEMENT, E. et REYNARD, P. (1993). Le traitement de documents administratifs par des populations de bas niveau de formation. Le Travail Humain, 56(4):345–367.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>A SIDDHARTHAN</author>
</authors>
<title>Syntactic Simplification and Text Cohesion.</title>
<date>2006</date>
<journal>Research on Language &amp; Computation,</journal>
<volume>4</volume>
<issue>1</issue>
<marker>SIDDHARTHAN, 2006</marker>
<rawString>SIDDHARTHAN, A. (2006). Syntactic Simplification and Text Cohesion. Research on Language &amp; Computation, 4(1):77–109.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>L SPECIA</author>
</authors>
<title>Translating from Complex to Simplified Sentences.</title>
<date>2010</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the 9th International Conference on Computational Processing of the Portuguese Language (Propor-2010).,</booktitle>
<pages>30--39</pages>
<marker>SPECIA, 2010</marker>
<rawString>SPECIA, L. (2010). Translating from Complex to Simplified Sentences. In Proceedings of the 9th International Conference on Computational Processing of the Portuguese Language (Propor-2010)., pages 30–39.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>J WILLMS</author>
</authors>
<title>Literacy proficiency of youth : Evidence of converging socioeconomic gradients.</title>
<date>2003</date>
<journal>International Journal of Educational Research,</journal>
<volume>39</volume>
<issue>3</issue>
<marker>WILLMS, 2003</marker>
<rawString>WILLMS, J. (2003). Literacy proficiency of youth : Evidence of converging socioeconomic gradients. International Journal of Educational Research, 39(3):247–252.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>K et LAPATA WOODSEND</author>
<author>M</author>
</authors>
<title>Learning to Simplify Sentences with Quasi-Synchronous Grammar and Integer Programming.</title>
<date>2011</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the 2011 Conference on Empirical Methods in Natural Language Processing,</booktitle>
<pages>409--420</pages>
<location>Edinburgh, Scotland, UK.</location>
<marker>WOODSEND, M, 2011</marker>
<rawString>WOODSEND, K. et LAPATA, M. (2011). Learning to Simplify Sentences with Quasi-Synchronous Grammar and Integer Programming. In Proceedings of the 2011 Conference on Empirical Methods in Natural Language Processing, pages 409–420, Edinburgh, Scotland, UK.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Z ZHU</author>
<author>D et GUREVYCH BERNHARD</author>
<author>I</author>
</authors>
<title>A Monolingual Tree-based Translation Model for Sentence Simplification.</title>
<date>2010</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the 23rd International Conference on Computational Linguistics (Coling</booktitle>
<pages>1353--1361</pages>
<location>Beijing, China.</location>
<marker>ZHU, BERNHARD, I, 2010</marker>
<rawString>ZHU, Z., BERNHARD, D. et GUREVYCH, I. (2010). A Monolingual Tree-based Translation Model for Sentence Simplification. In Proceedings of the 23rd International Conference on Computational Linguistics (Coling 2010), pages 1353–1361, Beijing, China.</rawString>
</citation>
</citationList>
</algorithm>
</algorithms>