<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<algorithms version="110505">
<algorithm name="ParsCit" version="110505">
<citationList>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>C et CALLISON-BURCH BANNARD</author>
<author>C</author>
</authors>
<title>Paraphrasing with bilingual parallel corpora.</title>
<date>2005</date>
<booktitle>In Actes de ACL,</booktitle>
<location>Ann Arbor, USA.</location>
<marker>BANNARD, C, 2005</marker>
<rawString>BANNARD, C. et CALLISON-BURCH, C. (2005). Paraphrasing with bilingual parallel corpora. In Actes de ACL, Ann Arbor, USA.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>R et LEE BARZILAY</author>
<author>L</author>
</authors>
<title>Learning to paraphrase : an unsupervised approach using multiple-sequence alignment.</title>
<date>2003</date>
<booktitle>In Actes de NAACL-HLT,</booktitle>
<location>Edmonton, Canada.</location>
<marker>BARZILAY, L, 2003</marker>
<rawString>BARZILAY, R. et LEE, L. (2003). Learning to paraphrase : an unsupervised approach using multiple-sequence alignment. In Actes de NAACL-HLT, Edmonton, Canada.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>R et MCKEOWN BARZILAY</author>
<author>K</author>
</authors>
<title>Extracting paraphrases from a parallel corpus.</title>
<date>2001</date>
<booktitle>In Actes de ACL,</booktitle>
<location>Toulouse, France.</location>
<marker>BARZILAY, K, 2001</marker>
<rawString>BARZILAY, R. et MCKEOWN, K. (2001). Extracting paraphrases from a parallel corpus. In Actes de ACL, Toulouse, France.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>M S BERNSTEIN</author>
<author>G LITTLE</author>
<author>R C MILLER</author>
<author>B HARTMANN</author>
<author>M S ACKERMAN</author>
<author>D R KARGER</author>
<author>D et PANOVICH CROWELL</author>
<author>K</author>
</authors>
<title>Soylent : a word processor with a crowd inside.</title>
<date>2010</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the ACM symposium on User interface software and technology.</booktitle>
<marker>BERNSTEIN, LITTLE, MILLER, HARTMANN, ACKERMAN, KARGER, CROWELL, K, 2010</marker>
<rawString>BERNSTEIN, M. S., LITTLE, G., MILLER, R. C., HARTMANN, B., ACKERMAN, M. S., KARGER, D. R., CROWELL, D. et PANOVICH, K. (2010). Soylent : a word processor with a crowd inside. In Proceedings of the ACM symposium on User interface software and technology.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Bannard et Callison-Burch</author>
</authors>
<title>ont montré que l’utilisation simultanée de plusieurs langues pivots permettait de diminuer de façon importante les phénomènes de bruit.</title>
<date>2005</date>
<contexts>
<context position="7470" citStr="Callison-Burch, 2005" startWordPosition="1097" endWordPosition="1098">lement montré, au travers d’une tentative d’identification automatique à base de règles, les difficultés pour parvenir à une bonne couverture de l’ensemble des phénomènes paraphrastiques présents. Peu de travaux, ont, à notre connaissance, porté sur l’utilisation du paraphrasage contextuel dans le cadre de l’aide à la rédaction. Max et Zock (2008) présentent une méthode proposant aux rédacteurs des paraphrases sous-phrastiques candidates pour les segments qu’ils souhaitent reformuler. L’approche utilisée pour la génération des paraphrases est fondée sur l’équivalence de traduction (Bannard et Callison-Burch, 2005). Les travaux de Bernstein et al. (2010) portent eux sur l’externalisation de diverses tâches d’édition de texte, dont la révision, via le crowdsourcing. Par ailleurs, la réécriture d’un texte peut être destinée plus spécifiquement à une application automatique. Dans (Resnik et al., 2010), des reformulations pour des segments jugés difficiles à traduire sont acquises via le crowdsourcing : des contributeurs monolingues de la langue source proposent ainsi des reformulations en contexte pour ces unités 2. Les reformulations collectées sont ensuite utilisées en entrée dans un système de traductio</context>
<context position="11866" citStr="Callison-Burch, 2005" startWordPosition="1730" endWordPosition="1731">(Madnani et Dorr, 2010). Les techniques proposées apparaissent néanmoins assez fortement liées aux types de ressources auxquelles elles s’appliquent. Les types de corpus utilisés pour sont principalement : • des paires de paraphrases d’énoncés (corpus monolingues parallèles), qui permettent d’obtenir des paraphrases précises, mais en faible quantité (Barzilay et McKeown, 2001; Pang et al., 2003; Cohn et al., 2008; Bouamor et al., 2011) ; • des paires d’énoncés en relation de traduction (corpus multilingues parallèles), qui permettent de générer de nombreuses paraphrases candidates (Bannard et Callison-Burch, 2005; Kok et Brockett, 2010) ; • des paires d’énoncés en relation partielle (corpus monolingues parallèles), qui permettent sur le principe d’acquérir de nombreuses paraphrases (Barzilay et Lee, 2003; Pasça et Dienes, 2005; Bhagat et Ravichandran, 2008; Deléger et Zweigenbaum, 2009). Bien que la précision de ces techniques d’acquisition peut se mesurer sur la base d’une référence attendue portant sur une collection de paires d’énoncés (Cohn et al., 2008), il est plus utile de pouvoir la mesurer au travers de la question de substituabilité en contexte, laquelle a déjà été abordée au niveau lexical </context>
<context position="32703" citStr="Callison-Burch, 2005" startWordPosition="4905" endWordPosition="4906"> pour l’apprentissage et l’évaluation, nous considérons cette condition comme la plus utile pour l’interprétation des résultats de ces travaux préliminaires. Ici, notre système obtient la meilleur performance, avec un avantage de 6,06 points par rapport à WEBLM. Ceci montre que la seule utilisation d’un modèle de langue, aussi bien estimé soit-il, est trop limitée pour rendre compte correctement de l’ensemble des phénomènes de paraphrases présents dans notre corpus d’évaluation, ce qui confirme des résultats précédents où les modèles de langue n’étaient pas issus de comptes du Web (Bannard et Callison-Burch, 2005). Finalement, la figure 4 détaille les performances atteintes par chacune des méthodes d’acquisition de paraphrases pour chacune des 3 conditions. Il n’est tout d’abord pas surprenant que les reformulations extraites de WICOPACO soient largement identifiées comme de bonnes paraphrases en contexte, en particulier dans les conditions POSSIBLES et SÛRES++. Ces paraphrases sont le résultat de reformulations par des contributeurs de Wikipédia dans le contexte d’évaluation, et avaient déjà été reconnues comme telles par une première annotatrice. WICOPACO HUMAIN PIVOTES PIVOTZH POSSIBLES 89,33 67,00 </context>
</contexts>
<marker>Callison-Burch, 2005</marker>
<rawString>16. Bannard et Callison-Burch (2005) ont montré que l’utilisation simultanée de plusieurs langues pivots permettait de diminuer de façon importante les phénomènes de bruit.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>R et RAVICHANDRAN BHAGAT</author>
<author>D</author>
</authors>
<title>Large scale acquisition of paraphrases for learning surface patterns.</title>
<date>2008</date>
<booktitle>In Actes de ACL-HLT,</booktitle>
<location>Columbus, États-Unis.</location>
<marker>BHAGAT, D, 2008</marker>
<rawString>BHAGAT, R. et RAVICHANDRAN, D. (2008). Large scale acquisition of paraphrases for learning surface patterns. In Actes de ACL-HLT, Columbus, États-Unis.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>H BOUAMOR</author>
<author>A et VILNAT MAX</author>
<author>A</author>
</authors>
<title>Monolingual alignment by edit rate computation on sentential paraphrase pairs.</title>
<date>2011</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of ACL, Short Papers session,</booktitle>
<location>Portland, USA.</location>
<marker>BOUAMOR, MAX, A, 2011</marker>
<rawString>BOUAMOR, H., MAX, A. et VILNAT, A. (2011). Monolingual alignment by edit rate computation on sentential paraphrase pairs. In Proceedings of ACL, Short Papers session, Portland, USA.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>C et DOLAN BROCKETT</author>
<author>W B</author>
</authors>
<title>Support vector machines for paraphrase identification and corpus construction.</title>
<date>2005</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of The 3rd International Workshop on Paraphrasing IWP, Jeju Island,</booktitle>
<location>South</location>
<marker>BROCKETT, B, 2005</marker>
<rawString>BROCKETT, C. et DOLAN, W. B. (2005). Support vector machines for paraphrase identification and corpus construction. In Proceedings of The 3rd International Workshop on Paraphrasing IWP, Jeju Island, South Korea.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>M CANDITO</author>
<author>B et DENIS CRABBÉ</author>
<author>P</author>
</authors>
<title>Statistical French dependency parsing : treebank conversion and first results.</title>
<date>2010</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of LREC,</booktitle>
<location>Valletta,</location>
<marker>CANDITO, CRABBÉ, P, 2010</marker>
<rawString>CANDITO, M., CRABBÉ, B. et DENIS, P. (2010). Statistical French dependency parsing : treebank conversion and first results. In Proceedings of LREC, Valletta, Malta.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>C-C et LIN CHANG</author>
<author>C-J</author>
</authors>
<title>LIBSVM : a library for support vector machines. Software available at http://www.csie.ntu.edu.tw/~cjlin/libsvm.</title>
<date>2001</date>
<marker>CHANG, C-J, 2001</marker>
<rawString>CHANG, C.-C. et LIN, C.-J. (2001). LIBSVM : a library for support vector machines. Software available at http://www.csie.ntu.edu.tw/~cjlin/libsvm.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>T COHN</author>
<author>C et LAPATA CALLISON-BURCH</author>
<author>M</author>
</authors>
<title>Constructing corpora for the development and evaluation of paraphrase systems.</title>
<date>2008</date>
<journal>Comput. Linguist.,</journal>
<volume>34</volume>
<issue>4</issue>
<marker>COHN, CALLISON-BURCH, M, 2008</marker>
<rawString>COHN, T., CALLISON-BURCH, C. et LAPATA, M. (2008). Constructing corpora for the development and evaluation of paraphrase systems. Comput. Linguist., 34(4).</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>T et LAPATA COHN</author>
<author>M</author>
</authors>
<title>Sentence compression beyond word deletion.</title>
<date>2008</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the 22nd International Conference on Computational Linguistics (Coling</booktitle>
<location>Manchester, UK.</location>
<marker>COHN, M, 2008</marker>
<rawString>COHN, T. et LAPATA, M. (2008). Sentence compression beyond word deletion. In Proceedings of the 22nd International Conference on Computational Linguistics (Coling 2008), Manchester, UK.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>M et ROTH CONNOR</author>
<author>D</author>
</authors>
<title>Context sensitive paraphrasing with a single unsupervised classifier.</title>
<date>2007</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of ECML,</booktitle>
<location>Warsaw, Poland.</location>
<marker>CONNOR, D, 2007</marker>
<rawString>CONNOR, M. et ROTH, D. (2007). Context sensitive paraphrasing with a single unsupervised classifier. In Proceedings of ECML, Warsaw, Poland.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>L et ZWEIGENBAUM DELÉGER</author>
<author>P</author>
</authors>
<title>Extracting lay paraphrases of specialized expressions from monolingual comparable medical corpora.</title>
<date>2009</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the 2nd Workshop on Building and Using Comparable Corpora : from Parallel to Non-parallel Corpora,</booktitle>
<marker>DELÉGER, P, 2009</marker>
<rawString>DELÉGER, L. et ZWEIGENBAUM, P. (2009). Extracting lay paraphrases of specialized expressions from monolingual comparable medical corpora. In Proceedings of the 2nd Workshop on Building and Using Comparable Corpora : from Parallel to Non-parallel Corpora, Singapore.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>C DUTREY</author>
<author>H BOUAMOR</author>
<author>D et MAX BERNHARD</author>
<author>A</author>
</authors>
<title>Paraphrases et modifications locales dans l’historique des révisions de wikipédia.</title>
<date>2011</date>
<booktitle>In Actes de TALN 2011,</booktitle>
<location>Montpellier, France.</location>
<marker>DUTREY, BOUAMOR, BERNHARD, A, 2011</marker>
<rawString>DUTREY, C., BOUAMOR, H., BERNHARD, D. et MAX, A. (2011). Paraphrases et modifications locales dans l’historique des révisions de wikipédia. In Actes de TALN 2011, Montpellier, France.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>J GANITKEVITCH</author>
<author>C CALLISON-BURCH</author>
<author>C et VAN DURME NAPOLES</author>
<author>B</author>
</authors>
<title>Learning sentential paraphrases from bilingual parallel corpora for text-to-text generation.</title>
<date>2011</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of EMNLP,</booktitle>
<location>Edinburgh, UK.</location>
<marker>GANITKEVITCH, CALLISON-BURCH, NAPOLES, B, 2011</marker>
<rawString>GANITKEVITCH, J., CALLISON-BURCH, C., NAPOLES, C. et VAN DURME, B. (2011). Learning sentential paraphrases from bilingual parallel corpora for text-to-text generation. In Proceedings of EMNLP, Edinburgh, UK.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>S et BROCKETT KOK</author>
<author>C</author>
</authors>
<title>Hitting the Right Paraphrases in Good Time.</title>
<date>2010</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of NAACL,</booktitle>
<location>Los Angeles, USA.</location>
<marker>KOK, C, 2010</marker>
<rawString>KOK, S. et BROCKETT, C. (2010). Hitting the Right Paraphrases in Good Time. In Proceedings of NAACL, Los Angeles, USA.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>J et KOCH LANDIS</author>
<author>G</author>
</authors>
<title>The measurement of observer agreement for categorical data.</title>
<date>1977</date>
<journal>Biometrics,</journal>
<pages>159--174</pages>
<marker>LANDIS, G, 1977</marker>
<rawString>LANDIS, J. et KOCH, G. (1977). The measurement of observer agreement for categorical data. Biometrics, pages 159–174.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>M et KELLER LAPATA</author>
<author>F</author>
</authors>
<title>Web-based Models for Natural Language Processing.</title>
<date>2005</date>
<journal>ACM Transactions on Speech and Language Processing,</journal>
<volume>2</volume>
<issue>1</issue>
<marker>LAPATA, F, 2005</marker>
<rawString>LAPATA, M. et KELLER, F. (2005). Web-based Models for Natural Language Processing. ACM Transactions on Speech and Language Processing, 2(1):1–31.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>N et DORR MADNANI</author>
<author>B J</author>
</authors>
<title>Generating Phrasal and Sentential Paraphrases : A Survey of Data-Driven Methods .</title>
<date>2010</date>
<journal>Computational Linguistics,</journal>
<volume>36</volume>
<issue>3</issue>
<marker>MADNANI, J, 2010</marker>
<rawString>MADNANI, N. et DORR, B. J. (2010). Generating Phrasal and Sentential Paraphrases : A Survey of Data-Driven Methods . Computational Linguistics, 36(3).</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>N MADNANI</author>
<author>P RESNIK</author>
<author>B et SCHWARTZ DORR</author>
<author>R</author>
</authors>
<title>Are multiple reference translations necessary ? investigating the value of paraphrased reference translations in parameter optimization.</title>
<date>2008</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of AMTA, Waikiki,</booktitle>
<location>Hawai’i.</location>
<marker>MADNANI, RESNIK, DORR, R, 2008</marker>
<rawString>MADNANI, N., RESNIK, P., DORR, B. et SCHWARTZ, R. (2008). Are multiple reference translations necessary ? investigating the value of paraphrased reference translations in parameter optimization. In Proceedings of AMTA, Waikiki, Hawai’i.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>A MAX</author>
</authors>
<title>From controlled document authoring to interactive document normalization.</title>
<date>2004</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of COLING,</booktitle>
<location>Geneva, Switzerland.</location>
<marker>MAX, 2004</marker>
<rawString>MAX, A. (2004). From controlled document authoring to interactive document normalization. In Proceedings of COLING, Geneva, Switzerland.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>A et WISNIEWSKI MAX</author>
<author>G</author>
</authors>
<title>Mining Naturally-occurring Corrections and Paraphrases from Wikipedia’s Revision History.</title>
<date>2010</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of LREC,</booktitle>
<location>Valletta,</location>
<marker>MAX, G, 2010</marker>
<rawString>MAX, A. et WISNIEWSKI, G. (2010). Mining Naturally-occurring Corrections and Paraphrases from Wikipedia’s Revision History. In Proceedings of LREC, Valletta, Malta.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>A et ZOCK MAX</author>
<author>M</author>
</authors>
<title>Looking up phrase rephrasings via a pivot language.</title>
<date>2008</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the COLING Workshop on Cognitive Aspects of the Lexicon,</booktitle>
<location>Manchester, United Kingdom.</location>
<marker>MAX, M, 2008</marker>
<rawString>MAX, A. et ZOCK, M. (2008). Looking up phrase rephrasings via a pivot language. In Proceedings of the COLING Workshop on Cognitive Aspects of the Lexicon, Manchester, United Kingdom.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>D et NAVIGLI MCCARTHY</author>
<author>R</author>
</authors>
<title>The english lexical substitution task.</title>
<date>2009</date>
<journal>Language Resources and Evaluation,</journal>
<volume>43</volume>
<issue>2</issue>
<marker>MCCARTHY, R, 2009</marker>
<rawString>MCCARTHY, D. et NAVIGLI, R. (2009). The english lexical substitution task. Language Resources and Evaluation, 43(2).</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>A MUTTON</author>
</authors>
<title>Evaluation of sentence grammaticality using Parsers and a Support Vector Machine. Thèse de doctorat,</title>
<date>2006</date>
<institution>Macquarie University.</institution>
<marker>MUTTON, 2006</marker>
<rawString>MUTTON, A. (2006). Evaluation of sentence grammaticality using Parsers and a Support Vector Machine. Thèse de doctorat, Macquarie University.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>T ONISHI</author>
<author>M et SUMITA UTIYAMA</author>
<author>E</author>
</authors>
<title>Paraphrase lattice for statistical machine translation.</title>
<date>2010</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the ACL 2010 Conference, Short Paper session,</booktitle>
<location>Uppsala,</location>
<marker>ONISHI, UTIYAMA, E, 2010</marker>
<rawString>ONISHI, T., UTIYAMA, M. et SUMITA, E. (2010). Paraphrase lattice for statistical machine translation. In Proceedings of the ACL 2010 Conference, Short Paper session, Uppsala, Sweden.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>B PANG</author>
<author>K et MARCU KNIGHT</author>
<author>D</author>
</authors>
<title>Syntax-based alignement of multiple translations : Extracting paraphrases and generating new sentences.</title>
<date>2003</date>
<booktitle>In Actes de NAACL-HLT,</booktitle>
<location>Edmonton, Canada.</location>
<marker>PANG, KNIGHT, D, 2003</marker>
<rawString>PANG, B., KNIGHT, K. et MARCU, D. (2003). Syntax-based alignement of multiple translations : Extracting paraphrases and generating new sentences. In Actes de NAACL-HLT, Edmonton, Canada.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>M et DIENES PASÇA</author>
<author>P</author>
</authors>
<title>Aligning Needles in a Haystack : Paraphrase Acquisition Across the Web. In</title>
<date>2005</date>
<booktitle>Proceedings of IJCNLP, Jeju Island,</booktitle>
<location>South</location>
<marker>PASÇA, P, 2005</marker>
<rawString>PASÇA, M. et DIENES, P. (2005). Aligning Needles in a Haystack : Paraphrase Acquisition Across the Web. In Proceedings of IJCNLP, Jeju Island, South Korea.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>S et KLEIN PETROV</author>
<author>D</author>
</authors>
<title>Improved inference for unlexicalized parsing.</title>
<date>2007</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of NAACL-HLT,</booktitle>
<location>Rochester, USA.</location>
<marker>PETROV, D, 2007</marker>
<rawString>PETROV, S. et KLEIN, D. (2007). Improved inference for unlexicalized parsing. In Proceedings of NAACL-HLT, Rochester, USA.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>C QUIRK</author>
<author>C et DOLAN BROCKETT</author>
<author>W B</author>
</authors>
<title>Monolingual machine translation for paraphrase generation.</title>
<date>2004</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of EMNLP,</booktitle>
<volume>149</volume>
<location>Barcelona,</location>
<marker>QUIRK, BROCKETT, B, 2004</marker>
<rawString>QUIRK, C., BROCKETT, C. et DOLAN, W. B. (2004). Monolingual machine translation for paraphrase generation. In Proceedings of EMNLP, volume 149, Barcelona, Spain.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>P RESNIK</author>
<author>O BUZEK</author>
<author>C HU</author>
<author>Y KRONROD</author>
<author>A et BEDERSON QUINN</author>
<author>B B</author>
</authors>
<title>Improving translation via targeted paraphrasing.</title>
<date>2010</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the 2010 Conference on Empirical Methods in Natural Language Processing,</booktitle>
<location>Cambridge, MA.</location>
<marker>RESNIK, BUZEK, HU, KRONROD, QUINN, B, 2010</marker>
<rawString>RESNIK, P., BUZEK, O., HU, C., KRONROD, Y., QUINN, A. et BEDERSON, B. B. (2010). Improving translation via targeted paraphrasing. In Proceedings of the 2010 Conference on Empirical Methods in Natural Language Processing, Cambridge, MA.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>H SCHMID</author>
</authors>
<title>Probabilistic part-of-speech tagging using decision trees.</title>
<date>1994</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of International Conference on New Methods in Language Processing,</booktitle>
<location>Manchester, UK.</location>
<marker>SCHMID, 1994</marker>
<rawString>SCHMID, H. (1994). Probabilistic part-of-speech tagging using decision trees. In Proceedings of International Conference on New Methods in Language Processing, Manchester, UK.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>J SCHROEDER</author>
<author>T et KOEHN COHN</author>
<author>P</author>
</authors>
<title>Word Lattices for Multi-Source Translation.</title>
<date>2009</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of EACL,</booktitle>
<location>Athens, Greece.</location>
<marker>SCHROEDER, COHN, P, 2009</marker>
<rawString>SCHROEDER, J., COHN, T. et KOEHN, P. (2009). Word Lattices for Multi-Source Translation. In Proceedings of EACL, Athens, Greece.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>M SNOVER</author>
<author>N MADNANI</author>
<author>B J et SCHWARTZ DORR</author>
<author>R</author>
</authors>
<title>TER-Plus : paraphrase, semantic, and alignment enhancements to Translation Edit Rate.</title>
<date>2010</date>
<journal>Machine Translation,</journal>
<pages>23--2</pages>
<marker>SNOVER, MADNANI, DORR, R, 2010</marker>
<rawString>SNOVER, M., MADNANI, N., DORR, B. J. et SCHWARTZ, R. (2010). TER-Plus : paraphrase, semantic, and alignment enhancements to Translation Edit Rate. Machine Translation, 23(2-3).</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>K WANG</author>
<author>C THRASHER</author>
<author>E VIEGAS</author>
<author>X et HSU LI</author>
<author>P B-j</author>
</authors>
<title>An Overview of Microsoft Web N-gram Corpus and Applications.</title>
<date>2010</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the NAACL-HLT Demonstration Session,</booktitle>
<location>Los Angeles, USA.</location>
<marker>WANG, THRASHER, VIEGAS, LI, B-j, 2010</marker>
<rawString>WANG, K., THRASHER, C., VIEGAS, E., LI, X. et HSU, B.-j. P. (2010). An Overview of Microsoft Web N-gram Corpus and Applications. In Proceedings of the NAACL-HLT Demonstration Session, Los Angeles, USA.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>S ZHAO</author>
<author>X LAN</author>
<author>T et LI LIU</author>
<author>S</author>
</authors>
<title>Application-driven Statistical Paraphrase Generation.</title>
<date>2009</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the Joint Conference of the 47th Annual Meeting of the ACL and the 4th International Joint Conference on Natural Language Processing of the AFNLP,</booktitle>
<location>Suntec, Singapore.</location>
<marker>ZHAO, LAN, LIU, S, 2009</marker>
<rawString>ZHAO, S., LAN, X., LIU, T. et LI, S. (2009). Application-driven Statistical Paraphrase Generation. In Proceedings of the Joint Conference of the 47th Annual Meeting of the ACL and the 4th International Joint Conference on Natural Language Processing of the AFNLP, Suntec, Singapore.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>S ZHAO</author>
<author>T LIU</author>
<author>X YUAN</author>
<author>S et ZHANG LI</author>
<author>Y</author>
</authors>
<title>Automatic acquisition of context-specific lexical paraphrases.</title>
<date>2007</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of IJCAI,</booktitle>
<location>Hyderabad, India.</location>
<marker>ZHAO, LIU, YUAN, LI, Y, 2007</marker>
<rawString>ZHAO, S., LIU, T., YUAN, X., LI, S. et ZHANG, Y. (2007). Automatic acquisition of context-specific lexical paraphrases. In Proceedings of IJCAI, Hyderabad, India.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>S ZHAO</author>
<author>H WANG</author>
<author>T LIU</author>
<author>et LI</author>
<author>S</author>
</authors>
<title>Leveraging multiple mt engines for paraphrase generation.</title>
<date>2010</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of COLING,</booktitle>
<location>Beijing, China.</location>
<marker>ZHAO, WANG, LIU, LI, S, 2010</marker>
<rawString>ZHAO, S., WANG, H., LIU, T., et LI, S. (2010). Leveraging multiple mt engines for paraphrase generation. In Proceedings of COLING, Beijing, China.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Z ZHU</author>
<author>D et GUREVYCH BERNHARD</author>
<author>I</author>
</authors>
<title>A monolingual tree-based translation model for sentence simplification.</title>
<date>2010</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of COLING,</booktitle>
<location>Beijing, China.</location>
<marker>ZHU, BERNHARD, I, 2010</marker>
<rawString>ZHU, Z., BERNHARD, D. et GUREVYCH, I. (2010). A monolingual tree-based translation model for sentence simplification. In Proceedings of COLING, Beijing, China.</rawString>
</citation>
</citationList>
</algorithm>
</algorithms>