<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<algorithms version="110505">
<algorithm name="ParsCit" version="110505">
<citationList>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Références C PAICE ET G HUSK</author>
</authors>
<title>Towards the automatic recognition of anaphoric features in English text: the impersonal pronoun it. Computer Speech and Language.</title>
<date>1987</date>
<marker>HUSK, 1987</marker>
<rawString>Références C. PAICE ET G. HUSK (1987). Towards the automatic recognition of anaphoric features in English text: the impersonal pronoun it. Computer Speech and Language.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>D WEISSENBACHER ET A NAZARENKO</author>
</authors>
<title>A bayesian classifier for the recognition of the impersonal occurrences of the it pronoun.</title>
<date>2007</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of DAARC’07,</booktitle>
<marker>NAZARENKO, 2007</marker>
<rawString>D. WEISSENBACHER ET A. NAZARENKO (2007). A bayesian classifier for the recognition of the impersonal occurrences of the it pronoun. In Proceedings of DAARC’07, 2007.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>S LAPPIN ET H LEASS</author>
</authors>
<title>An algorithm for pronominal anaphora resolution,</title>
<date>1994</date>
<journal>Computational Linguistics,</journal>
<volume>20</volume>
<issue>4</issue>
<pages>535--561</pages>
<marker>LEASS, 1994</marker>
<rawString>S. LAPPIN ET H. LEASS (1994). An algorithm for pronominal anaphora resolution, Computational Linguistics, 20(4), 1994, p. 535–561.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>S MEZGHANI HAMMAMI</author>
<author>L HADRICH BELGUITH R SELLAMI</author>
</authors>
<title>A Bayesian Classifier for the Identification of Non-referential Pronouns</title>
<date>2010</date>
<booktitle>in Arabic. The 7th INFOS</booktitle>
<marker>HAMMAMI, SELLAMI, 2010</marker>
<rawString>S. MEZGHANI HAMMAMI., R.SELLAMI, L. HADRICH BELGUITH (2010). A Bayesian Classifier for the Identification of Non-referential Pronouns in Arabic. The 7th INFOS 2010.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>S HAMMAMI</author>
<author>L BELGUITH</author>
<author>A BEN HAMADOU</author>
</authors>
<title>A Rule-Based Method for Detecting Arabic Anaphoric Pronouns.</title>
<date>2009</date>
<booktitle>Proceedings of the 7th DAARC’2009, Goa-India,</booktitle>
<marker>HAMMAMI, BELGUITH, HAMADOU, 2009</marker>
<rawString>S. HAMMAMI, L. BELGUITH, A. BEN HAMADOU (2009). A Rule-Based Method for Detecting Arabic Anaphoric Pronouns. Proceedings of the 7th DAARC’2009, Goa-India, 2009.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>R EVANS</author>
</authors>
<title>Applying machine learning toward an automatic classiϧcation of it.</title>
<date>2001</date>
<booktitle>Literary and linguistic computing,</booktitle>
<volume>16</volume>
<pages>45--57</pages>
<marker>EVANS, 2001</marker>
<rawString>R. EVANS (2001). Applying machine learning toward an automatic classiϧcation of it. Literary and linguistic computing, 16, 2001, p. 45–57.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>M DENBER</author>
</authors>
<title>Automatic resolution of anaphora in English. Eastman Kodak Co,</title>
<date>1998</date>
<marker>DENBER, 1998</marker>
<rawString>M. DENBER (1998). Automatic resolution of anaphora in English. Eastman Kodak Co, 1998.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>M ABDUL-MAGEED</author>
</authors>
<title>Automatic detection of Arabic non-anaphoric pronouns for improving anaphora resolution.</title>
<date>2011</date>
<journal>Asian Lang. Inform.</journal>
<location>Process.</location>
<marker>ABDUL-MAGEED, 2011</marker>
<rawString>ABDUL-MAGEED, M. 2011. Automatic detection of Arabic non-anaphoric pronouns for improving anaphora resolution. Asian Lang. Inform. Process. (March 2011).</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>S BERGSMA</author>
<author>D LIN ET R GOEBEL</author>
</authors>
<date>2008</date>
<booktitle>Distributional Identification of Non-Referential Pronouns. ACL,</booktitle>
<pages>10--18</pages>
<location>Columbus Ohio,</location>
<marker>BERGSMA, GOEBEL, 2008</marker>
<rawString>S. BERGSMA, D. LIN ET R. GOEBEL (2008). Distributional Identification of Non-Referential Pronouns. ACL, Columbus Ohio, 2008, p. 10-18.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>A BOYD</author>
<author>W GEGG-HARRISON ET D BYRON</author>
</authors>
<title>Identifying non-referential it: a machine learning approach incorporating linguistically motivated features.</title>
<date>2005</date>
<booktitle>Workshop on Feature Engineering for Machine Learning in Natural Language Processing,</booktitle>
<marker>BOYD, BYRON, 2005</marker>
<rawString>A. BOYD, W. GEGG-HARRISON ET D. BYRON (2005). Identifying non-referential it: a machine learning approach incorporating linguistically motivated features. Workshop on Feature Engineering for Machine Learning in Natural Language Processing, 2005.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>C</author>
</authors>
<title>MÜLLER (2007).Resolving It, This, and That in Unrestricted Multi-Party Dialog.</title>
<date>2007</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the 45th Annual Meeting of the Association of Computational Linguistics,</booktitle>
<marker>C, 2007</marker>
<rawString>C. MÜLLER (2007).Resolving It, This, and That in Unrestricted Multi-Party Dialog. In Proceedings of the 45th Annual Meeting of the Association of Computational Linguistics, 2007.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>D BYRON</author>
</authors>
<title>Resolving Pronominal Reference to Abstrac Entities.</title>
<date>2002</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of th 40th Annual Meeting of the Association of Computation Linguistics (ACL),</booktitle>
<location>Philadelphia</location>
<marker>BYRON, 2002</marker>
<rawString>D. BYRON (2002). Resolving Pronominal Reference to Abstrac Entities. In Proceedings of th 40th Annual Meeting of the Association of Computation Linguistics (ACL), Philadelphia 2002.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>C NAVARETTA</author>
</authors>
<title>Automatic Recognition of the Function of Singular Neuter</title>
<date>2009</date>
<booktitle>Pronouns in Texts and Spoken Data. In DAARC</booktitle>
<marker>NAVARETTA, 2009</marker>
<rawString>C. NAVARETTA (2009). Automatic Recognition of the Function of Singular Neuter Pronouns in Texts and Spoken Data. In DAARC 2009.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>N PRAKASH</author>
<author>S KAUSHIK</author>
</authors>
<title>Probabilistic neural network approach to the classification of demonstrative pronouns for indirect anaphora in</title>
<date>2010</date>
<booktitle>Hindi. International Journal Information Technology and Intelligent Computing,</booktitle>
<marker>PRAKASH, KAUSHIK, 2010</marker>
<rawString>K. DUTTA , N. PRAKASH, S. KAUSHIK (2010). Probabilistic neural network approach to the classification of demonstrative pronouns for indirect anaphora in Hindi. International Journal Information Technology and Intelligent Computing, 2010.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>N CHAÂBEN KAMMOUN</author>
<author>L HADRICH BELGUITH ET A BEN HAMADOU</author>
</authors>
<title>The MORPH2 new version: A robust morphological analyzer for Arabic texts.</title>
<date>2010</date>
<pages>2010</pages>
<marker>KAMMOUN, HAMADOU, 2010</marker>
<rawString>N. CHAÂBEN KAMMOUN, L. HADRICH BELGUITH ET A. BEN HAMADOU (2010). The MORPH2 new version: A robust morphological analyzer for Arabic texts. JADT’2010.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>E FRANK</author>
<author>IAN H WITTEN</author>
</authors>
<date>2005</date>
<booktitle>Practical Machine Learning Tools and Techniques, Second Edition.</booktitle>
<publisher>Morgan Kaufmann</publisher>
<note>series in data management systems).</note>
<marker>FRANK, WITTEN, 2005</marker>
<rawString>E. FRANK, IAN H. WITTEN (2005). Practical Machine Learning Tools and Techniques, Second Edition. (Morgan Kaufmann series in data management systems).</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>L BELGUITH</author>
<author>L BACCOUR</author>
<author>G MOURAD</author>
</authors>
<title>Segmentation de textes arabes basée sur l&apos;analyse contextuelle des signes de ponctuations et de certaines particules (TALN’2005).</title>
<date>2005</date>
<marker>BELGUITH, BACCOUR, MOURAD, 2005</marker>
<rawString>BELGUITH, L., BACCOUR, L. AND MOURAD, G. (2005). Segmentation de textes arabes basée sur l&apos;analyse contextuelle des signes de ponctuations et de certaines particules (TALN’2005).</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>MITKOV R Mitkov</author>
</authors>
<title>Anaphora resolution».</title>
<date>2002</date>
<location>Longman.</location>
<contexts>
<context position="7313" citStr="Mitkov, 2002" startWordPosition="1006" endWordPosition="1007"> sont considérés comme démonstratifs, et qui désignent le temps (كاذنیح/Hyn*Ak/, كاذنأ/On*Ak/) et le lieu (انھ/hnA/, كانھ/hnAkA/, كلانھ/hnAlkA/, انھھ/hhnA/, مَّ ث/vm~/). D’après notre étude statistique, il y a des pronoms qui sont utilisés beaucoup plus que d’autres tels que les pronoms اذھ/h*A/، كلت/tlk/, هذھ/h*h/، كلذ/*lk/. L’utilisation des pronoms démonstratifs (*lkmA/امكلذ, *lkm/مكلذ, tlkmA/امكلت, *lkn/نكلذ) est presque négligeable (ils apparaissent dans le saint coran ou dans les anciens livres arabes). 3 Travaux antérieurs L’anaphore pronominale est le type d’anaphore le plus fréquent (Mitkov, 2002), c’est pourquoi la résolution automatique des pronoms est un domaine de recherche qui a suscité énormément d&apos;attention depuis plusieurs années. Un système de résolution des anaphores pronominales doit être capable de distinguer les occurrences des pronoms non-référentielles de celles référentielles avant de s&apos;attaquer à leur résolution. De nombreux travaux se sont intéressés particulièrement à cette étape vue son importance et sa difficulté. La plus part des chercheurs se sont intéressés aux pronoms personnels. Nous pouvons distinguer trois types d’approches : une approche à base de règles te</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Mitkov, 2002</marker>
<rawString>MITKOV (2002): R. Mitkov, «Anaphora resolution». Longman. 2002.</rawString>
</citation>
</citationList>
</algorithm>
</algorithms>