<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<algorithms version="110505">
<algorithm name="ParsCit" version="110505">
<citationList>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Références ABDULJALEEL</author>
<author>N et LARKEY</author>
<author>L</author>
</authors>
<title>Statistical transliteration for English-Arabic Cross Language Information Retrieval.</title>
<date>2003</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the Twelfth ACM International Conference on Information and Knowledge Management,</booktitle>
<pages>139--146</pages>
<location>New Orleans, Louisiana,</location>
<marker>ABDULJALEEL, LARKEY, L, 2003</marker>
<rawString>Références ABDULJALEEL, N. et LARKEY, L. (2003). Statistical transliteration for English-Arabic Cross Language Information Retrieval. In Proceedings of the Twelfth ACM International Conference on Information and Knowledge Management, New Orleans, Louisiana, pages 139–146.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>M ALGHAMDI</author>
</authors>
<title>Alghorithms for Romanizing Arabic names.</title>
<date>2005</date>
<journal>In Journal of King Saud University: Computer Sciences and Information, n°</journal>
<volume>17</volume>
<pages>1--27</pages>
<location>Riyadh,</location>
<marker>ALGHAMDI, 2005</marker>
<rawString>ALGHAMDI, M. (2005). Alghorithms for Romanizing Arabic names. In Journal of King Saud University: Computer Sciences and Information, n° 17, 2005, Riyadh, pages 1–27.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>A ALSALMAN</author>
<author>M ALGHAMDI</author>
<author>K et ALSUBAI ALHUQAYL</author>
<author>S</author>
</authors>
<title>Romanization System for Arabic Names.</title>
<date>2007</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of The First International Symposium on Computer and Arabic Language (ISCAL – 07),</booktitle>
<pages>214--227</pages>
<location>Riyadh,</location>
<marker>ALSALMAN, ALGHAMDI, ALHUQAYL, S, 2007</marker>
<rawString>ALSALMAN, A., ALGHAMDI, M., ALHUQAYL, K. et ALSUBAI, S. (2007). Romanization System for Arabic Names. In Proceedings of The First International Symposium on Computer and Arabic Language (ISCAL – 07), Riyadh, pages 214–227.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>M BARKAT-DEFRADAS</author>
<author>R et PELLEGRINO HAMDI</author>
<author>F</author>
</authors>
<title>De la caractérisation linguistique à l’identification automatique des dialectes arabes.</title>
<date>2004</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of MIDL</booktitle>
<marker>BARKAT-DEFRADAS, HAMDI, F, 2004</marker>
<rawString>BARKAT-DEFRADAS, M., HAMDI, R. et PELLEGRINO, F. (2004). De la caractérisation linguistique à l’identification automatique des dialectes arabes. In Proceedings of MIDL 2004.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>R BESANÇON</author>
<author>G DE CHALENDAR</author>
<author>O FERRET</author>
<author>F GARA</author>
<author>M LAIB</author>
<author>O et SEMMAR MESNARD</author>
<author>N</author>
</authors>
<title>Lima: A multilingual framework for linguistic analysis and linguistic resources development and evaluation.</title>
<date>2010</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of LREC</booktitle>
<marker>BESANÇON, DE CHALENDAR, FERRET, GARA, LAIB, MESNARD, N, 2010</marker>
<rawString>BESANÇON, R., DE CHALENDAR, G., FERRET, O., GARA, F., LAIB, M., MESNARD, O. et SEMMAR, N. (2010). Lima: A multilingual framework for linguistic analysis and linguistic resources development and evaluation. In Proceedings of LREC 2010, Malta.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>M GUIDERE</author>
</authors>
<title>Le traitement de la parole et la détection des dialectes arabes.</title>
<date>2004</date>
<booktitle>In Langues stratégiques et défense nationale, Publications du CREC, Saint-Cyr,</booktitle>
<pages>53--75</pages>
<marker>GUIDERE, 2004</marker>
<rawString>GUIDERE, M. (2004). Le traitement de la parole et la détection des dialectes arabes. In Langues stratégiques et défense nationale, Publications du CREC, Saint-Cyr, pages 53–75.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>K et GRAEHL KNIGHT</author>
<author>J</author>
</authors>
<title>Machine transliteration.</title>
<date>1997</date>
<journal>In Journal version Computational Linguistics,</journal>
<volume>24</volume>
<issue>4</issue>
<pages>599--612</pages>
<marker>KNIGHT, J, 1997</marker>
<rawString>KNIGHT, K. et GRAEHL, J. (1997). Machine transliteration. In Journal version Computational Linguistics, 24(4), 1997, pages 599–612.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="false">
<authors>
<author>P KOEHN</author>
<author>H HOANG</author>
<author>A BIRCH</author>
<author>C CALLISON-BURCH</author>
<author>M FEDERICO</author>
<author>N BERTOLDI</author>
<author>B COWAN</author>
<author>W SHEN</author>
<author>C MORGAN</author>
<author>R ZENS</author>
<author>C DYER</author>
<author>O BOJAR</author>
<author>A et HERBST CONSTANTIN</author>
<author>E</author>
</authors>
<marker>KOEHN, HOANG, BIRCH, CALLISON-BURCH, FEDERICO, BERTOLDI, COWAN, SHEN, MORGAN, ZENS, DYER, BOJAR, CONSTANTIN, E, </marker>
<rawString>KOEHN, P., HOANG, H., BIRCH, A., CALLISON-BURCH, C., FEDERICO, M., BERTOLDI, N., COWAN, B., SHEN, W., MORGAN, C., ZENS, R., DYER, C., BOJAR, O., CONSTANTIN, A. et HERBST, E.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<title>Moses: Open source toolkit for statistical machine translation.</title>
<date>2007</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of ACL 2007, demo session,</booktitle>
<location>Prague.</location>
<marker>2007</marker>
<rawString>(2007). Moses: Open source toolkit for statistical machine translation. In Proceedings of ACL 2007, demo session, Prague.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>P et HOANG KOEHN</author>
<author>H</author>
</authors>
<title>Factored Translation Models.</title>
<date>2007</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the Joint Conference on Empirical Methods in Natural Language Processing and Computational Natural Language Learning (ACL</booktitle>
<pages>868--876</pages>
<location>Prague,</location>
<marker>KOEHN, H, 2007</marker>
<rawString>KOEHN, P. et HOANG, H. (2007). Factored Translation Models. In Proceedings of the Joint Conference on Empirical Methods in Natural Language Processing and Computational Natural Language Learning (ACL 2007), Prague, pages 868–876.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>R et PEDERSEN MIHALCEA</author>
<author>T</author>
</authors>
<title>An evaluation exercise for word alignment.</title>
<date>2003</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the Workshop on Building and Using Parallel Texts: Data Driven Machine Translation and Beyond,</booktitle>
<pages>10--10</pages>
<location>Edmonton,</location>
<marker>MIHALCEA, T, 2003</marker>
<rawString>MIHALCEA, R. et PEDERSEN, T. (2003). An evaluation exercise for word alignment. In Proceedings of the Workshop on Building and Using Parallel Texts: Data Driven Machine Translation and Beyond, Edmonton, pages 10–10.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>N et LAIB SEMMAR</author>
<author>M</author>
</authors>
<title>Using a Hybrid Word Alignment Approach for Automatic Construction and Updating of Arabic to French Lexicons.</title>
<date>2010</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of LREC 2010: Workshop on Language Resources and Human Technologies for Semitic Languages,</booktitle>
<marker>SEMMAR, M, 2010</marker>
<rawString>SEMMAR, N. et LAIB, M. (2010). Using a Hybrid Word Alignment Approach for Automatic Construction and Updating of Arabic to French Lexicons. In Proceedings of LREC 2010: Workshop on Language Resources and Human Technologies for Semitic Languages, Malta.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>L et NG SHAO</author>
<author>H T</author>
</authors>
<title>Mining new word translations from comparable corpora.</title>
<date>2004</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the 20th International Conference on Computational Linguistics (COLING’04),</booktitle>
<pages>618--624</pages>
<location>Stroudsburg,</location>
<marker>SHAO, T, 2004</marker>
<rawString>SHAO, L. et NG, H. T. (2004). Mining new word translations from comparable corpora. In Proceedings of the 20th International Conference on Computational Linguistics (COLING’04), Stroudsburg, pages 618–624.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>T et KONDRAK SHERIF</author>
<author>G</author>
</authors>
<title>Bootstrapping a stochastic transducer for Arabic-English transliteration extraction.</title>
<date>2007</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the 45th Annual Meeting of the Association of Computational Linguistics (ACL</booktitle>
<pages>864--871</pages>
<location>Prague,</location>
<marker>SHERIF, G, 2007</marker>
<rawString>SHERIF, T. et KONDRAK, G. (2007). Bootstrapping a stochastic transducer for Arabic-English transliteration extraction. In Proceedings of the 45th Annual Meeting of the Association of Computational Linguistics (ACL 2007), Prague, pages 864–871.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>B et KNIGHT STALLS</author>
<author>K</author>
</authors>
<title>Translating names and technical terms in arabic text.</title>
<date>1998</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the COLING/ACL Workshop on Computational Approches to Semitic Languages,</booktitle>
<location>Montreal.</location>
<marker>STALLS, K, 1998</marker>
<rawString>STALLS, B. et KNIGHT, K . (1998). Translating names and technical terms in arabic text. In Proceedings of the COLING/ACL Workshop on Computational Approches to Semitic Languages, Montreal.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>T TAO</author>
<author>S Y YOON</author>
<author>A FISTER</author>
<author>R et ZHAI SPROAT</author>
<author>C</author>
</authors>
<title>Unsupervised named entity transliteration using temporal and phonetic correlation.</title>
<date>2006</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the Conference on Empirical Methods in Natural Language Processing (EMNLP’06),</booktitle>
<pages>250--257</pages>
<location>Sydney,</location>
<marker>TAO, YOON, FISTER, SPROAT, C, 2006</marker>
<rawString>TAO, T., YOON, S. Y., FISTER, A., SPROAT, R. et ZHAI, C. (2006). Unsupervised named entity transliteration using temporal and phonetic correlation. In Proceedings of the Conference on Empirical Methods in Natural Language Processing (EMNLP’06), Sydney, pages 250–257.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>J VERONIS</author>
<author>O HAMON</author>
<author>C AYACHE</author>
<author>R BELMOUHOUB</author>
<author>O KRAIF</author>
<author>D LAURENT</author>
<author>T M H NGUYEN</author>
<author>N SEMMAR</author>
<author>F et ZAGHOUANI STUCK</author>
<author>W</author>
</authors>
<title>Arcade II Action de recherche concertée sur l’alignement de documents et son évaluation.</title>
<date>2008</date>
<booktitle>In Chapitre 2, Editions Hermès.</booktitle>
<marker>VERONIS, HAMON, AYACHE, BELMOUHOUB, KRAIF, LAURENT, NGUYEN, SEMMAR, STUCK, W, 2008</marker>
<rawString>VERONIS, J., HAMON, O., AYACHE, C., BELMOUHOUB, R., KRAIF, O., LAURENT, D., NGUYEN, T. M. H., SEMMAR, N., STUCK, F. et ZAGHOUANI, W. (2008). Arcade II Action de recherche concertée sur l’alignement de documents et son évaluation. In Chapitre 2, Editions Hermès.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>A O et KNIGHT YASER</author>
<author>K</author>
</authors>
<title>Translating named entities using monolingual and bilingual resources.</title>
<date>2002</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the 40th Annual Meeting of the Association of Computational Linguistics (ACL’02),</booktitle>
<pages>400--408</pages>
<location>Philadelphia,</location>
<marker>YASER, K, 2002</marker>
<rawString>YASER, A. O. et KNIGHT, K. (2002). Translating named entities using monolingual and bilingual resources. In Proceedings of the 40th Annual Meeting of the Association of Computational Linguistics (ACL’02), Philadelphia, pages 400–408.</rawString>
</citation>
</citationList>
</algorithm>
</algorithms>