<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<algorithms version="110505">
<algorithm name="ParsCit" version="110505">
<citationList>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>P ANICK</author>
</authors>
<title>Using terminological feedback for web search refinement: a log-based study,</title>
<date>2003</date>
<booktitle>Proceedings of the 26th annual international ACM SIGIR conference on Research and development in information retrieval,</booktitle>
<location>Toronto, Canada,</location>
<marker>ANICK, 2003</marker>
<rawString>ANICK P., (2003), Using terminological feedback for web search refinement: a log-based study, Proceedings of the 26th annual international ACM SIGIR conference on Research and development in information retrieval, Toronto, Canada, 88–95.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Mohamed Yassine El Amrani</author>
</authors>
<title>Sylvain Delisle et Ismaïl Biskri</title>
<date>2000</date>
<pages>344--363</pages>
<marker>El Amrani, 2000</marker>
<rawString>Mohamed Yassine El Amrani, Sylvain Delisle et Ismaïl Biskri BELLOT P., EL-BÈZE M. (2000), Clustering by means of Unsupervised Decision Trees or Hierarchical and K-means-like Algorithm, Conférence sur la Recherche d&apos;Informations Assistée par Ordinateur, 344−363.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>I BISKRI</author>
<author>S DELISLE</author>
</authors>
<title>Text Classification and Multilinguism: Getting at Words via Ngrams of Characters,</title>
<date>2002</date>
<booktitle>6th World Multiconference on Systemics, (SCI-2002),</booktitle>
<pages>110--115</pages>
<marker>BISKRI, DELISLE, 2002</marker>
<rawString>BISKRI I., DELISLE S., (2002), Text Classification and Multilinguism: Getting at Words via Ngrams of Characters, 6th World Multiconference on Systemics, (SCI-2002), 110−115.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>C CARPINETO</author>
<author>G ROMANO</author>
<author>V GIANNINI</author>
</authors>
<title>Improving Retrieval Feedback with Multiple Term-Ranking Function Combination,</title>
<date>2002</date>
<journal>ACM Transactions on Information Systems (TOIS), Volume</journal>
<volume>20</volume>
<pages>259--290</pages>
<marker>CARPINETO, ROMANO, GIANNINI, 2002</marker>
<rawString>CARPINETO C., ROMANO G., GIANNINI V., (2002), Improving Retrieval Feedback with Multiple Term-Ranking Function Combination, ACM Transactions on Information Systems (TOIS), Volume 20, Issue 3 (July 2002), 259−290.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>M Y EL AMRANI</author>
</authors>
<title>Outils d&apos;assistance à la construction de Webs personnels : Utilisation des traitements des langues naturelles dans l&apos;aide à la reformulation de requêtes,</title>
<date>2001</date>
<booktitle>Actes de la 5e Rencontre des Étudiants Chercheurs en Informatique pour le Traitement Automatique des Langues,</booktitle>
<pages>497--502</pages>
<location>Tours, France,</location>
<marker>EL AMRANI, 2001</marker>
<rawString>EL AMRANI M.Y., (2001), Outils d&apos;assistance à la construction de Webs personnels : Utilisation des traitements des langues naturelles dans l&apos;aide à la reformulation de requêtes, Actes de la 5e Rencontre des Étudiants Chercheurs en Informatique pour le Traitement Automatique des Langues, Tours, France, 497−502.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>M Y EL AMRANI</author>
</authors>
<title>AgeWeb : Les agents personnels d’aide à la recherche documentaire sur le Web, Mémoire de maîtrise en mathématiques et informatique appliquées, Université du Québec à Trois-Rivières,</title>
<date>2003</date>
<location>Trois-Rivières, Canada.</location>
<marker>EL AMRANI, 2003</marker>
<rawString>EL AMRANI M.Y., (2003), AgeWeb : Les agents personnels d’aide à la recherche documentaire sur le Web, Mémoire de maîtrise en mathématiques et informatique appliquées, Université du Québec à Trois-Rivières, Trois-Rivières, Canada.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>M Y EL AMRANI</author>
<author>S DELISLE</author>
<author>I BISKRI</author>
</authors>
<title>Coping with Information Retrieval Problems on the Web: Towards Personal Web Weaver Agents,</title>
<date>2001</date>
<booktitle>International Conference on Artificial Intelligence (IC-AI&apos;2001),</booktitle>
<pages>1225--1231</pages>
<location>Las Vegas, USA,</location>
<marker>EL AMRANI, DELISLE, BISKRI, 2001</marker>
<rawString>EL AMRANI M.Y., DELISLE S., BISKRI I., (2001). Coping with Information Retrieval Problems on the Web: Towards Personal Web Weaver Agents, International Conference on Artificial Intelligence (IC-AI&apos;2001), Las Vegas, USA, 1225−1231.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="false">
<authors>
<author>A HUST</author>
</authors>
<title>Introducing Query Expansion Methods for Collaborative Information Retrieval.</title>
<date>2004</date>
<journal>Lecture Notes in Computer Science. À paraître. (http://www.dfki.uni-kl.de/~hust/publications.html) MCARTHUR R., BRUZA P.D.,</journal>
<booktitle>Proceedings of the Information Doors Workshop (held in conjunction with the ACM Hypertext and Digital Libraries Conferences).</booktitle>
<marker>HUST, 2004</marker>
<rawString>HUST A., (2004). Introducing Query Expansion Methods for Collaborative Information Retrieval. Lecture Notes in Computer Science. À paraître. (http://www.dfki.uni-kl.de/~hust/publications.html) MCARTHUR R., BRUZA P.D., (2000), The Ranking of Query Refinements in Interactive Webbased Retrieval, Proceedings of the Information Doors Workshop (held in conjunction with the ACM Hypertext and Digital Libraries Conferences).</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="false">
<authors>
<author>S M SALVATIERRA</author>
</authors>
<title>Statistical models for classification and discrimination with application to classifying web documents,</title>
<date>1999</date>
<tech>Ph.D. Thesis Proposal,</tech>
<pages>215--228</pages>
<institution>Department of Statistics, Carnegie Mellon University,</institution>
<location>Nantes, France,</location>
<note>http://citeseer.nj.nec.com/306657.html SERRADURA</note>
<marker>SALVATIERRA, 1999</marker>
<rawString>SALVATIERRA S.M. (1999), Statistical models for classification and discrimination with application to classifying web documents, Ph.D. Thesis Proposal, Department of Statistics, Carnegie Mellon University, http://citeseer.nj.nec.com/306657.html SERRADURA L., SLIMANE M., VINCENT N., (2002), Classification semi-automatique de documents Web à l&apos;aide des Chaînes de Markov Cachées, Publication de l’équipe RFAI, Colloque Inforsid 2002, Nantes, France, 215-228.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>L TAMINE</author>
<author>M BOUGHANEM</author>
</authors>
<title>Un Algorithme génétique spécifique à une reformulation multi-requêtes dans un système de recherche d’information,</title>
<date>2001</date>
<journal>Revue Information – Interaction – Intelligence,</journal>
<volume>1</volume>
<pages>3</pages>
<marker>TAMINE, BOUGHANEM, 2001</marker>
<rawString>TAMINE L., BOUGHANEM M. (2001), Un Algorithme génétique spécifique à une reformulation multi-requêtes dans un système de recherche d’information, Revue Information – Interaction – Intelligence, Volume 1, numéro 1, http://www.revue-i3.org.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>N TURENNE</author>
</authors>
<title>Apprentissage statistique pour l’extraction de concepts à partir de textes (Application au filtrage d’informations textuelles), Thèse de doctorat en informatique, Université Louis-Pasteur,</title>
<date>2000</date>
<location>Strasbourg, France.</location>
<marker>TURENNE, 2000</marker>
<rawString>TURENNE N., (2000), Apprentissage statistique pour l’extraction de concepts à partir de textes (Application au filtrage d’informations textuelles), Thèse de doctorat en informatique, Université Louis-Pasteur, Strasbourg, France.</rawString>
</citation>
</citationList>
</algorithm>
</algorithms>