<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<algorithms version="110505">
<algorithm name="ParsCit" version="110505">
<citationList>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>S A&apos;1&apos;t—Mokhtar</author>
<author>Chanod J—P</author>
<author>C Roux</author>
</authors>
<title>Robustness beyond shallowness: incremental dependency parsing,</title>
<date>2002</date>
<booktitle>Special Issue on Robust Methods in Analysis of Natural Language Data,</booktitle>
<volume>8</volume>
<pages>121--144</pages>
<marker>A&apos;1&apos;t—Mokhtar, J—P, Roux, 2002</marker>
<rawString>A&apos;1&apos;t—Mokhtar S., Chanod J—P. and Roux C. (2002), Robustness beyond shallowness: incremental dependency parsing, Special Issue on Robust Methods in Analysis of Natural Language Data, Vol. 8, 121-144.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>C Brun</author>
<author>C Hagege</author>
</authors>
<title>Normalization and Paraphrasing Using Symbolic Methods,</title>
<date>2003</date>
<booktitle>Proceeding of the Second International Workshop on Paraphrasing. ACL 2003,</booktitle>
<pages>129--152</pages>
<publisher>Hermes.</publisher>
<location>Sapporo, Japan Brun</location>
<marker>Brun, Hagege, 2003</marker>
<rawString>Brun C., Hagege C. (2003), Normalization and Paraphrasing Using Symbolic Methods, Proceeding of the Second International Workshop on Paraphrasing. ACL 2003, Sapporo, Japan Brun C., Dymetman M. (2002), Multilinguisme et traitement de l’inforn1ation Re’daction multilingue assiste’e dans le modele MDA, pages 129-152 — T raite’ des sciences et techniques de l ’information. Hermes.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>N Cancedda</author>
</authors>
<title>Text Generation from MUC Templates.</title>
<date>1999</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the 7th European Workshop on Natural Language Generation (EWNLG’99) Marc Dymetman.</booktitle>
<marker>Cancedda, 1999</marker>
<rawString>Cancedda N. (1999), Text Generation from MUC Templates. In Proceedings of the 7th European Workshop on Natural Language Generation (EWNLG’99) Marc Dymetman. 2002. Text authoring, knowledge acquisition and description logics. In Proceedings of Coling 2002, Taiwan.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>A Hartley</author>
<author>D Scott</author>
<author>J Bateman</author>
<author>D Dochev</author>
</authors>
<title>AGILE — A system for Multilingual Generation of Technical Instructions.</title>
<date>2001</date>
<contexts>
<context position="26898" citStr="Hartley et al. 2001" startWordPosition="3795" endWordPosition="3798">la mesure ou plusieurs composantes rentrent en jeu. Nous avons ici choisi d’éValuer dans un premier temps les performances de la premiere partie du traitement (Extraction d’information cible’e). Cette e’Valuation effectuée sur une collection de 30 textes du domaine qui n’ont pas e’té préalablement traite’s par le systeme a donne’ les résultats suivants en terme de precision et de rappel. De part l’approche que Precision Rappel FScore .96 .65 .77 nous avons adopte’e toute l’information extraite apparait nécessairement dans les résumés ﬁnaux. Par ailleurs, nous adoptons les criteres déﬁnis par (Hartley et al. 2001) pour l’éValuation d’une application de generation multilingue et nous pouvons faire les constatations suiVantes: L’acceptabilité des résume’s produites est optimale dans la mesure ou la combinatoire des expressions linguistiques possibles est contr6le’e et prévue a priori dans la grammaire MDA. Pour ces memes raisons le critere de grammaticalité des résume’s obtenus est également optimale. Enﬁn, la notion de couverture est en fait un reﬂet des résultats de la phrase d’extraction d’information, puisque tout prédicat extrait dans la premiere phase aura une realisation en langue naturelle. Le tr</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Hartley, Scott, Bateman, Dochev, 2001</marker>
<rawString>Hartley A., Scott D., Bateman J., Dochev D. (2001), AGILE — A system for Multilingual Generation of Technical Instructions.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>L Kossein</author>
<author>S Beauregard</author>
<author>L Lapalme</author>
</authors>
<title>Using Information Extraction and Natural language Generation to Answer E—n1ail.</title>
<date>2001</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the 5th International Conference on Application of Natural Language to Information Systems.</booktitle>
<location>Versailles, France.</location>
<marker>Kossein, Beauregard, Lapalme, 2001</marker>
<rawString>Kossein L., Beauregard S., Lapalme L. (2001), Using Information Extraction and Natural language Generation to Answer E—n1ail. In Proceedings of the 5th International Conference on Application of Natural Language to Information Systems. Versailles, France.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>C Brun</author>
<author>M Dymetman</author>
<author>V Lux</author>
</authors>
<title>Document structure and multilingual authoring.</title>
<date>2000</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the First International Natural Language Generation Conference (INLG ’2000),</booktitle>
<volume>1</volume>
<pages>.</pages>
<location>Mitzpe Ramon,</location>
<marker>Brun, Dymetman, Lux, 2000</marker>
<rawString>Brun C., Dymetman M., Lux V. (2000), Document structure and multilingual authoring. In Proceedings of the First International Natural Language Generation Conference (INLG ’2000), Mitzpe Ramon, Israel 24-3 1 .</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="false">
<authors>
<author>C Hagege</author>
<author>C Roux</author>
</authors>
<title>Entre syntaxe et sémantique: Normalisation de l’analyse syntaxique en vue de l’amélioration de l’extraction d’inforn1ation a partir de textes. Actes de TALN</title>
<date>2003</date>
<booktitle>Multilingual Sumrnarization by Integrating Linguistic Resources in the MLIS—MUSI Project. Proceedings of the 3rd International Conference on Language Resources and Evaluation (LREC ’02),</booktitle>
<publisher>Cambridge University Press.</publisher>
<location>Batz—sur—Mer, France</location>
<marker>Hagege, Roux, 2003</marker>
<rawString>Hagege C., Roux C. (2003), Entre syntaxe et sémantique: Normalisation de l’analyse syntaxique en vue de l’amélioration de l’extraction d’inforn1ation a partir de textes. Actes de TALN 2003, Batz—sur—Mer, France Lenci, A. Bartolini, R., Calzolari N., Agua A., Buseman S., Cartier E., Chevreau K., Coch J. (2002), Multilingual Sumrnarization by Integrating Linguistic Resources in the MLIS—MUSI Project. Proceedings of the 3rd International Conference on Language Resources and Evaluation (LREC ’02), May 29-31, Las Palmas, Canary Islands, Spain, 2002 Reiter E., Dale R. (2000), Building Natural Language Generation Systems. Studies in Natural Language Processing, Cambridge University Press.</rawString>
</citation>
</citationList>
</algorithm>
</algorithms>