<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<algorithms version="110505">
<algorithm name="ParsCit" version="110505">
<citationList>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>E KRIARAS</author>
</authors>
<title>The New Greek Dictionary,</title>
<date>1996</date>
<booktitle>The Art of Computer Programming, Volume 3: Sorting and Searching,</booktitle>
<publisher>Addison-Wesley,</publisher>
<location>in</location>
<marker>KRIARAS, 1996</marker>
<rawString>KRIARAS E. (1996), The New Greek Dictionary, (in Greek). KNUTH E. (1973), The Art of Computer Programming, Volume 3: Sorting and Searching, Addison-Wesley, Reading, Mass.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>G BABINOTIS</author>
</authors>
<title>The Dictionary of Modern Greek,</title>
<date>1999</date>
<location>(in Greek).</location>
<marker>BABINOTIS, 1999</marker>
<rawString>BABINOTIS G. (1999), The Dictionary of Modern Greek, (in Greek).</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>S A Neurosoft</author>
</authors>
<date>2003</date>
<note>Language tools. WWW site: http://www.neurosoft.gr/download/main.asp. Accesed on 21-Dec-2003.</note>
<contexts>
<context position="11522" citStr="Neurosoft, 2003" startWordPosition="1861" endWordPosition="1862">nings exist in MG (and not in dialects or ancient Greek). An electronic dictionary as a basis for NLP tools: The Greek case Figure 1: LexEdit tool 4 NLP Tools The new language tools that have been deployed are a result of systematic work of three and more years, at research level -in the areas of lexicography and NLP- as well as at the level of development of specialised electronic lexicons and computer systems for checking, correction and text hyphenation. Moreover, they are based on a redesign and reconstruction of the lexicon as was described above. The tools (they can be found at the Web (Neurosoft, 2003) are renewed two times per year. Thus far the following NLP tools have been implemented, based on the lexicon that was described above: a new spelling correction system and a hyphenator for MG. The new spelling correction system includes approximately 90,000 lemmas (over 1,200,000 word forms). It was checked against a corpus of documents with more than 100,000,000 words. At the same time it includes approximately 200,000 English words thus it allows English and Greek spelling checking. The search engine for the suggestions has been improved substantially. A number of new methods for correcting</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Neurosoft, 2003</marker>
<rawString>Neurosoft S.A. (2003). Language tools. WWW site: http://www.neurosoft.gr/download/main.asp. Accesed on 21-Dec-2003.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>M STAMISON-ATMATZIDI</author>
<author>A VAGELATOS</author>
<author>D CHRISTODOULAKIS</author>
</authors>
<title>Teaching English Engineering Terminology in a Hypermedia Environment,</title>
<date>1995</date>
<journal>Computer Assisted Language Learning, An International journal,</journal>
<volume>8</volume>
<pages>2--3</pages>
<marker>STAMISON-ATMATZIDI, VAGELATOS, CHRISTODOULAKIS, 1995</marker>
<rawString>STAMISON-ATMATZIDI M., VAGELATOS A., CHRISTODOULAKIS D. (1995), Teaching English Engineering Terminology in a Hypermedia Environment, Computer Assisted Language Learning, An International journal, vol. 8, n. 2-3.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>G TEGOPOULOS</author>
<author>A FYTRAKIS</author>
</authors>
<title>The Dictionary of Modern Greek,</title>
<date>1993</date>
<location>(in Greek).</location>
<marker>TEGOPOULOS, FYTRAKIS, 1993</marker>
<rawString>TEGOPOULOS G., FYTRAKIS A. (1993), The Dictionary of Modern Greek, (in Greek).</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>A VAGELATOS</author>
<author>T TRIANTOPOULOU</author>
<author>C TSALIDIS</author>
<author>D CHRISTODOULAKIS</author>
</authors>
<title>A spelling Correction System for Modern Greek,</title>
<date>1994</date>
<journal>International Journal on Artificial Intelligence &amp; Tools,</journal>
<volume>3</volume>
<marker>VAGELATOS, TRIANTOPOULOU, TSALIDIS, CHRISTODOULAKIS, 1994</marker>
<rawString>VAGELATOS A., TRIANTOPOULOU T., TSALIDIS C., CHRISTODOULAKIS D. (1994), A spelling Correction System for Modern Greek, International Journal on Artificial Intelligence &amp; Tools, vol. 3, n. 4.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>A VAGELATOS</author>
<author>M STAMISON-ATMATZIDI</author>
<author>TRIADOPOULOU TH</author>
<author>V FARMAKI</author>
<author>D CHRISTODOULAKIS</author>
</authors>
<title>Analysis of the Literary Style of Poet A. Sikelianos - A Computer Based Approach,</title>
<date>1994</date>
<booktitle>CONSENCUS EX MACHINA, Joint International Conference, ALLC-ACH94, Sorbonne,</booktitle>
<location>Paris.</location>
<marker>VAGELATOS, STAMISON-ATMATZIDI, TH, FARMAKI, CHRISTODOULAKIS, 1994</marker>
<rawString>VAGELATOS A., STAMISON-ATMATZIDI M., TRIADOPOULOU TH., FARMAKI V., CHRISTODOULAKIS D. (1994), Analysis of the Literary Style of Poet A. Sikelianos - A Computer Based Approach, CONSENCUS EX MACHINA, Joint International Conference, ALLC-ACH94, Sorbonne, Paris.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>A VAGELATOS</author>
<author>F PELEKI</author>
<author>D CHRISTODOULAKIS</author>
</authors>
<title>Word stemming with the use of a computer, 15th meeting of the linguistic department of the Aristoteleion University of Thessaloniki, Thessaloniki, Greece,</title>
<date>1994</date>
<location>(in Greek).</location>
<marker>VAGELATOS, PELEKI, CHRISTODOULAKIS, 1994</marker>
<rawString>VAGELATOS A., PELEKI F., CHRISTODOULAKIS D. (1994), Word stemming with the use of a computer, 15th meeting of the linguistic department of the Aristoteleion University of Thessaloniki, Thessaloniki, Greece, (in Greek).</rawString>
</citation>
</citationList>
</algorithm>
</algorithms>