<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<algorithms version="110505">
<algorithm name="ParsCit" version="110505">
<citationList>
<citation valid="false">
<title>This material is based upon works supported by the Science Foundation Ireland under Grant No. 02/IN1/ I100. The opinions, findings and conclusions or recommendations expressed in this material are those of the authors and do not necessarily reflect the views of Science Foundation Ireland.</title>
<date>2000</date>
<journal>Références CAHILL L., CARSON-BERNDSEN J. &amp; GAZDAR G.</journal>
<booktitle>In F. V. EYNDE &amp; D. GIBBON, Eds., Lexicon Development for Speech and Natural Language Processing,</booktitle>
<pages>77--114</pages>
<publisher>Kluwer.</publisher>
<location>Dordrecht:</location>
<marker>2000</marker>
<rawString>This material is based upon works supported by the Science Foundation Ireland under Grant No. 02/IN1/ I100. The opinions, findings and conclusions or recommendations expressed in this material are those of the authors and do not necessarily reflect the views of Science Foundation Ireland. Références CAHILL L., CARSON-BERNDSEN J. &amp; GAZDAR G. (2000). Phonologically based lexical knowledge representation. In F. V. EYNDE &amp; D. GIBBON, Eds., Lexicon Development for Speech and Natural Language Processing, p. 77–114. Dordrecht: Kluwer.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>J CARSON-BERNDSEN</author>
<author>R KELLY</author>
</authors>
<title>Automatic induction of multilingual phonotactic resources.</title>
<date>2004</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the 4th International Conference on Language Resources and Evaluation (LREC),</booktitle>
<location>Lisbon.</location>
<marker>CARSON-BERNDSEN, KELLY, 2004</marker>
<rawString>CARSON-BERNDSEN J. &amp; KELLY R. (2004). Automatic induction of multilingual phonotactic resources. In Proceedings of the 4th International Conference on Language Resources and Evaluation (LREC), Lisbon.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>N IDE</author>
</authors>
<title>Encoding linguistic corpora.</title>
<date>1999</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the Sixth Workshop on Very Large Corpora.</booktitle>
<marker>IDE, 1999</marker>
<rawString>IDE N. (1999). Encoding linguistic corpora. In Proceedings of the Sixth Workshop on Very Large Corpora.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>M NEUGEBAUER</author>
<author>S WILSON</author>
</authors>
<title>Phonological treebanks – issues in generation and application.</title>
<date>2004</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the 4th International Conference on Language Resources and Evaluation (LREC),</booktitle>
<location>Lisbon.</location>
<marker>NEUGEBAUER, WILSON, 2004</marker>
<rawString>NEUGEBAUER M. &amp; WILSON S. (2004). Phonological treebanks – issues in generation and application. In Proceedings of the 4th International Conference on Language Resources and Evaluation (LREC), Lisbon.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>C TIBERIUS</author>
<author>R EVANS</author>
</authors>
<title>Phonological feature based multilingual lexical description.</title>
<date>2000</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of Traitement automatique des langues naturelles,</booktitle>
<location>Lausanne.</location>
<marker>TIBERIUS, EVANS, 2000</marker>
<rawString>TIBERIUS C. &amp; EVANS R. (2000). Phonological feature based multilingual lexical description. In Proceedings of Traitement automatique des langues naturelles, Lausanne.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>S WILSON</author>
<author>J CARSON-BERNDSEN</author>
<author>M WALSH</author>
</authors>
<title>Enhancing phonological representations for multilingual speech technology.</title>
<date>2003</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the International Congress of Phonetic Sciences,</booktitle>
<location>Barcelona.</location>
<marker>WILSON, CARSON-BERNDSEN, WALSH, 2003</marker>
<rawString>WILSON S., CARSON-BERNDSEN J. &amp; WALSH M. (2003). Enhancing phonological representations for multilingual speech technology. In Proceedings of the International Congress of Phonetic Sciences, Barcelona.</rawString>
</citation>
</citationList>
</algorithm>
</algorithms>