<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<algorithms version="110505">
<algorithm name="ParsCit" version="110505">
<citationList>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>M CHAROLLES</author>
</authors>
<title>Organisation des discours et segmentation des écrit. In Inscription Spatiale du Langage: structures et processus, IRIT,</title>
<date>2002</date>
<location>Toulouse, France.</location>
<marker>CHAROLLES, 2002</marker>
<rawString>CHAROLLES M. (2002). Organisation des discours et segmentation des écrit. In Inscription Spatiale du Langage: structures et processus, IRIT, Toulouse, France.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>F CHOI</author>
</authors>
<title>Advances in domain independent linear text segmentation.</title>
<date>2000</date>
<booktitle>In Proceding of the 1 st North American Chapter of the Association for Computational Linguistics,</booktitle>
<pages>26--33</pages>
<location>Seattle, Washington.</location>
<marker>CHOI, 2000</marker>
<rawString>CHOI F. (2000). Advances in domain independent linear text segmentation. In Proceding of the 1 st North American Chapter of the Association for Computational Linguistics, p. 26–33, Seattle, Washington.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>H CUNNINGHAM</author>
<author>D MAYNARD</author>
<author>K BONTCHEVA</author>
<author>V TABLAN</author>
</authors>
<title>Gate: A framework and graphical development environment for robust nlp tools and applications.</title>
<date>2002</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the 40th Anniversary Meeting of the Association for Computational Linguistics (ACL’02),</booktitle>
<location>Philadelphia.</location>
<marker>CUNNINGHAM, MAYNARD, BONTCHEVA, TABLAN, 2002</marker>
<rawString>CUNNINGHAM H., MAYNARD D., BONTCHEVA K. &amp; TABLAN V. (2002). Gate: A framework and graphical development environment for robust nlp tools and applications. In Proceedings of the 40th Anniversary Meeting of the Association for Computational Linguistics (ACL’02), Philadelphia.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>M A HEARST</author>
</authors>
<title>Multi-paragraph segmentation of expository text.</title>
<date>1994</date>
<booktitle>In the 32nd Meeting of the Association for Computational Linguistics,</booktitle>
<location>Los Cruces, NM.</location>
<marker>HEARST, 1994</marker>
<rawString>HEARST M. A. (1994). Multi-paragraph segmentation of expository text. In the 32nd Meeting of the Association for Computational Linguistics, Los Cruces, NM.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>M HEPPLE</author>
</authors>
<title>Independence and commitment: Assumptions for rapid training and execution of rule-based part-of-speech taggers.</title>
<date>2000</date>
<booktitle>In the 38th Annual Meeting of the Association for Computational Linguistics (ACL-2000),</booktitle>
<pages>278--285</pages>
<marker>HEPPLE, 2000</marker>
<rawString>HEPPLE M. (2000). Independence and commitment: Assumptions for rapid training and execution of rule-based part-of-speech taggers. In the 38th Annual Meeting of the Association for Computational Linguistics (ACL-2000), p. 278–285.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>L MAILHOT</author>
</authors>
<title>Ecrire la décision: guide pratique de rédaction judiciaire.</title>
<date>1996</date>
<location>Québec, Canada: Editions Yvon Blais.</location>
<marker>MAILHOT, 1996</marker>
<rawString>MAILHOT L. (1996). Ecrire la décision: guide pratique de rédaction judiciaire. Québec, Canada: Editions Yvon Blais.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>J-L MINEL</author>
<author>J-P DESCLÉS</author>
<author>E CARTIER</author>
<author>G CRISPINO</author>
<author>BEN HAZEZ S</author>
<author>A JACKIEWICZ</author>
</authors>
<title>Résumé automatique par filtrage sémantique d’informations dans des textes.</title>
<date>2001</date>
<journal>Revue Technique et Science Informatiques,</journal>
<volume>3</volume>
<marker>MINEL, DESCLÉS, CARTIER, CRISPINO, S, JACKIEWICZ, 2001</marker>
<rawString>MINEL J.-L., DESCLÉS J.-P., CARTIER E., CRISPINO G., BEN HAZEZ S. &amp; JACKIEWICZ A. (2001). Résumé automatique par filtrage sémantique d’informations dans des textes. Revue Technique et Science Informatiques, (3).</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>G MOURAD</author>
<author>J-P DESCLÉS</author>
</authors>
<title>Identification et extraction automatique des informations citationnelles dans un texte.</title>
<date>2003</date>
<booktitle>In Ci-Dit, Colloque international et interdisciplinaire,</booktitle>
<location>Bruxelles.</location>
<marker>MOURAD, DESCLÉS, 2003</marker>
<rawString>MOURAD G. &amp; DESCLÉS J.-P. (2003). Identification et extraction automatique des informations citationnelles dans un texte. In Ci-Dit, Colloque international et interdisciplinaire, Bruxelles.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>J C SMITH</author>
<author>C DEEDMAN</author>
</authors>
<title>The application of expert systems technology to case-based law. ICAIL,</title>
<date>1987</date>
<pages>84--93</pages>
<marker>SMITH, DEEDMAN, 1987</marker>
<rawString>SMITH J. C. &amp; DEEDMAN C. (1987). The application of expert systems technology to case-based law. ICAIL, p. 84–93.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>C UYTTENDAELE</author>
<author>M-F MOENS</author>
<author>J DUMORTIER</author>
</authors>
<title>Salomon: Abstracting of legal cases for effective access to court decisions.</title>
<date>1996</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of JURIX 96 Ninth International Conference on Legal Knowledge Based Systems,</booktitle>
<pages>47--58</pages>
<publisher>Tilburg: University Press.</publisher>
<marker>UYTTENDAELE, MOENS, DUMORTIER, 1996</marker>
<rawString>UYTTENDAELE C., MOENS M.-F. &amp; DUMORTIER J. (1996). Salomon: Abstracting of legal cases for effective access to court decisions. In Proceedings of JURIX 96 Ninth International Conference on Legal Knowledge Based Systems, p. 47–58: Tilburg: University Press.</rawString>
</citation>
</citationList>
</algorithm>
</algorithms>