<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<algorithms version="110505">
<algorithm name="ParsCit" version="110505">
<citationList>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>J Atlas</author>
</authors>
<title>Philosophy without Ambiguity.</title>
<date>1989</date>
<location>Oxford, Clarendon Press. Bickel, B.</location>
<marker>Atlas, 1989</marker>
<rawString>Atlas, J. (1989), Philosophy without Ambiguity. Oxford, Clarendon Press. Bickel, B. (1996), Aspect, Mood and Time in Belhare. Zürich, ASAS.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>R Carston</author>
</authors>
<title>Thoughts and Utterances.</title>
<date>2002</date>
<location>Oxford, Blackwell</location>
<contexts>
<context position="6489" citStr="Carston 2002" startWordPosition="941" endWordPosition="942"> 1989): Q-inferences are based on the first quantity maxim (‘make your statement as informative as possible’) and license inference to the negation or invalidity of a stronger expression, M-inferences stem from violations of the manner maxim (‘avoid prolixity’), and lincense the inference from marked expressions to marked interpretations. I-inferences are based on the second quantity maxim (‘do not say more than necessary’) and allow for inference to a stereotype. Contrary to the Gricean view, however, these are assumed to work also on the subpropositional level giving rise to ‘explicatures’ (Carston 2002), which enrich underspecified lexical representation. Q-inferences derive the meaning of unmarked forms by giving rise to scalar implicatures (scale &lt;pf, ipf&gt;), meaning that the use or the weaker element (ipf) entitles the hearer to infer the non-validity of the stronger expression (pf), thereby giving rise to the three possible values stated above (figure 1). M-inferences occur here with mismatches between aspectual selector and verbal basis, i.e. with the application of a φ- or τ-selector on a basis that does not provide the respective feature, which hast to be induced semantically or pragma</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Carston, 2002</marker>
<rawString>Carston, R. (2002), Thoughts and Utterances. Oxford, Blackwell Glovinskaja, M. J. (1982), Semantičeskije Tipy Vidovych Protivopostavlenija Russkogo Glagola. Moskva, Nauka.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>P Grice</author>
</authors>
<title>Studies in the Way of Words. Cambridge,</title>
<date>1989</date>
<publisher>Harvard University Press.</publisher>
<contexts>
<context position="5882" citStr="Grice 1989" startWordPosition="851" endWordPosition="852">ive reading then is derived by means of context and world-knowledge, cf. figure 1: VI Relation Reading of the ipf Aspect IPF I. synchronous, bounded TT included in φdyn actual-processual II. synchronous, non- TT simultaneous with habitual, inactual/continuous, potential, bounded (φdyn τ φstat) permanent, atemporal III. retrospective TT includes (φdyn τ φstat) general-factual, durative Figure 1: Classification of the readings of Russian ipf aspect 3 Basic pragmatics The pragmatic principles are Levinson’s (2000) default heuristics for interpretation based on the Gricean Maxims of Conversation (Grice 1989): Q-inferences are based on the first quantity maxim (‘make your statement as informative as possible’) and license inference to the negation or invalidity of a stronger expression, M-inferences stem from violations of the manner maxim (‘avoid prolixity’), and lincense the inference from marked expressions to marked interpretations. I-inferences are based on the second quantity maxim (‘do not say more than necessary’) and allow for inference to a stereotype. Contrary to the Gricean view, however, these are assumed to work also on the subpropositional level giving rise to ‘explicatures’ (Carsto</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Grice, 1989</marker>
<rawString>Grice, P. (1989), Studies in the Way of Words. Cambridge, Harvard University Press.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>S Levinson</author>
</authors>
<title>Presumptive Meanings.</title>
<date>2000</date>
<publisher>MIT Press.</publisher>
<location>Cambridge, London,</location>
<marker>Levinson, 2000</marker>
<rawString>Levinson, S. (2000), Presumptive Meanings. Cambridge, London, MIT Press.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>M Moens</author>
<author>M Steedman</author>
</authors>
<title>Temporal ontology and temporal reference.</title>
<date>1988</date>
<journal>Computational Linguistics,</journal>
<volume>14</volume>
<pages>29--43</pages>
<marker>Moens, Steedman, 1988</marker>
<rawString>Moens, M., Steedman, M. (1988), Temporal ontology and temporal reference. Computational Linguistics, Vol. 14/2, pp. 29-43.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>E V Padučeva</author>
</authors>
<title>Semantičeskije Issledovanija.</title>
<date>1996</date>
<location>Moskva, «Jazyki</location>
<note>russkoj kuĺtury».</note>
<contexts>
<context position="1906" citStr="Padučeva 1996" startWordPosition="254" endWordPosition="255">the basis for a rule-guided derivation of its different readings. Keywords – Mots Clés Indétermination, aspect, interprétation, sémantique, pragmatique Underspecification, aspect, interpretation, semantics, pragmatics 1 Underspecification of Russian ipf Aspect One instance of underspecification is aspect in Russian, especially the ipf, which gives rise to a considerable variety of readings. These temporal and further, rather specific readings arise due to an interplay of information provided by different linguistic and non-linguistic sources. Some examples are illustrated in (1a-d) below (cf. Padučeva 1996). The defeasibility of these 1 ‘ipf’ = (Russian) imperfective aspect; ‘pf’ = (Russian) perfective aspect Barbara Sonnenhauser readings indicates their at least partial pragmatic character. A further difficulty for NLP applications is that – presuming cooperativity – any utterance can receive an interpretation by appropriately accommodating the context. (1) a. actual-processual reading Kogda ja vošel, moj brat čital knigu. when I enter:PAST:pf, my brother read:PAST:ipf a book:ACC. ‘When I entered, my brother was reading a book.’ This reading is assumed to be the default reading, requiring no ad</context>
<context position="4647" citStr="Padučeva 1996" startWordPosition="669" endWordPosition="670">onditional evaluation at a validation interval VI. The non-selected parts of the event are presupposed or left to implicatures. Note, that aspect requires a certain input, and if this input is not given by the verbal basis, it has to be adjusted accordingly2. The marked members of the respective aspectual oppositions explicitly select a certain part; the unmarked forms are sense-general, their meaning has to be specified semantically or pragmatically. The readings of ipf can be grouped according to the character of their VI, which may be retrospective or synchronous (bounded or unbounded, cf. Padučeva 1996) with respect to the selected part. The relation 2 Contrary to what an anonymous reviewer pointend out, this analysis does make the correct predictions about ‘He is being silly’ meaning ‘He is acting silly’: the progressive requires a dynamic phase to be present, and this phase is pragmatically induced resulting in the respective interpretation (M-inference, cf. section 4). Towards a rule-guided derivation of aspectual readings in Russian characterizes the values ipf may acquire in interpretation.3 In most cases, VI is lexically specified and serves as a hint as to which group of readings (I-I</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Padučeva, 1996</marker>
<rawString>Padučeva, E. V. (1996), Semantičeskije Issledovanija. Moskva, «Jazyki russkoj kuĺtury».</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>S Pulman</author>
</authors>
<title>Aspectual shift as type coercion.</title>
<date>1997</date>
<journal>Transactions of the Philological Society,</journal>
<volume>95</volume>
<pages>279--317</pages>
<contexts>
<context position="7247" citStr="Pulman 1997" startWordPosition="1052" endWordPosition="1053">le &lt;pf, ipf&gt;), meaning that the use or the weaker element (ipf) entitles the hearer to infer the non-validity of the stronger expression (pf), thereby giving rise to the three possible values stated above (figure 1). M-inferences occur here with mismatches between aspectual selector and verbal basis, i.e. with the application of a φ- or τ-selector on a basis that does not provide the respective feature, which hast to be induced semantically or pragmatically, thereby enriching the logical structure. This can be systematically captured and formalized by ‘coercion operators’ (Thomas/Pulman 1999; Pulman 1997). I-inferences refer back to worldknowledge, thereby enriching the lexical meaning of the aspecto-temporal forms. As frequently encountered concepts are more likely to get activated, they constitute the stereotypes to which the I-inferences are drawn. 4 Towards a rule-guided derivation A list of readings has to be established (see figure 1), the factors involved their derivation have to be fixed and rules of interaction have to be stated that can be expressed in the propositional logic form A → B (cf. Vazov/Lapalme 2000). Interpretation of aspectual forms processes incrementally, i.e. informat</context>
<context position="8663" citStr="Pulman 1997" startWordPosition="1270" endWordPosition="1271">ee possibilities is indicated by a look at Turkish, which has morphological means to express the respective relation (cf. Sonnenhauser 2003). Barbara Sonnenhauser indexed for whether they add φ or τ and aspectual selectors indexed for what they select and for their status within the language specific markedness relation. That is how Q-inferences are drawn. VI constrains the interpretations of the unmarked aspectual partner. The default combinations of base and selector have to be stated, as well as rules for resolving the mismatches. M-inferences then can be pinned down by coercion operators (Pulman 1997; Thomas/Pulman 1999). More difficult is the problem of how to specify verbs for the commonsens knowledge they provide access to, which is indespensable for I-inference to be drawn. One means would be corpus analysis in order to detect regularities and coocurrences of lexical items that might hint to a conceptual connection. As the factor ‘probability’ can’t be eliminated, there is to be implemented a condition preferring the shortest line of reasoning (Thomas/Pulman 1999). The default case is a fit of basis and marker, where the verbal basis provides the necessary input for the marker to appl</context>
<context position="11615" citStr="Pulman 1997" startWordPosition="1753" endWordPosition="1754">e was working as a teacher.’) Depending on the semantic representation of the verb, implicatures or presuppositions may arise. Ipf with the structure [φ τ] leaves the reaching of the boundary as an implicature, ipf with [τ φ] leaves the initial boundary as presupposition. Towards a rule-guided derivation of aspectual readings in Russian Whenever an aspectual marker is applied on a basis not providing the relevant feature (φ or τ) for it to apply, that feature is semantically or pragmatically induced in order to eliminate that mismatch. Coercion operators capture this recategorization process (Pulman 1997): (9) a. Ivan vyigral gonku. Ivan win:PAST:pf race:ACC ‘Ivan won the race.’ Here, pf is applied to a verb that provides a τ; no coercion is necessary. b. Ivan vyigryval gonku (četyre raza). Ivan win: PAST:ipf race:ACC (four times). ‘Ivan won the race four times / was winning the race.’ The application of ipf in (9b) requires a φ, which the verb vyigrat́ (‘win’) does not provide. So it has to be induced by iteration or by zooming in on φdyn. Two coercion operators may be applied: “iterate / stretch: point → process” (Pulman 1997). In most cases, context provides the necessary cues for disambigu</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Pulman, 1997</marker>
<rawString>Pulman, S. (1997), Aspectual shift as type coercion. Transactions of the Philological Society, Vol. 95/2, pp. 279-317.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="false">
<authors>
<author>B Sonnenhauser</author>
</authors>
<title>Aspect and the semantics-pragmatics interface.</title>
<date>2003</date>
<journal>Natural Language and Linguistic Theory,</journal>
<booktitle>Proceedings of RANLP 03, Borovets</booktitle>
<volume>16</volume>
<pages>347--385</pages>
<location>Tilburg,</location>
<contexts>
<context position="8192" citStr="Sonnenhauser 2003" startWordPosition="1197" endWordPosition="1198"> (see figure 1), the factors involved their derivation have to be fixed and rules of interaction have to be stated that can be expressed in the propositional logic form A → B (cf. Vazov/Lapalme 2000). Interpretation of aspectual forms processes incrementally, i.e. information once provided and processed can’t be undone. Input factors for algorithms are the following: Verbs indexed for φ and τ they contain; lexical items 3 That we have indeed to distinguish between those three possibilities is indicated by a look at Turkish, which has morphological means to express the respective relation (cf. Sonnenhauser 2003). Barbara Sonnenhauser indexed for whether they add φ or τ and aspectual selectors indexed for what they select and for their status within the language specific markedness relation. That is how Q-inferences are drawn. VI constrains the interpretations of the unmarked aspectual partner. The default combinations of base and selector have to be stated, as well as rules for resolving the mismatches. M-inferences then can be pinned down by coercion operators (Pulman 1997; Thomas/Pulman 1999). More difficult is the problem of how to specify verbs for the commonsens knowledge they provide access to,</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Sonnenhauser, 2003</marker>
<rawString>Sonnenhauser, B. (2003), Aspect and the semantics-pragmatics interface. Proceedings of RANLP 03, Borovets de Swart, H. (1998), Aspect shift and type coercion. Natural Language and Linguistic Theory, Vol. 16/2, pp. 347-385 Thomas, J., Pulman, S. (1999), Bidirectional interpretation of tense and aspect. Bunt, H. et al. (eds), Proceedings of the 3rd International Workshop on Computational Semantics. Tilburg, pp. 247-263.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>N Vazov</author>
<author>G Lapalme</author>
</authors>
<title>Are the temporal structures of texts algorithms?.</title>
<date>2000</date>
<booktitle>Proceedings of the 7th International Conference on Principles of Knowledge Representation and Reasoning.</booktitle>
<pages>79--86</pages>
<location>Breckenridge,</location>
<marker>Vazov, Lapalme, 2000</marker>
<rawString>Vazov, N., Lapalme, G. (2000), Are the temporal structures of texts algorithms?. Proceedings of the 7th International Conference on Principles of Knowledge Representation and Reasoning. Breckenridge, pp. 79-86.</rawString>
</citation>
</citationList>
</algorithm>
</algorithms>