<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<algorithms version="110505">
<algorithm name="ParsCit" version="110505">
<citationList>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>A Dikovsky</author>
</authors>
<title>Grammars for Local and Long Dependencies.</title>
<date>2001</date>
<booktitle>Proceedings of the 39th Annual Meeting of the ACL.</booktitle>
<contexts>
<context position="22759" citStr="Dikovsky, 2001" startWordPosition="4273" endWordPosition="4274"> 7F F . Figure 6 illustrates one  æ f h { of the possible D-trees generated by and associated with the string . f Ü Ý Ü Ü Ü Ñ Ò Ü Ñ f f h Ñ Ú Û Ú Ü Ý Ü Ú Ú Ü Ú Ü Ú Ñ Ò Ü Ú Ñ h h Ñ Ú Û Ú Ú { Ú Ú Ú ä&gt;å ä Ú Ú ä Ú ä Ú Í&gt;Î ä Í Ú { { Ú Í 7 7 7 f h { Tæ Figure 6: D-tree of the string generated by To conclude this section, we establish the following result. ,Uç1· T Theorem 5.2 The strict inclusion S ÁS holds. 6 Conclusions We introduced a formal model for the generation of dependency trees, dealing with free word order phenomena. The problem is currently under study (see (Holan et al., 1998), (Dikovsky, 2001), (Gramatovici &amp; Plátek, 2003)) and is far to be solved. The model of dependency contextual grammars we propose here is based on two main characteristics: the intrinsic similitude between dependency trees and contextual grammars and the flexibility of the latter in expressing non-local dependencies. Our approach is closer to the intrinsic motivations of original dependency grammars than other current similar attempts are. The research of dependency contextual grammars just started since the model has to be further tested on both mathematical and linguistical sides. R. Gramatovici, C. Martı́n-V</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Dikovsky, 2001</marker>
<rawString>Dikovsky A. (2001). Grammars for Local and Long Dependencies. Proceedings of the 39th Annual Meeting of the ACL.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>A Dikovsky</author>
<author>L Modina</author>
</authors>
<date>2000</date>
<booktitle>Dependencies on the Other Side of the Curtain. In Traitement Automatique des Langues (TAL),</booktitle>
<volume>41</volume>
<issue>1</issue>
<pages>79--111</pages>
<marker>Dikovsky, Modina, 2000</marker>
<rawString>Dikovsky A. &amp; Modina L. (2000). Dependencies on the Other Side of the Curtain. In Traitement Automatique des Langues (TAL), 41 (1), 79-111.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>R Gramatovici</author>
<author>M Plátek</author>
</authors>
<title>On D-trivial Dependency Grammars.</title>
<date>2003</date>
<note>Submitted.</note>
<marker>Gramatovici, Plátek, 2003</marker>
<rawString>Gramatovici R. &amp; Plátek M. (2003). On D-trivial Dependency Grammars. Submitted.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>T Holan</author>
<author>V Kuboň</author>
<author>K Oliva</author>
<author>M Plátek</author>
</authors>
<title>Two Useful Measures of Word Order Complexity.</title>
<date>1998</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the Coling’98 Workshop “Processing of Dependency-Based Grammars”, Polguere</booktitle>
<pages>21--28</pages>
<editor>A. &amp; Kahane S. eds.,</editor>
<institution>University of Montreal,</institution>
<location>Montreal,</location>
<contexts>
<context position="22741" citStr="Holan et al., 1998" startWordPosition="4269" endWordPosition="4272">e second language, 7 7 7F F . Figure 6 illustrates one  æ f h { of the possible D-trees generated by and associated with the string . f Ü Ý Ü Ü Ü Ñ Ò Ü Ñ f f h Ñ Ú Û Ú Ü Ý Ü Ú Ú Ü Ú Ü Ú Ñ Ò Ü Ú Ñ h h Ñ Ú Û Ú Ú { Ú Ú Ú ä&gt;å ä Ú Ú ä Ú ä Ú Í&gt;Î ä Í Ú { { Ú Í 7 7 7 f h { Tæ Figure 6: D-tree of the string generated by To conclude this section, we establish the following result. ,Uç1· T Theorem 5.2 The strict inclusion S ÁS holds. 6 Conclusions We introduced a formal model for the generation of dependency trees, dealing with free word order phenomena. The problem is currently under study (see (Holan et al., 1998), (Dikovsky, 2001), (Gramatovici &amp; Plátek, 2003)) and is far to be solved. The model of dependency contextual grammars we propose here is based on two main characteristics: the intrinsic similitude between dependency trees and contextual grammars and the flexibility of the latter in expressing non-local dependencies. Our approach is closer to the intrinsic motivations of original dependency grammars than other current similar attempts are. The research of dependency contextual grammars just started since the model has to be further tested on both mathematical and linguistical sides. R. Gramato</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Holan, Kuboň, Oliva, Plátek, 1998</marker>
<rawString>Holan T., Kuboň V., Oliva K. &amp; Plátek M. (1998). Two Useful Measures of Word Order Complexity. In Proceedings of the Coling’98 Workshop “Processing of Dependency-Based Grammars”, Polguere A. &amp; Kahane S. eds., University of Montreal, Montreal, 21-28.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>A K Joshi</author>
</authors>
<title>An Introduction to Tree Adjoining Grammars.</title>
<date>1987</date>
<booktitle>In Mathematics of Languages, Manaster-Ramer A. ed.,</booktitle>
<pages>87--114</pages>
<location>Amsterdam, Philadelphia: Johm Bejamins,</location>
<contexts>
<context position="16976" citStr="Joshi, 1987" startWordPosition="3029" endWordPosition="3030"> on strings generated by CGs, one may speak about the strong generative power of the structured CGs. The strong generative power means the capacity of (dependency, in our case) CGs to generate different dendrolanguages, underlying the same language. In this section, we investigate some structural properties of IDCGs. Top-down and bottom-up derivation The derivation of phrases in a context-free grammar is a top-down process starting with the root of the (constituent) tree and leading to its leaves. Among the novelties brought by tree-adjoining Contextual Grammars and Dependency Trees grammars (Joshi, 1987) and other formalisms in the area of the mild context sensitiveness, was the fact that derivation is not necessarily a top-down process. It is important to remark the capacity of IDCGs to construct the (same) structure of the (same) string in totally different ways. ,ØeGgf&lt; hoQW kG@*fWhI kG@ Ä QjQW m4GjX3QW m f6 hi kG@*f&lt; E m Ä Qj} TÙ Example 4.1 Consider    and 4Ggf&lt; hoQW kG@ f_hI kG@ Ä QjQW m f  h  m f&lt; hEE kG@ f_E m Ä Qj}    two IDCGs. 7 7 f h The D-tree represented in Figure 2 corresponding to the string is generated in a top-down f</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Joshi, 1987</marker>
<rawString>Joshi A. K. (1987). An Introduction to Tree Adjoining Grammars. In Mathematics of Languages, Manaster-Ramer A. ed., Amsterdam, Philadelphia: Johm Bejamins, 87-114.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>M Kappes</author>
</authors>
<title>Bracketed Contextual Grammars. Doctoral Dissertation, Johann Wolfgang Goethe Universität,</title>
<date>2000</date>
<location>Frankfurt am Main.</location>
<contexts>
<context position="11960" citStr="Kappes, 2000" startWordPosition="2118" endWordPosition="2119">of ( ̈ is called the root of 2 ); ii) for any © , there is a unique inde K &amp;quot; K ax © &amp;quot;BCe &amp;quot;B±̄@ C} ®&amp;(¢ «  ¬ such that depends on ; iii) « ¬ is an anti-reflexive relation, i.e. , for any +&amp; *   K &amp;quot; K a © . We denote by ́ the set of D-trees over a set of terminals. Linguistically motivated, the structures over CGs were introduced in (Martı́n-Vide &amp; Păun, 1998) (see al(Marcus et al., 1998), or Section 7.6 in (Păun, 1997)). Bracketed CGs, i.e. contextual grammars working on strings of terminal symbols enriched with a well-formed structure of brackets, were extensively studied in (Kappes, 2000). We are interested here in the second type of structured CGs introduced in (Martı́n-Vide &amp; Păun, 1998), which do not use brackets for creating tree-like structures on strings, but binary relations between terminal symbols. However, the definition of a dependency CG given below is formally different from the definition of a structured CG given in (Martı́n-Vide &amp; Păun, 1998). μ¶*+ , ·+2 oDkDoDk ·?3 We call an internal dependency contextual grammar (IDCG) iff is   ,  an alphabet, ́ is a finite set of D-trees over (the axioms) .&amp; aand for any © , ·̧1*c® {®   c3</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Kappes, 2000</marker>
<rawString>Kappes M. (2000). Bracketed Contextual Grammars. Doctoral Dissertation, Johann Wolfgang Goethe Universität, Frankfurt am Main.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>S Marcus</author>
</authors>
<title>Algebraic Linguistics. Analytical Models.</title>
<date>1967</date>
<publisher>Academic Press.</publisher>
<location>New-York, London:</location>
<contexts>
<context position="10386" citStr="Marcus, 1967" startWordPosition="1781" endWordPosition="1782">e length of the substrings of the given string, which are used to select contexts at some derivation step. In Section 5, we provide with a different method for the improvement of the (weak) generative power of CGs. 3 Dependency Contextual Grammars A dependency tree (D-tree) is a tree whose nodes are labelled over an alphabet of terminal symbols. Sometimes, its edges are also labelled over another alphabet (of syntactic categories), but we will not use this feature here as it is not relevant for the purpose of this paper. We will introduce D-trees using the concept of a structured string from (Marcus, 1967) (see also (Martı́n-Vide &amp; Păun, 1998), (Marcus et al., 1998)).   Ya  Let be an alphabet. If is a natural number, we denote by © the set of the first natural  C&amp;quot;? «W¬g &amp;quot;%&amp;(  numbers. A structured string over is a pair , where is a non-empty string  « ¬ K &amp;quot; K a K &amp;quot; K a G@C} ® K &amp; K &amp;quot; K a Q z over and © © © is an anti-reflexive binary relation, called &amp;quot; &amp;quot; T&amp; &amp;quot; a &amp;quot;B ®  dependency relation K Kon . If is a string and © , we denote by the -th symbol of &amp;quot; « ¬Ē &amp;quot;B°̄_ &amp;quot;B e «O . If , then we say that depends ¬on . Let us denote by (and call dominance &amp;quot; «W¬ *«_ ̄ &amp;quot;BCe</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Marcus, 1967</marker>
<rawString>Marcus S. (1967). Algebraic Linguistics. Analytical Models. New-York, London: Academic Press.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>S Marcus</author>
</authors>
<date>1969</date>
<journal>Contextual Grammars, Rev. Roum. Math. Pures Appl..</journal>
<volume>14</volume>
<issue>10</issue>
<pages>69--74</pages>
<contexts>
<context position="1567" citStr="Marcus, 1969" startWordPosition="209" endWordPosition="210">ependency trees, is introduced. The new generative model, called dependency contextual grammar, improves both the strong and weak generative power of contextual grammars, while being a potential candidate for the mathematical description of dependency-based syntactic models.  This work was written during a research visit of the first author at the Research Group on Mathematical Linguistics of Rovira i Virgili University. The research visit was funded by the NATO Scientific Committee. R. Gramatovici, C. Martı́n-Vide 1 Introduction Contextual grammars were introduced in 1969 by Solomon Marcus (Marcus, 1969) as an attempt to transform in generative devices some procedures developed within the framework of analytical models (see (Marcus, 1997) for a comprehensive discussion on the linguistic motivations of contextual grammars). In many respects, (the mathematical model of) contextual grammars and (the linguistic model of) dependency grammars ((Mel’čuk, 1987) and others) have the same roots. The similitude between contextual grammars and dependency syntactic models based on dependency trees go further, since both formalisms deal mostly with symbols of the language and less or at all with auxiliary </context>
</contexts>
<marker>Marcus, 1969</marker>
<rawString>Marcus S. (1969). Contextual Grammars, Rev. Roum. Math. Pures Appl.. 14 (10), 69-74.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>S Marcus</author>
</authors>
<title>Contextual Grammars and Natural Languages.</title>
<date>1997</date>
<booktitle>In The Handbook of Formal Languages,</booktitle>
<volume>2</volume>
<pages>215--235</pages>
<editor>G. &amp; Salomaa A. eds.,</editor>
<publisher>Springer-Verlag,</publisher>
<location>Rozenberg</location>
<contexts>
<context position="1704" citStr="Marcus, 1997" startWordPosition="230" endWordPosition="231">ive power of contextual grammars, while being a potential candidate for the mathematical description of dependency-based syntactic models.  This work was written during a research visit of the first author at the Research Group on Mathematical Linguistics of Rovira i Virgili University. The research visit was funded by the NATO Scientific Committee. R. Gramatovici, C. Martı́n-Vide 1 Introduction Contextual grammars were introduced in 1969 by Solomon Marcus (Marcus, 1969) as an attempt to transform in generative devices some procedures developed within the framework of analytical models (see (Marcus, 1997) for a comprehensive discussion on the linguistic motivations of contextual grammars). In many respects, (the mathematical model of) contextual grammars and (the linguistic model of) dependency grammars ((Mel’čuk, 1987) and others) have the same roots. The similitude between contextual grammars and dependency syntactic models based on dependency trees go further, since both formalisms deal mostly with symbols of the language and less or at all with auxiliary symbols as in the case of formalisms based on constituents trees. A similar argument to this one is presented in (Mráz et al., 2000), whe</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Marcus, 1997</marker>
<rawString>Marcus S. (1997). Contextual Grammars and Natural Languages. In The Handbook of Formal Languages, Rozenberg G. &amp; Salomaa A. eds., Berlin, Heidelberg, New-York: Springer-Verlag, vol. 2, 215-235.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>S Marcus</author>
<author>C Martı́n-Vide</author>
<author>Păun Gh</author>
</authors>
<title>Contextual Grammars as Generative Models of Natural Languages.</title>
<date>1998</date>
<journal>Computational Linguistics,</journal>
<volume>24</volume>
<issue>2</issue>
<pages>245--274</pages>
<marker>Marcus, Martı́n-Vide, Gh, 1998</marker>
<rawString>Marcus S., Martı́n-Vide C. &amp; Păun Gh. (1998). Contextual Grammars as Generative Models of Natural Languages. Computational Linguistics, 24 (2), 245-274.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>C Martı́n-Vide</author>
<author>Păun Gh</author>
</authors>
<date>1998</date>
<journal>Structured Contextual Grammars. Grammars,</journal>
<volume>1</volume>
<issue>1</issue>
<pages>33--55</pages>
<marker>Martı́n-Vide, Gh, 1998</marker>
<rawString>Martı́n-Vide C. &amp; Păun Gh. (1998). Structured Contextual Grammars. Grammars, 1 (1), 33-55.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>C Martı́n-Vide</author>
<author>A Mateescu</author>
<author>J Miquel-Verges</author>
<author>Păun Gh</author>
</authors>
<title>Internal contextual grammars: minimal, maximal and scattered use of selectors.</title>
<date>1997</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of The Fourth Bar-Ilan Symposium on Foundations of Artificial Intelligence. Focusing on Natural Languages and Artificial Intelligence - Philosophical and Computational Aspects, Koppel</booktitle>
<pages>159--168</pages>
<editor>M. &amp; Shamir E. eds., Menlo Park:</editor>
<publisher>AAAI Press,</publisher>
<marker>Martı́n-Vide, Mateescu, Miquel-Verges, Gh, 1997</marker>
<rawString>Martı́n-Vide C., Mateescu A., Miquel-Verges J. &amp; Păun Gh. (1997). Internal contextual grammars: minimal, maximal and scattered use of selectors. In Proceedings of The Fourth Bar-Ilan Symposium on Foundations of Artificial Intelligence. Focusing on Natural Languages and Artificial Intelligence - Philosophical and Computational Aspects, Koppel M. &amp; Shamir E. eds., Menlo Park: AAAI Press, 159-168.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>I Mel’čuk</author>
</authors>
<title>Dependency Syntax. Theory and Practice,</title>
<date>1987</date>
<publisher>Press.</publisher>
<institution>State University of New-York</institution>
<location>Albany:</location>
<marker>Mel’čuk, 1987</marker>
<rawString>Mel’čuk I. (1987). Dependency Syntax. Theory and Practice, Albany: State University of New-York Press.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>F Mráz</author>
<author>M Plátek</author>
<author>M Procházcha</author>
</authors>
<title>Restarting automata, deleting and Marcus grammars.</title>
<date>2000</date>
<booktitle>In Recent Topics in Mathematical and Computational Linguistics, Martin-Vide</booktitle>
<pages>218--233</pages>
<editor>C. &amp; Păun Gh. eds.,</editor>
<publisher>Academy Publishing House,</publisher>
<location>Bucharest: Romanian</location>
<contexts>
<context position="2299" citStr="Mráz et al., 2000" startWordPosition="320" endWordPosition="323">els (see (Marcus, 1997) for a comprehensive discussion on the linguistic motivations of contextual grammars). In many respects, (the mathematical model of) contextual grammars and (the linguistic model of) dependency grammars ((Mel’čuk, 1987) and others) have the same roots. The similitude between contextual grammars and dependency syntactic models based on dependency trees go further, since both formalisms deal mostly with symbols of the language and less or at all with auxiliary symbols as in the case of formalisms based on constituents trees. A similar argument to this one is presented in (Mráz et al., 2000), where contextual mechanism is described as dual to the analysis by reduction linguistic method. However, no relationship was established yet between contextual and dependency grammars. This happened probably because, originally, contextual grammars developed a string generative mechanism and structures on strings generated by contextual grammars were introduced only recently in (Martı́n-Vide &amp; Păun, 1998). In this paper, we propose a new approach to the generation of dependency trees (D-trees), based on contextual grammars. The notion of internal dependency contextual grammar (DCG) is introd</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Mráz, Plátek, Procházcha, 2000</marker>
<rawString>Mráz F., Plátek M. &amp; Procházcha M. (2000). Restarting automata, deleting and Marcus grammars. In Recent Topics in Mathematical and Computational Linguistics, Martin-Vide C. &amp; Păun Gh. eds., Bucharest: Romanian Academy Publishing House, 218-233.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Păun Gh</author>
</authors>
<title>Marcus Contextual Grammars,</title>
<date>1997</date>
<publisher>Kluwer.</publisher>
<location>Dordrecht, Boston, London:</location>
<marker>Gh, 1997</marker>
<rawString>Păun Gh. (1997). Marcus Contextual Grammars, Dordrecht, Boston, London: Kluwer.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>X M Nguyen</author>
</authors>
<title>On the inner contextual grammars,</title>
<date>1980</date>
<journal>Rev. Roum. Math. Pures Appl.,</journal>
<volume>25</volume>
<pages>641--651</pages>
<contexts>
<context position="5002" citStr="Nguyen, 1980" startWordPosition="741" endWordPosition="742">, in the form of contexts (pairs of strings, possibly one-sided) selected by the strings already present in the sentence. Formally, an internal contextual grammar (CG)     is a construct , where is   an alphabet, is a finite language over (the set of axioms),   is a finite subset of (the fffiset of contexts) and ffifl     is the choice (or selection) recursive map. When !#&amp;quot;$% &amp;quot;&apos;&amp;   ()*+ , , , for all , we say that is a CG without choice and write . The Contextual Grammars and Dependency Trees internal derivation style (introduced in (Păun &amp; Nguyen, 1980)) of a CG is defined by: &amp;quot;.-0/ &amp;quot;ffi1&amp;quot;324&amp;quot;65 &amp;quot;67 /89&amp;quot;32;:&lt;&amp;quot;65 =&gt;&amp;quot;67  :? =@$&amp;ABC&amp;quot;65ED iff and for some   - - *,HGI&amp;quot;J&amp;1 LKMON &amp;P N - &amp;quot;RQ If is the reflexive and transitive closure of , then F   T denotes the language generated by . We denote by S and S the classes of languages generated by internal CGs without, respectively with choice1. 2+U    Example 2.1 Consider a very simple internal CG with choice , where   G QWV John likes Lyn really   G QWV John likes Lyn   G@ XYQWV really G@ XQW &amp;quot;L !#&amp;quot; Z really if likes [ V otherwise \2 The langu</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Nguyen, 1980</marker>
<rawString>Păun Gh. &amp; Nguyen X. M. (1980). On the inner contextual grammars, Rev. Roum. Math. Pures Appl., 25, 641-651.</rawString>
</citation>
</citationList>
</algorithm>
</algorithms>