<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<algorithms version="110505">
<algorithm name="ParsCit" version="110505">
<citationList>
<citation valid="false">
<authors>
<author>Similarité Similaire</author>
</authors>
<title>semblable, pareil, équivalent, ressemblant, synonyme, proche, identique, rapproché Demande Souhaite, faut, désire, désirerais, peux, pourrais, veux, voudrais, possible, aimerais, souhaiterais Ordre Montrer, indiquer, sélectionner, trouver, donner, afﬁcher, présenter, prendre, passer,</title>
<date>2001</date>
<journal>chercher BOUSQUET-VERNHETTES C. &amp; VIGOUROUX N.</journal>
<booktitle>In International Workshop on Speech and Computer; SPECOM’0I,</booktitle>
<location>Moscow.</location>
<marker>Similaire, 2001</marker>
<rawString>Similarité Similaire, semblable, pareil, équivalent, ressemblant, synonyme, proche, identique, rapproché Demande Souhaite, faut, désire, désirerais, peux, pourrais, veux, voudrais, possible, aimerais, souhaiterais Ordre Montrer, indiquer, sélectionner, trouver, donner, afﬁcher, présenter, prendre, passer, chercher BOUSQUET-VERNHETTES C. &amp; VIGOUROUX N. (2001). Context use to improve the speech understanding processing. In International Workshop on Speech and Computer; SPECOM’0I, Moscow.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>P CHEESEMAN</author>
<author>J STUTZ</author>
</authors>
<title>Bayesian classiﬁcation (autoclass): Theory and results.</title>
<date>1996</date>
<booktitle>In Advances in Knowledge Discovery and Data</booktitle>
<marker>CHEESEMAN, STUTZ, 1996</marker>
<rawString>CHEESEMAN P. &amp; STUTZ J. (1996). Bayesian classiﬁcation (autoclass): Theory and results. In Advances in Knowledge Discovery and Data Mining. U. Fayyad, G. Shapiro, P. Smyth, R. Uthurusamy.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>S JAMOUSSI</author>
<author>K SMAILI</author>
<author>J HATON</author>
</authors>
<title>Neural network and information theory in speech understanding.</title>
<date>2002</date>
<booktitle>In International Workshop on Speech and Computer; SPECOM’02, St. Petersbourg.</booktitle>
<marker>JAMOUSSI, SMAILI, HATON, 2002</marker>
<rawString>JAMOUSSI S., SMAILI K. &amp; HATON J . (2002). Neural network and information theory in speech understanding. In International Workshop on Speech and Computer; SPECOM’02, St. Petersbourg.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>H MAYNARD</author>
<author>F LEFEVRE</author>
</authors>
<title>Apprentissage d’un module stochastique de compréhension de la parole.</title>
<date>2002</date>
<booktitle>In 24emes Joumées d ’Etude sur la parole,</booktitle>
<location>Nancy.</location>
<marker>MAYNARD, LEFEVRE, 2002</marker>
<rawString>MAYNARD H. &amp; LEFEVRE F. (2002). Apprentissage d’un module stochastique de compréhension de la parole. In 24emes Joumées d ’Etude sur la parole, Nancy.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>R PIERACCINI</author>
<author>E LEVIN</author>
<author>E VIDAL</author>
</authors>
<title>Learning how to understand language.</title>
<date>1993</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the 4rd European Conference on Speech Communication and Technology,</booktitle>
<location>Berlin.</location>
<marker>PIERACCINI, LEVIN, VIDAL, 1993</marker>
<rawString>PIERACCINI R., LEVIN E. &amp; VIDAL E. (1993). Learning how to understand language. In Proceedings of the 4rd European Conference on Speech Communication and Technology, Berlin.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>R ROSENFELD</author>
</authors>
<title>Adaptive Statistical Language Modeling: A Maximum Entropy Approach.</title>
<date>1994</date>
<tech>PhD thesis,</tech>
<pages>15213</pages>
<institution>School of Computer Science Carnegie Mellon University,</institution>
<location>Pittsburgh, PA</location>
<marker>ROSENFELD, 1994</marker>
<rawString>ROSENFELD R. (1994). Adaptive Statistical Language Modeling: A Maximum Entropy Approach. PhD thesis, School of Computer Science Carnegie Mellon University, Pittsburgh, PA 15213.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>K-C SIU</author>
<author>H M MENG</author>
</authors>
<title>Semi-automatic acquisition of domain-speciﬁc semantic structures.</title>
<date>1999</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the 6th European Conference on Speech Communication and Technology,</booktitle>
<location>Budapest.</location>
<marker>SIU, MENG, 1999</marker>
<rawString>SIU K.-C. &amp; MENG H. M. (1999). Semi-automatic acquisition of domain-speciﬁc semantic structures. In Proceedings of the 6th European Conference on Speech Communication and Technology, Budapest.</rawString>
</citation>
</citationList>
</algorithm>
</algorithms>