<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<algorithms version="110505">
<algorithm name="ParsCit" version="110505">
<citationList>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>S CHANOD J P AÏT-MOKHTAR</author>
<author>C ROUX</author>
</authors>
<title>Robustness beyond shallowness: Incremental deep parsing.</title>
<date>2002</date>
<journal>Special Issue of the Natural Language Engineering Journal on Robust Methods in Analysis of Natural Language Data,</journal>
<pages>121--144</pages>
<marker>AÏT-MOKHTAR, ROUX, 2002</marker>
<rawString>AÏT-MOKHTAR, S. CHANOD J. P. &amp; ROUX C. (2002). Robustness beyond shallowness: Incremental deep parsing. Special Issue of the Natural Language Engineering Journal on Robust Methods in Analysis of Natural Language Data, p. 121–144.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>D BOURIGAULT</author>
<author>C FABRE</author>
</authors>
<title>Approche linguistique pour l’analyse syntaxique de corpus.</title>
<date>2000</date>
<journal>Cahiers de Grammaire,</journal>
<volume>25</volume>
<pages>139--151</pages>
<marker>BOURIGAULT, FABRE, 2000</marker>
<rawString>BOURIGAULT D. &amp; FABRE C. (2000). Approche linguistique pour l’analyse syntaxique de corpus. Cahiers de Grammaire, 25, 139–151.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>GALA PAVIA N</author>
</authors>
<title>Un modèle d’analyseur syntaxique robuste fondé sur la modularité et la lexicalisation de ses grammaires. Thèse de doctorat, Université de Paris-Sud, UFR Scientifique d’Orsay.</title>
<date>2003</date>
<marker>N, 2003</marker>
<rawString>GALA PAVIA N. (2003). Un modèle d’analyseur syntaxique robuste fondé sur la modularité et la lexicalisation de ses grammaires. Thèse de doctorat, Université de Paris-Sud, UFR Scientifique d’Orsay.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>G GREFENSTETTE</author>
</authors>
<title>The World Wide Web as a resource for example-based machine translation tasks.</title>
<date>1999</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of Aslib Conference on Translating and the Computer 21,</booktitle>
<location>London.</location>
<marker>GREFENSTETTE, 1999</marker>
<rawString>GREFENSTETTE G. (1999). The World Wide Web as a resource for example-based machine translation tasks. In Proceedings of Aslib Conference on Translating and the Computer 21, London.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>C JACQUEMIN</author>
<author>C BUSH</author>
</authors>
<title>Combining lexical and formatting cues for named entity acquisition from the Web. In</title>
<date>2000</date>
<booktitle>Proceedings of Joint Sigdat Conference On Empirical Methods In Natural Language Processing And Very Large Corpora (EMNLP/VLC-2000),</booktitle>
<location>Hong Kong.</location>
<marker>JACQUEMIN, BUSH, 2000</marker>
<rawString>JACQUEMIN C. &amp; BUSH C. (2000). Combining lexical and formatting cues for named entity acquisition from the Web. In H. SCHUTZE, Ed., Proceedings of Joint Sigdat Conference On Empirical Methods In Natural Language Processing And Very Large Corpora (EMNLP/VLC-2000), Hong Kong.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>T LEBARBÉ</author>
</authors>
<title>Hiérarchie inclusive des unités linguistiques en analyse syntaxique coopérative. Thèse de doctorat, Université de Caen.</title>
<date>2002</date>
<marker>LEBARBÉ, 2002</marker>
<rawString>LEBARBÉ T. (2002). Hiérarchie inclusive des unités linguistiques en analyse syntaxique coopérative. Thèse de doctorat, Université de Caen.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>M VOLK</author>
</authors>
<title>Exploiting the WWW as a corpus to resolve PP attachment.</title>
<date>2001</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of Conference on Corpus Linguistics,</booktitle>
<pages>601--606</pages>
<location>Lancaster.</location>
<marker>VOLK, 2001</marker>
<rawString>VOLK M. (2001). Exploiting the WWW as a corpus to resolve PP attachment. In Proceedings of Conference on Corpus Linguistics, p. 601–606, Lancaster.</rawString>
</citation>
</citationList>
</algorithm>
</algorithms>