<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<algorithms version="110505">
<algorithm name="ParsCit" version="110505">
<citationList>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>M H Al-Adhaileh</author>
<author>E K Tang</author>
</authors>
<date>1999</date>
<booktitle>Example-Based Machine Translation Based on the Synchronous SSTC Annotation Schema. Machine Translation Summit VII, Singapore,</booktitle>
<pages>244--249</pages>
<marker>Al-Adhaileh, Tang, 1999</marker>
<rawString>Al-Adhaileh, M. H. &amp; Tang E. K. 1999. Example-Based Machine Translation Based on the Synchronous SSTC Annotation Schema. Machine Translation Summit VII, Singapore, 244–249.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>T Andriamanankasina</author>
<author>K Araki</author>
<author>K Tochinai</author>
</authors>
<title>Ebmt of pos-tagged sentences with inductive learning.</title>
<date>2003</date>
<booktitle>In (Carl &amp; Way,</booktitle>
<marker>Andriamanankasina, Araki, Tochinai, 2003</marker>
<rawString>Andriamanankasina, T., K. Araki, &amp; K, Tochinai. 2003. Ebmt of pos-tagged sentences with inductive learning. In (Carl &amp; Way, 2003).</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>T Andriamanankasina</author>
<author>K Araki</author>
<author>K Tochinai</author>
</authors>
<title>Example-Based Machine Translation of PartOf-Speech Tagged Sentences by Recursive Division. Machine Translation Summit VII,</title>
<date>1999</date>
<pages>509--517</pages>
<marker>Andriamanankasina, Araki, Tochinai, 1999</marker>
<rawString>Andriamanankasina, T., K. Araki &amp; K. Tochinai. 1999. Example-Based Machine Translation of PartOf-Speech Tagged Sentences by Recursive Division. Machine Translation Summit VII, Singapore, 509–517.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>P F Brown</author>
<author>J Cocke</author>
<author>S A Della Pietra</author>
<author>V J Della Pietra</author>
<author>F Jelinek</author>
<author>J D Lafferty</author>
<author>R L Mercer</author>
<author>P S Roossin</author>
</authors>
<title>A Statistical Approach to Machine Translation.</title>
<date>1990</date>
<journal>Computational Linguistics</journal>
<volume>16</volume>
<pages>79--85</pages>
<marker>Brown, Cocke, Pietra, Pietra, Jelinek, Lafferty, Mercer, Roossin, 1990</marker>
<rawString>Brown, P. F., J. Cocke, S. A. Della Pietra, V. J. Della Pietra, F. Jelinek, J. D. Lafferty, R. L. Mercer &amp; P. S. Roossin. 1990. A Statistical Approach to Machine Translation. Computational Linguistics 16, 79–85.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>R D Brown</author>
</authors>
<title>Example-Based Machine Translation in the Pangloss System. Coling</title>
<date>1996</date>
<pages>169--174</pages>
<marker>Brown, 1996</marker>
<rawString>Brown, R. D. 1996. Example-Based Machine Translation in the Pangloss System. Coling (1996), 169–174.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Michael Carl Brown</author>
<author>R D</author>
</authors>
<title>Automated Dictionary Extraction for “Knowledge-Free” Example-Based Translation. TMI</title>
<date>1997</date>
<pages>111--118</pages>
<marker>Brown, D, 1997</marker>
<rawString>Michael Carl Brown, R. D. 1997. Automated Dictionary Extraction for “Knowledge-Free” Example-Based Translation. TMI (1997), 111–118.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>R D Brown</author>
</authors>
<title>Adding Linguistic Knowledge to a Lexical Example-based Translation System. TMI</title>
<date>1999</date>
<pages>22--32</pages>
<marker>Brown, 1999</marker>
<rawString>Brown, R. D. 1999. Adding Linguistic Knowledge to a Lexical Example-based Translation System. TMI (1999), 22–32.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<date>2003</date>
<booktitle>Recent Advances in Example-Based Machine Translation.</booktitle>
<editor>Carl, M. &amp; A. Way, editors.</editor>
<publisher>Kluwer, Academic Publisher,</publisher>
<location>Boston/Dordrecht/London.</location>
<note>in press.</note>
<marker>2003</marker>
<rawString>Carl, M. &amp; A. Way, editors. 2003. Recent Advances in Example-Based Machine Translation. Kluwer, Academic Publisher, Boston/Dordrecht/London. in press.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>M Carl</author>
</authors>
<title>Inducing translation grammars from bracketed alignments.</title>
<date>2003</date>
<booktitle>In (Carl &amp; Way,</booktitle>
<contexts>
<context position="5588" citStr="Carl, 2003" startWordPosition="960" endWordPosition="961">s deux côtés sont connectés grâce à un dictionnaire bilingue. All other sniper training is wasted if the sniper misses his target . If the target is missed, the mission is a failure. S’il rate sa cible , tout le reste de son instruction de tireur d’élite ne lui sert à rien, et la mission est un échec . 5.2.2 Détermination de correspondances phrase à phrase les plus significantes Les poids des correspondances des arbres sont calculés à partir (i) des poids et le nombre des ancres lexicales (ii) la fréquence des correspondances dans le texte et (iii) l’isomorphisme des analyses partielles (cf. (Carl, 2003)) other sniper training the sniper his target 2 2 2Ł 2 26 correspondances R des phrases sont FLM examinées 2  2 Ł 2 R)   Anglais Français F[F FLM ^_ 2   _ _ _ b 2   _ _ c 2  2Ł   F  2  M  ` M 2  F R) _ _ 2  _ _ _ 2  2  F[F F R _a  2 Ł  d F 2  FM F  F 2Ł   ^ 2  F  `  2Ł  F a 2     2  FXF FM F F[F F  F[F F 2Ł 2     2   FLM F    2 Ł   F F F 2 2     2   F ML F FM F  R  MXM M F le reste de son instruction de tireur d’élite Cet extrait d’alignement de la section 5.2.1 montre trois segments </context>
</contexts>
<marker>Carl, 2003</marker>
<rawString>Carl, M. 2003. Inducing translation grammars from bracketed alignments. In (Carl &amp; Way, 2003).</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>M Carl</author>
<author>P Langlais</author>
</authors>
<title>Tuning general purpose translation knowledge to a sublanguage.</title>
<date>2003</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of EAMT/CLAW.</booktitle>
<contexts>
<context position="7994" citStr="Carl &amp; Langlais, 2003" startWordPosition="1464" endWordPosition="1467"> . 3 other sniper training + reste de son instruction de tireur d’élite 4 -   -other   + reste de son  de  5 training + instruction 6 sniper + tireur d’élite 7 his target + sa cible 8 his - - + sa  9 the mission + la mission 10 the - - + la  11 mission + mission 12 a failure + un échec 13 - -a  + un  6 Expériences en traduction guidée par l’exemple Dans cette section nous générons des grammaires avec l’approche presenté en section 5. Un texte test est traduit avec EDGAR présenté en section 4. Une description plus étendue des expériences peut être trouvé dans (Carl &amp; Langlais, 2003). Les expériences se basent sur le Canadian Hansards, texte bilingue Anglais + Français. Nous présentons des expériences différentes d’extraction de grammaire aussi bien en ce qui concerne le nombre d’exemples que le degré d’ambiguı̈té de la grammaire générée. 6.1 Extraction d’une grammaire de traduction Les ressources utilisées pour extraire une grammaire de traduction (GT - ) Anglais + Français incluent un dictionnaire bilingue de 77.016 entrées, un programme de segmentation en segments et un ensemble de 50.000 exemples de traduction alignés du Canadian Hansard. Le dictionnaire couvre prèsqu</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Carl, Langlais, 2003</marker>
<rawString>Carl, M. &amp; Langlais, P. 2003. Tuning general purpose translation knowledge to a sublanguage. In Proceedings of EAMT/CLAW.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>M Carl</author>
</authors>
<title>Inducing Translation Templates for Example-Based Machine Translation. Machine Translation Summit VII,</title>
<date>1999</date>
<marker>Carl, 1999</marker>
<rawString>Carl, M. 1999. Inducing Translation Templates for Example-Based Machine Translation. Machine Translation Summit VII, Singapore, 250–258.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>M Carl</author>
<author>A Schmidt-Wigger</author>
</authors>
<title>Shallow Postmorphological Processing with KURD.</title>
<date>1998</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of NeMLaP3/CoNLL98,</booktitle>
<pages>257--265</pages>
<location>Sydney.</location>
<contexts>
<context position="2292" citStr="Carl &amp; Schmidt-Wigger, 1998" startWordPosition="402" endWordPosition="405">iques (p.ex. lu en bas). De plus, les traits peuvent être atomique disjonctifs (p.ex. case=d;g) ou comples disjonctifs. Par exemple, la représentation du mot allemand “der” porte les traits suivants: ^_ b _ ^_ b _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ lu=d_art,c=w,sc=art,fu=def _ _ _c lu=d_rel,c=w,sc=rel,fu=np, c ^_ b _c ^_ b _c ^_ b _c ^_ b _c ^_ b _c ` gen=f, gen=m, ` case=n, case=g;d, ` ` ` ` ` _ _ ; _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _a agr= _a nb=sg, _ __ ; _a nb=sg, _ ; _a nb=plu, _ _ _a agr= _a g=m, _ ; _a nb=sg, __ _ case=d;g d case=n d case=g d d nb=sg d g=f d d 4.3 Percoler des traits avec des règles KURD L’analyseur KURD (Carl &amp; Schmidt-Wigger, 1998) sert à percoler les traits dans les arbres de dérivation et à unifier et substituer des valeurs dans les noeuds. La règle NP monte l’information d’accord des noeuds terminaux dans le noeud père. NP = Aa ffi c=np ( [ Les opérations de KURD e ffi c=w,sc=art,agr=_AGR ( , # a ffi c=adj,agr=_AGR ( ,  Unification et suppression de traits. e e ffi c=noun,agr=_AGR (  ] Concaténation et substitution de valeurs.  Insertion et suppression de noeuds. : Au ffi agr=_AGR ( Michael Carl 5 Acquisition de grammaires de traduction 5.1 Propriétés des grammaires de traduction 5.1.1 Grammaire de traduction homo</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Carl, Schmidt-Wigger, 1998</marker>
<rawString>Carl, M. &amp; Schmidt-Wigger, A.. 1998. Shallow Postmorphological Processing with KURD. In Proceedings of NeMLaP3/CoNLL98, pages 257–265, Sydney.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>I Cicekli</author>
<author>H A Güvenir</author>
</authors>
<title>Learning Translation Templates from Bilingual Translation Examples.</title>
<date>2003</date>
<booktitle>In (Carl &amp; Way,</booktitle>
<marker>Cicekli, Güvenir, 2003</marker>
<rawString>Cicekli, I. &amp; H.A. Güvenir. 2003. Learning Translation Templates from Bilingual Translation Examples. In (Carl &amp; Way, 2003).</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>I Cicekli</author>
<author>H A Güvenir</author>
</authors>
<title>Learning Translation Rules From A Bilingual Corpus.</title>
<date>1996</date>
<booktitle>NeMLaP-2: Proceedings of the Second International Conference on New Methods in Language Processing,</booktitle>
<pages>90--97</pages>
<location>Ankara, Turkey,</location>
<marker>Cicekli, Güvenir, 1996</marker>
<rawString>Cicekli, I. &amp; H. A. Güvenir. 1996. Learning Translation Rules From A Bilingual Corpus. NeMLaP-2: Proceedings of the Second International Conference on New Methods in Language Processing, Ankara, Turkey, 90–97.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>B Collins</author>
<author>H Somers</author>
</authors>
<title>EBMT Seen as Case-based Reasoning.</title>
<date>2003</date>
<booktitle>In (Carl &amp; Way,</booktitle>
<marker>Collins, Somers, 2003</marker>
<rawString>Collins, B. &amp; H. Somers. 2003. EBMT Seen as Case-based Reasoning. In (Carl &amp; Way, 2003).</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>B Collins</author>
</authors>
<title>Example-Based Machine Translation: An Adaptation-Guided Retrieval Approach. PhD thesis,</title>
<date>1998</date>
<location>Trinity College, Dublin.</location>
<marker>Collins, 1998</marker>
<rawString>Collins, B. 1998. Example-Based Machine Translation: An Adaptation-Guided Retrieval Approach. PhD thesis, Trinity College, Dublin.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>B Collins</author>
<author>P Cunningham</author>
</authors>
<title>Adaptation Guided Retrieval: Approaching EBMT with Caution. TMI</title>
<date>1997</date>
<pages>119--126</pages>
<marker>Collins, Cunningham, 1997</marker>
<rawString>Collins, B. &amp; P. Cunningham. 1997. Adaptation Guided Retrieval: Approaching EBMT with Caution. TMI (1997), 119–126.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>L Cranias</author>
<author>H Papageorgiou</author>
<author>S Piperidis</author>
</authors>
<title>A Matching Technique in Example-Based Machine Translation. Coling</title>
<date>1994</date>
<pages>100--104</pages>
<marker>Cranias, Papageorgiou, Piperidis, 1994</marker>
<rawString>Cranias, L., H. Papageorgiou &amp; S. Piperidis. 1994. A Matching Technique in Example-Based Machine Translation. Coling (1994), 100–104.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>O Furuse</author>
<author>H Iida</author>
</authors>
<title>An Example-Based Method for Transfer-Driven Machine Translation. TMI</title>
<date>1992</date>
<pages>139--150</pages>
<marker>Furuse, Iida, 1992</marker>
<rawString>Furuse, O. &amp; H. Iida. 1992. An Example-Based Method for Transfer-Driven Machine Translation. TMI (1992), 139–150.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>O Furuse</author>
<author>H Iida</author>
</authors>
<title>Constituent Boundary Parsing for Example-Based Machine Translation. Coling</title>
<date>1994</date>
<pages>105--111</pages>
<marker>Furuse, Iida, 1994</marker>
<rawString>Furuse, O. &amp; H. Iida. 1994. Constituent Boundary Parsing for Example-Based Machine Translation. Coling (1994), 105–111.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>H A Güvenir</author>
<author>I Cicekli</author>
</authors>
<title>Learning Translation Templates from Examples.</title>
<date>1998</date>
<journal>Information Systems</journal>
<volume>23</volume>
<pages>353--363</pages>
<marker>Güvenir, Cicekli, 1998</marker>
<rawString>Güvenir, H. A. &amp; I. Cicekli. 1998. Learning Translation Templates from Examples. Information Systems 23, 353–363.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>H Kaji</author>
<author>Y Kida</author>
<author>Y Morimoto</author>
</authors>
<title>Learning Translation Templates from Bilingual Text. Coling</title>
<date>1992</date>
<pages>672--678</pages>
<marker>Kaji, Kida, Morimoto, 1992</marker>
<rawString>Kaji, H., Y. Kida &amp; Y. Morimoto. 1992. Learning Translation Templates from Bilingual Text. Coling (1992), 672–678.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>P Langlais</author>
</authors>
<title>Ressources terminologiques et traduction probabiliste: premiers pas positifs vers un système adaptatif.</title>
<date>2002</date>
<booktitle>In TALN-2002.</booktitle>
<contexts>
<context position="13120" citStr="Langlais, 2002" startWordPosition="2291" endWordPosition="2292">GT - GT  GT ¥ GT ¥ GT ¥  -  WER 71,91% 68,89% 66,93% 71,88% 69,75% 67,22% BLEU 0,1365 0,1421 0,1704 0,1398 0,1519 0,1706 #segments 3.581 4.405 4.685 3.599 4.314 4.659 #segments différents 992 1.279 1.387 1.055 1.343 1.450 #mots couverts 4.611 5.752 6.146 4.680 5.752 6.228 #segments longueur ¢ 2 767 966 1.050 816 1.032 1.108 #segments different 353 519 589 380 570 646 #mots couverts 1.952 2.652 2.863 2.170 2.844 3.062 6.4 Comparaison de GT, SMT et BabelFish Dans cette expérience nous comparons les résultats de traduction obtenus utilisant les grammaires GT 5 avec un système statistique (Langlais, 2002) entrainé sur les mêmes exemples de traduction ET 5 . Nous voyons que les résultats SMT sont inférieurs (toujours WER et BLEU) à ceux obtenus en GT. Le système SMT  qui a été entraı̂né sur un texte de 1,5 millions de exemples (15 fois plus que ET  ) obtient les meilleurs résultats. score GT  GT - GT  SMT  SMT - SMT  SMT  BabelFish BLEU 0,1365 0,1421 0,1704 0,1156 0,1231 0,1378 0,2061 0,1578 WER 71,91% 68,89% 66,93% 74,72% 73,54% 71,52% 61,66% 66,03% Le système commercial BabelFish obtient des résultats inférieurs à ceux de SMT  et GT  . Ceci est surtout dû aux particularités du te</context>
<context position="14489" citStr="Langlais, 2002" startWordPosition="2536" endWordPosition="2537">he speaker + le président” a été réalisée par GT et SMT alors que BabelFish génère la traduction “le haut-parleur”. De même : “some hon. members : oh , oh ! + des voix : oh , oh !” est une traduction qui se voit fréquemment en Canadian Hansards mais BabelFish produit “membres d’un certain hon : l’ OH OH”. Alors que ce sont des traductions possibles correctes dans d’autres contextes, elles sont erronées quant à la traduction du Canadian Hansards. La traduction guidée par l’exemple 6.5 Intégration SMT et GT Finalement nous essayons d’intégrer les grammaires GT et le système statistique suivant (Langlais, 2002) : quand la grammaire GT contient une entrée égale à une séquence de mots dans la phrase à traduire, le système SMT est forcé d’intégrer la traduction proposée par GT dans sa sortie. La qualité produite du système hybride est meilleure quant aux grammaires inverses (SMT 5 -GT 5 ); pour l’intégration des grammaires ambiguës dans le systeme statistique (SMT 5 -GT ¥ ) une amelioration des résultats n’a 5 pas pu être observé. SMT  -GT  SMT - -GT - SMT  -GT  SMT  -GT ¥ SMT - -GT ¥ SMT  -GT ¥  -  BLEU 0.1495 0.1684 0.1789 0.1406 0.1541 0.1654 WER 71.19% 70.32% 68.94% 72.70% 7</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Langlais, 2002</marker>
<rawString>Langlais, P. 2002. Ressources terminologiques et traduction probabiliste: premiers pas positifs vers un système adaptatif. In TALN-2002.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Y Matsumoto</author>
<author>M Kitamura</author>
</authors>
<title>Acquisition of Translation Rules from Parallel Corpora.</title>
<date>1995</date>
<booktitle>In R. Mitkov &amp; N. Nicolov (eds) Recent Advances in Natural Language Processing: Selected Papers from RANLP’95,</booktitle>
<pages>405--416</pages>
<location>Amsterdam: John Benjamins,</location>
<marker>Matsumoto, Kitamura, 1995</marker>
<rawString>Matsumoto, Y. &amp; M. Kitamura. 1995. Acquisition of Translation Rules from Parallel Corpora. In R. Mitkov &amp; N. Nicolov (eds) Recent Advances in Natural Language Processing: Selected Papers from RANLP’95, Amsterdam: John Benjamins, 405–416.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>K McTait</author>
<author>A Trujillo</author>
</authors>
<title>A Language-Neutral Sparse-Data Algorithm for Extracting Translation Patterns. TMI</title>
<date>1999</date>
<booktitle>In (Carl &amp; Way,</booktitle>
<marker>McTait, Trujillo, 1999</marker>
<rawString>McTait, K. &amp; A. Trujillo. 1999. A Language-Neutral Sparse-Data Algorithm for Extracting Translation Patterns. TMI (1999), 98–108. La traduction guidée par l’exemple Menezes, A. &amp; S.D. Richardson. 2003. A best-first alignment algorithm for automatic extraction of transfer mappings from bilingual corpora. In (Carl &amp; Way, 2003).</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>A Meyers</author>
<author>R Yangarber</author>
<author>R Grishman</author>
<author>C Macleod</author>
<author>A Moreno-Sandeval</author>
</authors>
<title>Deriving Transfer Rules from Dominance-Preserving Alignments. Coling-ACL</title>
<date>1998</date>
<pages>843--847</pages>
<marker>Meyers, Yangarber, Grishman, Macleod, Moreno-Sandeval, 1998</marker>
<rawString>Meyers, A., R. Yangarber, R. Grishman, C. Macleod &amp; A. Moreno-Sandeval. 1998. Deriving Transfer Rules from Dominance-Preserving Alignments. Coling-ACL (1998), 843–847.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>M Nagao</author>
</authors>
<title>A Framework of a Mechanical Translation between Japanese and English by Analogy Principle.</title>
<date>1984</date>
<booktitle>In A. Elithorn and R. Banerji (eds) Artificial and Human Intelligence,</booktitle>
<publisher>North-Holland.</publisher>
<location>173–180, Amsterdam:</location>
<marker>Nagao, 1984</marker>
<rawString>Nagao, M. 1984. A Framework of a Mechanical Translation between Japanese and English by Analogy Principle. In A. Elithorn and R. Banerji (eds) Artificial and Human Intelligence, 173–180, Amsterdam: North-Holland.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>S Nirenburg</author>
<author>S Beale</author>
<author>C Domashnev</author>
</authors>
<title>A Full-Text Experiment</title>
<date>1994</date>
<booktitle>in Example-Based Machine Translation. International Conference on New Methods in Language Processing (NeMLaP),</booktitle>
<pages>78--87</pages>
<location>Manchester, England,</location>
<marker>Nirenburg, Beale, Domashnev, 1994</marker>
<rawString>Nirenburg, S., S. Beale &amp; C. Domashnev. 1994. A Full-Text Experiment in Example-Based Machine Translation. International Conference on New Methods in Language Processing (NeMLaP), Manchester, England, 78–87.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>K Papineni</author>
<author>S Roukos</author>
<author>T Ward</author>
<author>W-J Zhu</author>
</authors>
<title>Bleu: a method for automatic evaluation of machine translation.</title>
<date>2002</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the 40th Annual Meeting of the ACL,</booktitle>
<pages>311--318</pages>
<location>Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, USA,</location>
<contexts>
<context position="9888" citStr="Papineni et al., 2002" startWordPosition="1763" endWordPosition="1766">15 23.675 #mots different 7.688 7.714 #mots/exemples 17,76 18,94 %anchors (en ET - ) 42,28% 43,53% Grammaire de traduction extraite GT - : Segments générés par le parser partiel : #règles lexicales 113.810 #segments 581,599 650,136 #schémas de traduction 70.153 #segments différents 180,006 226,339 6.2 Traduction d’un texte test (TT) Un texte test de 500 phrases est traduit de l’anglais vers le français avec les règles lexicales de GT - . Alors que la couverture du dictionnaire bilingue (DIC) est plus grande que celle de la grammaire GT - , la qualité de traduction, mesurée en WER1 et en BLEU (Papineni et al., 2002), est mieux en traduction GT - . Nous voyons ici une corrélation entre la qualité des traductions et la longueur des segments utilisés lors de la traduction. Texte Test (TT) GT - DIC Anglais Français %mots couverts 66,38% 66,99% #exemples 500 500 BLEU 0,1421 0,0573 #mots 8.665 9.806 WER 68,89% 81,68% #mots/exemples 17,33 19,61 longueur segments ¢¤£ #segments 966 146 #mots couverts 2,652 325 %mots couverts 30,61% 3,75% 6.3 Echelonnement de grammaires inverses et ambiguës Dans cette expérience nous étudions (i) la capacité de l’algorithme d’utiliser un nombre différent d’exemples de traduction e</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Papineni, Roukos, Ward, Zhu, 2002</marker>
<rawString>Papineni, K., S. Roukos, T. Ward, &amp; W.-J. Zhu. 2002. Bleu: a method for automatic evaluation of machine translation. In Proceedings of the 40th Annual Meeting of the ACL, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, USA, 311–318.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>S D Richardson</author>
<author>W B Dolan</author>
<author>A Menezes</author>
<author>J Pinkham</author>
</authors>
<title>Achieving Commercial-quality Translation with Example-based Methods.</title>
<date>2001</date>
<booktitle>MT Summit VIII: Machine Translation in the Information Age,</booktitle>
<location>Santiago de Compostela,</location>
<marker>Richardson, Dolan, Menezes, Pinkham, 2001</marker>
<rawString>Richardson, S.D., W.B. Dolan, A. Menezes &amp; J. Pinkham. 2001. Achieving Commercial-quality Translation with Example-based Methods. MT Summit VIII: Machine Translation in the Information Age, Santiago de Compostela, Spain, 293–298.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>S Sato</author>
<author>M Nagao</author>
</authors>
<title>Toward Memory-Based Translation. Coling</title>
<date>1990</date>
<volume>3</volume>
<pages>247--252</pages>
<marker>Sato, Nagao, 1990</marker>
<rawString>Sato, S. &amp; M. Nagao. 1990. Toward Memory-Based Translation. Coling (1990), Vol. 3, 247–252.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>H Somers</author>
</authors>
<title>Review Article: Example-based Machine Translation.</title>
<date>1999</date>
<journal>Machine Translation,</journal>
<volume>14</volume>
<issue>2</issue>
<marker>Somers, 1999</marker>
<rawString>Somers, H. 1999. Review Article: Example-based Machine Translation. Machine Translation, 14(2):113–157.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>H Somers</author>
</authors>
<title>An Overview of EBMT.</title>
<date>2003</date>
<booktitle>In (Carl &amp; Way,</booktitle>
<marker>Somers, 2003</marker>
<rawString>Somers, H. 2003. An Overview of EBMT. In (Carl &amp; Way, 2003).</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>E Sumita</author>
<author>H Iida</author>
</authors>
<date>1991</date>
<booktitle>Experiments and Prospects of Example-Based Machine Translation. 29th Annual Meeting of the Association for Computational Linguistics,</booktitle>
<pages>185--192</pages>
<location>Berkeley, California,</location>
<marker>Sumita, Iida, 1991</marker>
<rawString>Sumita, E. &amp; H. Iida. 1991. Experiments and Prospects of Example-Based Machine Translation. 29th Annual Meeting of the Association for Computational Linguistics, Berkeley, California, 185–192.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>E Sumita</author>
<author>H Iida</author>
<author>H Kohyama</author>
</authors>
<title>Translating with Examples: A New Approach to Machine Translation. TMI</title>
<date>1990</date>
<pages>203--212</pages>
<marker>Sumita, Iida, Kohyama, 1990</marker>
<rawString>Sumita, E., H. Iida &amp; H. Kohyama. 1990. Translating with Examples: A New Approach to Machine Translation. TMI (1990), 203–212.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>B Vauquois</author>
</authors>
<title>A Survey of Formal Grammars and Algorithms for Recognition and Transformation</title>
<date>1968</date>
<booktitle>in Machine Translation. IFIP Congress-68, Edinburgh, 254–260; reprinted in Ch. Boitet (ed.) Bernard Vauquois et la TAO: Vingt-cinq Ans de Traduction Automatique – Analectes,</booktitle>
<pages>201--213</pages>
<publisher>Association Champollion.</publisher>
<location>Grenoble</location>
<marker>Vauquois, 1968</marker>
<rawString>Vauquois, B. 1968. A Survey of Formal Grammars and Algorithms for Recognition and Transformation in Machine Translation. IFIP Congress-68, Edinburgh, 254–260; reprinted in Ch. Boitet (ed.) Bernard Vauquois et la TAO: Vingt-cinq Ans de Traduction Automatique – Analectes, 201–213, Grenoble (1988): Association Champollion.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>T Veale</author>
<author>A Way</author>
</authors>
<title>Gaijin: A Bootstrapping Approach to Example-Based Machine Translation.</title>
<date>1997</date>
<booktitle>International Conference, Recent Advances in Natural Language Processing, Tzigov Chark, Bulgaria,</booktitle>
<pages>239--244</pages>
<marker>Veale, Way, 1997</marker>
<rawString>Veale, T. &amp; A. Way. 1997. Gaijin: A Bootstrapping Approach to Example-Based Machine Translation. International Conference, Recent Advances in Natural Language Processing, Tzigov Chark, Bulgaria, 239–244.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>H Watanabe</author>
</authors>
<title>A Similarity-Driven Transfer System. Coling</title>
<date>1992</date>
<pages>770--776</pages>
<marker>Watanabe, 1992</marker>
<rawString>Watanabe, H. 1992. A Similarity-Driven Transfer System. Coling (1992), 770–776.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>H Watanabe</author>
</authors>
<title>A Method for Extracting Translation Patterns from Translation Examples. TMI</title>
<date>1993</date>
<pages>292--301</pages>
<marker>Watanabe, 1993</marker>
<rawString>Watanabe, H. 1993. A Method for Extracting Translation Patterns from Translation Examples. TMI (1993), 292–301.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>H Watanabe</author>
<author>K Takeda</author>
</authors>
<title>A Pattern-Based Machine Translation System Extended by ExampleBased Processing. Coling-ACL</title>
<date>1998</date>
<pages>1369--1373</pages>
<marker>Watanabe, Takeda, 1998</marker>
<rawString>Watanabe, H. &amp; K. Takeda. 1998. A Pattern-Based Machine Translation System Extended by ExampleBased Processing. Coling-ACL (1998), 1369–1373.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>A Way</author>
</authors>
<title>A Hybrid Architecture for Robust MT using LFG-DOP.</title>
<date>1999</date>
<journal>Journal of Experimental and Theoretical Artificial Intelligence</journal>
<volume>11</volume>
<pages>441--471</pages>
<marker>Way, 1999</marker>
<rawString>Way, A. 1999. A Hybrid Architecture for Robust MT using LFG-DOP. Journal of Experimental and Theoretical Artificial Intelligence 11, 441–471.</rawString>
</citation>
</citationList>
</algorithm>
</algorithms>