<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<algorithms version="110505">
<algorithm name="ParsCit" version="110505">
<citationList>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>N AUSSENAC-GILLES</author>
<author>A CONDAMINES</author>
<author>S SZULMAN</author>
</authors>
<title>Prise en compte de l’application dans la constitution de produits terminologiques.</title>
<date>2002</date>
<booktitle>In Actes des 2e Assises Nationales du GDR I3,</booktitle>
<pages>289--302</pages>
<marker>AUSSENAC-GILLES, CONDAMINES, SZULMAN, 2002</marker>
<rawString>AUSSENAC-GILLES N., CONDAMINES A. &amp; SZULMAN S. (2002). Prise en compte de l’application dans la constitution de produits terminologiques. In Actes des 2e Assises Nationales du GDR I3, p. 289–302.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>BEIJING UNIVERSITY ICL</author>
</authors>
<date>2001</date>
<note>PFR china daily corpus.</note>
<contexts>
<context position="14483" citStr="ICL, 2001" startWordPosition="2182" endWordPosition="2183">e recherche initiale et en décrivant le processus de construction des lexies. 2Dans la suite de l’article, le terme « lexie » sera utilisé pour désigner un « mot-forme ou syntagme lexicalisé représentant d’une lexie » lorsque nous parlerons des lexies découvertes dans le texte. Extraction de lexique dans un corpus spécialisé en chinois contemporain 4.1 Description des corpus Le corpus de référence contient 2 millions de graphies. Il est composé de deux corpus de chinois contemporain : The Lancaster Corpus of Mandarin Chinese (McEnery &amp; Xiao, 2004) et PFR China Daily corpus (Beijing University ICL, 2001) tous deux annotés selon la norme de l’Université de Beijing3. Il nous a servi à recueillir toutes les informations lexicales nécessaires à notre méthode. En nous basant sur ces annotations, nous avons extrait un lexique de référence d’environ 75 000 lexies, une liste des mots-vides et une liste des bigrammes syntaxiques (voir 4.2.3). Le corpus de test est un corpus de documents commerciaux de compagnies d’assurance publiés sur leur site internet. Il est composé de dix millions de caractères. Il a été recueilli automatiquement à partir d’une liste d’adresses de sites de compagnies d’assurance </context>
</contexts>
<marker>ICL, 2001</marker>
<rawString>BEIJING UNIVERSITY ICL (2001). PFR china daily corpus.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>J CHANG</author>
<author>K SU</author>
</authors>
<title>An unsupervised iterative method for Chinese new lexicon extraction.</title>
<date>1997</date>
<booktitle>In Computational Linguistics, Computational Linguistics,</booktitle>
<pages>22--29</pages>
<marker>CHANG, SU, 1997</marker>
<rawString>CHANG J. &amp; SU K. (1997). An unsupervised iterative method for Chinese new lexicon extraction. In Computational Linguistics, Computational Linguistics, p. 22–29.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>K W CHURCH</author>
<author>P HANKS</author>
</authors>
<title>Word association norms, mutual information and lexicography.</title>
<date>1997</date>
<booktitle>In M. PRESS, Ed., Computational Linguistics,</booktitle>
<volume>16</volume>
<pages>22--29</pages>
<marker>CHURCH, HANKS, 1997</marker>
<rawString>CHURCH K. W. &amp; HANKS P. (1997). Word association norms, mutual information and lexicography. In M. PRESS, Ed., Computational Linguistics, volume 16, p. 22–29.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>P DROUIN</author>
</authors>
<title>Spécificités lexicales et acquisition de la terminologie.</title>
<date>2004</date>
<booktitle>In JADT 2004 : 7ème Journées internationales d’Analyse statistique des Données Textuelles,</booktitle>
<pages>345--352</pages>
<marker>DROUIN, 2004</marker>
<rawString>DROUIN P. (2004). Spécificités lexicales et acquisition de la terminologie. In JADT 2004 : 7ème Journées internationales d’Analyse statistique des Données Textuelles, p. 345–352.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>H FENG</author>
<author>K CHEN</author>
<author>X DENG</author>
<author>W ZHENG</author>
</authors>
<title>Accessor variety criteria for Chinese word extraction.</title>
<date>2004</date>
<booktitle>In ACL,</booktitle>
<volume>30</volume>
<pages>75--93</pages>
<location>Cambridge.</location>
<marker>FENG, CHEN, DENG, ZHENG, 2004</marker>
<rawString>FENG H., CHEN K., DENG X. &amp; ZHENG W. (2004). Accessor variety criteria for Chinese word extraction. In ACL, volume 30, p. 75–93, Cambridge.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>P FUNG</author>
<author>D WU</author>
</authors>
<title>Statistical augmentation of a Chinese machine-readable dictionary.</title>
<date>1994</date>
<booktitle>In WVLC-94, Second Annual Workshop on Very Large Corpus.</booktitle>
<marker>FUNG, WU, 1994</marker>
<rawString>FUNG P. &amp; WU D. (1994). Statistical augmentation of a Chinese machine-readable dictionary. In WVLC-94, Second Annual Workshop on Very Large Corpus.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>M-C L’HOMME</author>
<author>A POLGUÈRE</author>
</authors>
<title>Mettre en bons termes les dictionnaires spécialisés et les dictionnaires de langue générale. In Lexicologie et terminologie: histoire de mots. Colloque en l’honneur d’Henri Béjoint,</title>
<date>2008</date>
<pages>191--206</pages>
<location>Lyon.</location>
<marker>L’HOMME, POLGUÈRE, 2008</marker>
<rawString>L’HOMME M.-C. &amp; POLGUÈRE A. (2008). Mettre en bons termes les dictionnaires spécialisés et les dictionnaires de langue générale. In Lexicologie et terminologie: histoire de mots. Colloque en l’honneur d’Henri Béjoint, p. 191–206, Lyon.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>H LI</author>
<author>C HUANG</author>
<author>J GAO</author>
<author>X FAN</author>
</authors>
<title>The use of SVM for Chinese new word identification.</title>
<date>2004</date>
<booktitle>In IJCNLP 2004, First International Joint Conference,</booktitle>
<pages>723--732</pages>
<marker>LI, HUANG, GAO, FAN, 2004</marker>
<rawString>LI H., HUANG C., GAO J. &amp; FAN X. (2004). The use of SVM for Chinese new word identification. In IJCNLP 2004, First International Joint Conference, p. 723–732.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>T MCENERY</author>
<author>R XIAO</author>
</authors>
<title>The Lancaster corpus of Mandarin Chinese.</title>
<date>2004</date>
<marker>MCENERY, XIAO, 2004</marker>
<rawString>MCENERY T. &amp; XIAO R. (2004). The Lancaster corpus of Mandarin Chinese.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>I MEL’CUK</author>
</authors>
<title>Cours de morphologie générale introduction et première partie : Le mot, volume 1. Les presses de l’université de Montréal - CNRS Edition.</title>
<date>1993</date>
<marker>MEL’CUK, 1993</marker>
<rawString>MEL’CUK I. (1993). Cours de morphologie générale introduction et première partie : Le mot, volume 1. Les presses de l’université de Montréal - CNRS Edition.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>H NAKAGAWA</author>
<author>H KOJIMA</author>
<author>A MAEDA</author>
</authors>
<title>Chinese term extraction from Web pages based on compound word productivity.</title>
<date>2004</date>
<booktitle>In Third SIGHAN Workshop on Chinese Language Processing,</booktitle>
<pages>79--85</pages>
<location>Barcelona,</location>
<marker>NAKAGAWA, KOJIMA, MAEDA, 2004</marker>
<rawString>NAKAGAWA H., KOJIMA H. &amp; MAEDA A. (2004). Chinese term extraction from Web pages based on compound word productivity. In Third SIGHAN Workshop on Chinese Language Processing, p. 79–85, Barcelona, Spain.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>E V T NGUYEN</author>
</authors>
<title>Unité lexicale et morphologie en chinois mandarin vers l’élaboration d’un DEC du chinois.</title>
<date>2006</date>
<tech>PhD thesis,</tech>
<institution>Université de Montréal.</institution>
<marker>NGUYEN, 2006</marker>
<rawString>NGUYEN E. V. T. (2006). Unité lexicale et morphologie en chinois mandarin vers l’élaboration d’un DEC du chinois. PhD thesis, Université de Montréal.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>S S PIAO</author>
<author>G SUN</author>
<author>P RAYSON</author>
<author>Q YUAN</author>
</authors>
<title>Automatic extraction of Chinese multiword expressions with a statistical tool.</title>
<date>2006</date>
<booktitle>In Workshop on Multi-word-expressions in a Multilingual Context held in conjunction with the 11th EACL 2006,</booktitle>
<location>Trento, Italy.</location>
<marker>PIAO, SUN, RAYSON, YUAN, 2006</marker>
<rawString>PIAO S. S., SUN G., RAYSON P. &amp; YUAN Q. (2006). Automatic extraction of Chinese multiword expressions with a statistical tool. In Workshop on Multi-word-expressions in a Multilingual Context held in conjunction with the 11th EACL 2006, Trento, Italy.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>A POLGUÈRE</author>
</authors>
<title>Lexicologie et sémantique lexicale. Notions fondamentales. Université de Montréal.</title>
<date>2003</date>
<marker>POLGUÈRE, 2003</marker>
<rawString>POLGUÈRE A. (2003). Lexicologie et sémantique lexicale. Notions fondamentales. Université de Montréal.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>U QUASTHOFF</author>
<author>C WOLFF</author>
</authors>
<title>The Poisson collocation measure and its application.</title>
<date>2002</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the 20th international conference on Computational Linguistics.</booktitle>
<marker>QUASTHOFF, WOLFF, 2002</marker>
<rawString>QUASTHOFF U. &amp; WOLFF C. (2002). The Poisson collocation measure and its application. In Proceedings of the 20th international conference on Computational Linguistics.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>R SPROAT</author>
<author>T EMERSON</author>
</authors>
<title>The first international Chinese word segmentation bakeoff.</title>
<date>2003</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the Second SIGHAN Workshop on Chinese Language Processing.</booktitle>
<marker>SPROAT, EMERSON, 2003</marker>
<rawString>SPROAT R. &amp; EMERSON T. (2003). The first international Chinese word segmentation bakeoff. In Proceedings of the Second SIGHAN Workshop on Chinese Language Processing.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>M SUN</author>
<author>D SHEN</author>
<author>B K TSOU</author>
</authors>
<title>Chinese word segmentation without lexicon and hand-crafted training data.</title>
<date>1998</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of ACL,</booktitle>
<pages>1265--1271</pages>
<marker>SUN, SHEN, TSOU, 1998</marker>
<rawString>SUN M., SHEN D. &amp; TSOU B. K. (1998). Chinese word segmentation without lexicon and hand-crafted training data. In Proceedings of ACL, p. 1265–1271.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>A WU</author>
<author>Z JIANG</author>
</authors>
<title>Statistically-enhanced new word identification in a rule-based Chinese system.</title>
<date>2000</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the 2nd Chinese Language Processing Workshop,</booktitle>
<volume>12</volume>
<pages>46--51</pages>
<publisher>ACL.</publisher>
<location>Hong Kong:</location>
<marker>WU, JIANG, 2000</marker>
<rawString>WU A. &amp; JIANG Z. (2000). Statistically-enhanced new word identification in a rule-based Chinese system. In Proceedings of the 2nd Chinese Language Processing Workshop, volume 12, p. 46–51, Hong Kong: ACL.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>W YANG</author>
<author>X LI</author>
</authors>
<title>Chinese keyword extraction based on max-duplicated strings of the documents.</title>
<date>2002</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the 25th Annual International ACM,</booktitle>
<pages>439--440</pages>
<marker>YANG, LI, 2002</marker>
<rawString>YANG W. &amp; LI X. (2002). Chinese keyword extraction based on max-duplicated strings of the documents. In Proceedings of the 25th Annual International ACM, p. 439–440.</rawString>
</citation>
</citationList>
</algorithm>
</algorithms>